<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f008"/>
<ab>
    <lb/><!-- Following transcription is partial. TEI by KAB to see if adding attributes to persName tags will work, and to test centering text, etc. -->
        <figure rend="middle-top">
        <figDesc>
            <head>THE LIFE OF</head>
        </figDesc>
        <lb/>
            <persName ref="#ortelius">
                ABRAHAM ORTELL
            </persName>,
        <lb/>COSMOGRAPHER TO 
            <persName ref="#philipII">
                PHILIP
            </persName> THE
        <lb/>SECOND, LATE KING OF SPAINE,
        <lb/>written first in Latine by 
            <persName ref="#francisSweert">
                <hi rend="italic"> Francis Sweert </hi> 
            </persName> of Antwerpe, his familiar
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">and louing friend, and now translated into English by</hi>
        <lb/>
            <persName>W.B.</persName>, <hi rend="italic">as great a louer of his learning 
        <lb/>and vertues</hi>.
        </figure>
        
        <lb/>THe stocke of the ORTELS flourished not long since, and liued in good state and credit at
        <lb/><placeName ref="#ausburg">Ausburg</placeName> in <placeName ref="#bayern">Bayern</placeName>, (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Augustam vindelicorum</hi></foreign>, the Latines called it.) From that family came
        <lb/><persName ref="#ortelius">WILLIAM ORTELL</persName>, who about the yere of our Lord <date>1360</date> left his natiue country, and where he did many notable things worthily deseruing great commendation: among which 
        <lb/>that is most memorable, that of his owne proper cost and charges he caused a goodly crosse
        <lb/>of free stone to be set vp without the Emperours gate, in that place where the malefactours
        <lb/>are vsusually woont to be executed and put to death. Beneath this crosse, at the base or foot
        <lb/>of the same, stood Mary and Iohn, and beside them, a little farther off, hung the two theeues, the one vpon the 
        <lb/>right hand and the other vpon the left, vpon thier seuerall gibbets. This <persName ref="#ortelius" style="font-style: italic;">William</persName> died on the <date>seuenth day of Ia-
        <lb/>nuary</date> in the yeere of our Lord God <date>1511</date>, and was buried in the cloisters of the Franciscane Friers in Antwerpe,
        <lb/>leauing his sonne <persName ref="#leonardOrtell">LEONARD ORTELL</persName> sole Exeutor, and heire, not only of his goods and substance, but also
        <lb/>of his vertues and good qualities: for they report that he was a man so deuout and religious, that it was an hard 
        <lb/>matter to finde him from his booke, serious meditation on heauly matters.
        
        <lb/>Transcription to be continued.
</ab>

</div></body></text>