<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f016"/>
<respStmt><!--I, Meghan Spargo, transcribed and tagged Seq.17 of this text.--> </respStmt>
<ab>
    <head>
        <lb/>A DESCRIPTION OF THE
        <lb/>WHOLE WORLD.
    </head>
</ab>
<ab>
    <lb/> 
    <lb/>THIS Map next ensuing containeth and representeth the portraiture of the whole earth,
    <lb/>and of the maine Ocean that enuirons &amp; compasseth the same: all which earthly Globe
    <lb/>the Ancients (who were not as then acquainted with the New world, not long since de-
    <lb/>scried) diuided into three parts; namely, <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#africa">Africa</placeName></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName></hi>. But since that discouery
    <lb/>of <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#america">America</placeName></hi>, the learned of our age haue made that a fourth part, and the huge Continent
    <lb/>vnder the <placeName ref="#southPole">South pole</placeName>, a fifth, <hi rend="italic"><persName ref="#gerardusMercator">Gerardus Mercator</persName></hi> the Prince of modern Geographers in his
    <lb/>neuer-sufficiently-commended vniuersall Table or Map of the whole world, diuides this
    <lb/>Circumference of the earth into three Continents: the first he calles that, which the Anci-
    <lb/>ents diuided into three parts, and from whence the holy Writ beares record, that mankind had their first origi-
    <lb/>nall, &amp; first was seated: the second, is that which at this present is named <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#america">America</placeName></hi> or the <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#westIndies">VVest Indies</placeName></hi>: for the third,
    <lb/>he appoints the <placeName ref="#southMaine">South maine</placeName>, which some call <hi rend="italic"><placeName ref="#magellanica">Magellanica</placeName></hi>, as yet on very few coasts thorowly discouered. That
    <lb/>this orbe or masse of the earthly Globe contains in circuit, where it is largest, 5400 German or 21600 Italian
    <lb/>miles, antiquity hath taught, &amp; late Writers haue subscribed to their opinion. <hi rend="italic">And these so manifold portions of earth</hi>
    <lb/>(sayth <hi rend="italic"><persName ref="#plinie">Plinie</persName></hi> in the 11. booke of his Naturall historie) <hi rend="italic">yea rather, as some haue termed them, the pricke or center of the world
    <lb/>(for so small is the earth in comparison of the whole frame of the world) this is the matter, this is the seat of our glorie. Here we enioy
    <lb/>honours, here we exercise authoritie, here we hunt after riches, here men turmoile and tire themselues, here we moue and maintaine ciuill
    <lb/>dissensions, and by mutuall slaughter make more roome vpon the earth. And to let passe the publike tumults of the world, this in which
    <lb/>we force the borderers to giue place and remoue farther off, and where we incroch by stelth vpon our neighbors lands: as he that extends
    <lb/>his lands &amp; lordships farthest, and cannot abide that any should seat themselues too neere his nose, How great, or rather how small a por-
    <lb/>tion of earth doth he enioy? Or when he hath glutted his auarice to the full, How little shall his dead carcase possesse?</hi> Thus far <hi rend="italic"><persName ref="#plinie">Plinie</persName>.</hi>
    <lb/>
    <lb/>The situation of this earth and sea, the disposition of the seuerall regions, with their inlets and gulfs, the maners and inclinations of the people, and other memorable and note-worthy matters are described by men of ancienter times, such as follow:
    <lb/>
    <lb/>
</ab>

</div></body></text>