<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f018"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--We, Audrey Gauthier and Haley Jensen, transcribed and encoded seq 19 of this text at Framingham State University.--></personalstmt>
<lb/><figure rend="middle-top">
    <figDesc><head><placeName ref="#europe">EVROPE</placeName></head></figDesc>
</figure>
<lb/>
<p>
    <lb/>In the diuision of the world, diuers haue placed <placeName ref="#africa">Africa</placeName> in the third part : some few haue made no more but <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> and <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> only ; and <placeName ref="#africa">Africa</placeName> they make a part of <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>, saith <persName ref="#salustius">Salustius</persName>. This is that which <persName ref="#stPaulinus">S. Paulinus</persName> in <placeName ref="#aulonius">Aulonius</placeName>, out o
    <lb/> the opinion of the same Saluit, thus writeth of : <foreign xml:lang="la">Europam Afiamque duo vel maxima terrae Membra, quibus Lybiam
    <lb/>dubie Sallustius addit, Europæ admixtram : poffit quum tertia dici</foreign> : <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> and <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> vast, the Earthly globe between 
    <lb/>them share. Yet whether <placeName ref="#africa">Africke</placeName> should a part of this our <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> be ; or make a third part by it selfe, Saluit doth doubt 
    <lb/>I see. But <persName ref="#philostratus">Philostratus</persName> also in <persName ref="#isocrates">Isocrates</persName> doth diuide the world into <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> and <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> : yea <persName ref="#isocrates">Isocrates</persName> himself, in his Pane-
    <lb/>gyricos. Moreouer in <persName ref="#varro">Varroes</persName> booke <foreign xml:lang="la">De lingua Latina</foreign> these words are read ; As all the world is diuided into <placeName ref="#heaven">Heaven</placeName>
    <lb/>and <placeName ref="#earth">Earth</placeName> : so <placeName ref="#heaven">Heaven</placeName> is seuered into his quarters : and the <placeName ref="#earth">Earth</placeName> into <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> and <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>. Againe the same author in his 
    <lb/>booke of Husbandrie writeth thus : first, when as the world, by <persName ref="#eratosthenes">Eratosthenes</persName>, was very fully and naturally divided into 
    <lb/>two parts, the one toward the South, <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> doubtlesse he meaneth the other in the north <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> we call it. <persName ref="#stAugustine">S. Augu-
    <lb/>stine</persName> in his 16. booke <foreign xml:lang="la">De Ciuitate Dei</foreign> : <persName ref="#lucane">Lucane</persName> in his 9. booke: and <persName ref="#orosius">Orosius</persName> in the first booke of his history, haue the like
    <lb/>wordes to the same sense. Notwithstanding custome since hath preuailed with all historiographers and cosmographers which haue written either in Latine 
    <lb/>or Greeke, ioinly to diuide the globe of the earth into these three parts: <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName>, <placeName ref="#africa">Africke</placeName> and <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>: the last of which we have taken vpon vs to describe in 
    <lb/>this place, not only in forme of a mappe or chart, like a Geographer: but in this present discourse, like an historian. Concerning the forme of it therefore, it 
    <lb/>is manifold, as <persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName> writeth. It is a Peninsula or demy-isle, and not an island; although <persName ref="#silenus">Silenus</persName>, as <persName ref="#elianus">Elianus</persName> writeth, did sometime to <persName ref="#midas">Midas</persName> so relate of
    <lb/>it. For it is on all sides, as you may see in the mappe, bounded and beaten with the salt sea, but only upon the East, where it is by a small necke ioined to the 
    <lb/>greater <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName>. Yet by what limits they are there distinguished, the ancient and the later writers do not altogether agree. For those which are more ancient 
    <lb/>as <persName ref="#aristotle">Aristotle</persName>, <persName ref="#plato">Plato</persName>, <persName ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</persName>, and others which do follow their opinion, do diuide <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> from <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName>, by the riuer <placeName ref="#phasis">Phasis</placeName>, (a riuer of Colchis falling 
    <lb/>into the <placeName ref="#euxineSea">Euxine sea</placeName>, <placeName ref="#marMaiore">Mar Maiore</placeName>, or <foreign xml:lang="la">Maurothalassa</foreign>, as the greeks call it) neere <placeName ref="#trapezonda">Trapezonda</placeName> : some mappes do now call that riuer <placeName ref="#fasso">Fasso</placeName>, others <placeName ref="#phazzeth">Phaz-
    <lb/>zeth</placeName>: the Scythians, (as <persName ref="#thevet">Theuet</persName> reporteth, Debbaffethca) or which is all one, by that ithmos or neckland which is between the forefaid <placeName ref="#marMaiore">Mar Maiore</placeName> or 
    <lb/><placeName ref="#pontusEuxinus">Pontus Euxinus</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Caspian sea</placeName> (<placeName ref="#marDeCachu">Mar de Cachu</placeName>, the ancient called it <placeName ref="#mareHyrcanum">Mare Hyrcanum</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#hyrcanianSea">Hyrcanie sea</placeName>) which formerly all old writers thought to 
    <lb/>be but a bay or gulfe of the Scythian or Northren ocean, as <persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName>, <persName ref="#pliny">Pliny</persName>, <persName ref="#mela">Mela</persName>, <persName ref="#dionysiusF">Dionysius</persName>, <persName ref="#plutarch">Plutarch</persName> (in the life of <persName ref="#alexander">Alexander</persName> and in his discourse of the 
    <lb/>face in the sphere of the Moone) and <persName ref="#iornandes">Iornandes</persName> a more late writer, have first recorded. Yet all of them were deceiued. Only <persName ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</persName> truly (as this 
    <lb/>our latter age doth approve and find to be so) doth affirme this to be a sea of it selfe, and to have neither in-let nor out-let, or to be intermeddled with any other 
    <lb/>sea. <persName ref="#dionysiusF">Dionysius</persName>, <persName ref="#arrianus">Arrianus</persName>, <persName ref="#diodorus">Diodorus</persName>, <persName ref="#polybius">Polybius</persName>, <persName ref="#iornandes">Iornandes</persName> and <persName ref="#ptolemy">Ptolemey</persName> have diuided it from <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> by the riuer <placeName ref="#tanais">Tanais</placeName> (<placeName ref="#don">Don</placeName> or <placeName ref="#tana">Tana</placeName>, as now the 
    <lb/>Italians name it) who think that both the rise of this riuer, and the land Northward from where it commeth, are both unknown and uncertaine. All 
    <lb/>doubt where to place and lay their bounds : as indeed who never perfectly knew those places toward the East and North, not being then discovered, but only 
    <lb/>described by them, from the fabulous reports of others: as for example, the <placeName ref="#riphaean">Riphæan</placeName> and <placeName ref="#hyperborean">Hyperboræan</placeName> mountaines, which are fained inventions of the 
    <lb/>Greekes, as <persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName> writeth: together with <placeName ref="#aluaniMontes">Aluani montes</placeName>, heere described by <persName ref="#ptolemy">Ptolemey</persName>, where not only these mountaines, but also no other at this 
    <lb/>day, are to be seene: but in their places diuers huge and vast woods, great fennes and bogges, or large champion plaines. <persName ref="#orpheus">Orpheus</persName> also long since described 
    <lb/>in this part of the continent I meane, between <placeName ref="#maeotisPalus">Mæotis palus</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#fenneMaeotis">fenne Mæotis</placeName>, (now called <placeName ref="#marDelleZabbache">Mar delle Zabbache</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#mardellaTana">Mardella Tana</placeName>) and the <placeName ref="#croniumSea">sea
    <lb/>Cronium</placeName>, an huge wood. Likewise, <persName ref="#dionysiusF">Dionysius</persName> after heereabouts placeth an infinite wood, as he termeth it, from whence he saith <placeName ref="#tanais">Tanais</placeName> or <placeName ref="#don">Don</placeName> doth
    <lb/>spring, which after many windings and turnings at last falleth into the forenamed <placeName ref="#fenneMaeotis">fenne Maeotis</placeName>. <persName ref="#isidorus">Isidorus</persName> heere hath the <placeName ref="#riphaeanWoods">Riphaean woods</placeName>, in which he
    <lb/>saith <placeName ref="#tanais">Tanais</placeName> doth first take the beginning. That <placeName ref="#danube">Donaw</placeName> (Danubis) doth diuide <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> from <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>, <persName ref="#seneca">Seneca</persName> in the sixth booke Naturall doth manifestly
    <lb/>affirm; of which his opinion, what do we thinke, we will, God willing, set downe in the discourse to the Mappe of <placeName ref="#dacia">Dacia</placeName>. Hitherto we see the forenamed au-
    <lb/>thours to doubt and disagree between themselues of the limits of these two parts of the world: if therefore they shall find me a meet vmpier and arbitratour
    <lb/>in this matter, I would, not vnfitly, and as I hope to the liking of all parties, decide the controuer thus: I would make the bounds to be <placeName ref="#tanais">Tanais</placeName>, or the ri-
    <lb/>uer <placeName ref="#don">Don</placeName>; the straits or narrow peece of the maine land that is between the riuer and the <placeName ref="#rha">riuer Rha</placeName> (Athel), which emptyeth it selfe into the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Caspian sea</placeName>:
    <lb/>the East branch of the same Athel: then from his head vnto the <placeName ref="#oby">riuer Oby</placeName>, and so even vnto his mouth or fall into the <placeName ref="#northSea">Northren sea</placeName>: For by this mouth, I
    <lb/>do easily perswade my selfe, that antiquity did verily beleeue that the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Caspian sea</placeName> did vnlade it selfe into the maine Ocean. For that the name of this <placeName ref="#oby">riuer O-
    <lb/>by</placeName> is ancient, it is very likely, for that <placeName ref="#montesObij">montes Obij</placeName>, certain mountaines called <placeName ref="#obij">Obij</placeName> are placed heere about in this tract, by <persName ref="#athenaeus">Athenaeus</persName>, which he saith for-
    <lb/>merly were called of the ancient <placeName ref="#montesRiphæi">montes Riphæi</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#riphaeanHills">Riphaean hils</placeName>: but then in his daies <placeName ref="#montesAlpes">montes Alpes</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#alpes">Alpes</placeName>. Againe <persName ref="#iornandes">Iornandes</persName> in this continent,
    <lb/>not farre from hence, describeth Ovim or Obim, a Scythian nation or family. And that these foresaid mountaines are in this place (not where <persName ref="#ptolemy">Ptolemey</persName>
    <lb/>and <persName ref="#pomponiusMela">Pomponius Mela</persName> haue placed them) very many men of great credit and learning in these our daies, sufficient witnesses do stoutly auouch. Amongst
    <lb/>which <persName ref="#herberstein">Baro Herberstein</persName>, in his history of <placeName ref="#moscovy">Moscouy</placeName>, is one: <persName ref="#paulOderborne">Paul Oderborne</persName>, in his treatise written of the life of <persName ref="#basilides">Bafilides</persName>, is another: lastly, <persName ref="#antonyWied">Antony
    <lb/>Wied</persName>, in his mappe of <placeName ref="#moscovy">Moscouy</placeName> may be the third. Now they name it vulgarly by diuers and sundrie names, but commonly they call it <placeName ref="#cingulumMundi">Cingulum mundi</placeName>,
    <lb/>The girdle of the world, as the said <persName ref="#herberstein">Herberstein</persName> doth affirme. In a mappe of these countries set out by <persName ref="#jenkinson">Master Jenkinson</persName>, an Englishman, who travelled
    <lb/>through these parts, it is called <placeName ref="#zonaOrbis">Zona Orbis</placeName>, The girdle of the Earth. Moreouer I haue in some sort for this diuision, <persName ref="#iornandes">Iornandes</persName> and <persName ref="#aethicus">AEthicus</persName>, upon my 
    <lb/>side, where they say that the <placeName ref="#ripheanMontes">Riphean mountaines</placeName> do part <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> and <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>. Againe these selfe same hils, yea, and in this tract, are the <placeName ref="#montesHyperborei">montes Hyperbo-
    <lb/>rei</placeName>; not where <persName ref="#ptolemy">Ptolemey</persName> placeth them. And they are the same with montes <placeName ref="#riphæi">Riphæi</placeName>, <placeName ref="#obij">Obij</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#alpes">Alpes</placeName>. Thus farre of the diusion of <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> from <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>.
</p>
<lb/>
<p>
    <persName ref="#pliny">     Pliny</persName> calleth this part of the world, The Nurce of all Nations; <persName ref="#mardonius">Mardonius</persName>, as <persName ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</persName> doth tell of him, auoucheth it to <persName ref="#xerxes">Xerxes</persName>, to be by farre 
    <lb/>the beautifulleft of all places of the World, to be a most goodly and gallant country, yielding all maner of fruits and fruitfull trees and those
    <lb/>in their kindes and best; and to be such that it were pity that any king in the World should haue ought to do in but he. <persName ref="#varro">Varro</persName> in his bo kes <foreign xml:lang="la">Dere 
    <lb/>Rustica</foreign>, of Husbandrie writeth, That it is a more temperate and healthful soile than <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName>. <persName ref="#statius">Statius</persName> in his Achilleidos, more than once or twice, calleth
    <lb/>it, The Mighty prouince of the World. <foreign xml:lang="la">Maximaterra viris &amp; fœcundissima doctis Vrbibus</foreign>, <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> for multitude of warlike men and scholers 
    <lb/>deeply learned, doth farre excell thus <persName ref="#mamilius">Mamilius</persName> writeth of it. <persName ref="#aristotle">Aristotle</persName>, the prince of Philospophers, maketh the inhabiters of this part of the world, to be, 
    <lb/>A very stout and couragious people. The same authour affirmeth, that, All kind of beasts and cattell heere, are in their kind, greater, and stronger 
    <lb/>than in <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> and <placeName ref="#africa">Africke</placeName>. But of the nature of this country, the maners and customes of the people, let vs heare what <persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName> that excellent Geographer saith
    <lb/>in his second book ; This part is most fertile of valiant and prudent men. It is all generally habitable, excepting only a very small portion toward 
    <lb/>the North, and abutting vpon the Hamaxici, which dwell vpon <placeName ref="#tanais">Tanais</placeName>, <placeName ref="#don">Don</placeName> Meo'is Palus (<placeName ref="#marDelleZabbache">Mar delle Zabacche</placeName>) and <placeName ref="#borysthenes">Borysthenes</placeName> (<placeName ref="#nieper">Nieper</placeName> or
    <lb/><placeName ref="#dnester">Dnester</placeName>) which place, by reason of the extream cold, is not habitable. Yet certaine bleake and mountainous places inhabited, although in re-
    <lb/>spect of the nature of the soile they are tilled and manured with greater difficulty, yet having gotten good skilull and industrious husbands,
    <lb/>those also are tamed and much bettered, which heeretofore were badly vsed, and kept only by theeues and out-lawes. And indeed the Greekes
    <lb/>when they dwelt vpon the rocks and mountaines, dwelt well and conueniently, by reason of their wise cariage in ciuill matters, arts, sciences and 
    <lb/>knowledge of those things, which necessarily are required to the maintenance of mans life. In like maner the Romanes, hauing brought many 
    <lb/>sauage and fierce Nations vnder their seruile yoke, seated, I meane, in places not very conuenient to dwell in, in respect of the nature of the coun- 
    <lb/>try, either for that it was rough and craggy, or wanted hauens, or was too bleake and cold, or for other causes, taught them to vse merchandise
    <lb/>before vnknowen, and haue brought them from a sauage and brutish life, to live ciuilly and more humanely. But those parts which are situate in
    <lb/>an equall and temperat climate, there nature administreth all things necessary for the maintenance of man and beast. Now when as those Nations
    <lb/>which do inhabite and dwell in fertile and rich countries, are maintainers of peace and quietnesse ; and those which are seated in barren and vn-
    <lb/>fruitfull countries, are most hardy and stout : it commeth to passe that both are helpfull one to another ; while these do vse their weapons for 
    <lb/>their countries defence, those againe do help and maintaine them by the profits that they raise out of the earth, by their arts and mysteries, as also
    <lb/>by their learning, wisedome and policy : euen as in like maner also the dammage is mutuall and either side feeleth a sensible hurt, when the one
    <lb/>part doth not helpe the other : yet the estate of the souldier and warlike man is somewhat better, if they be not ouercome with multitude. And
    <lb/>the nature of <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> serueth very fitly for this purpose : for it is all diuersly distinguished by lofty mountaines and lowly plaines ; so that euery
    <lb/>where the husbandmen and soldiers ; the politicians and the martiall warriers do dwell together : yet so as the greatest number are peaceable
    <lb/>men : which kind of life they enjoy especially by the meanes and labour of their captaines, first of the Greekes, then of the Macedonians, and
    <lb/>lastly of the Romanes. Therefore both in peace and warre it is sufficient of itselfe to maintaine and defend itselfe : for it hath great plenty both
    <lb/>of stout soldiers, painfull husbandmen, and politique statesmen. In this also it doth excel, that it bringeth foorth passing good fruits, such I
    <lb/>meane, as are necessary for the maintenance of mans life: with all sorts of mettall, for what vse soeuer. Spices or sweet smelling things and preti- 
    <lb/>ous stones, are brought hither from forren countries, WHICH THINGS WHOSOEVER HAVE NOT, THEY LIVE NEVER A WHIT 
    <lb/>WORSE THAN THOSE DO THAT HAVE THEM. Moreouer this is especially worth the noting, that hauing wonderfull store of cattell, 
    <lb/>sheep and oxen ; it breedeth very few dangerous wild beasts. Thus farre the learned <persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName>. Many other things thou maist read of this <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>,
    <lb/>together with the nature and condition of the people of the same, in that treatise which <persName ref="#hippocrates">Hippocrates</persName>, the prince of Physitions, wrote of the aire and waters.
    <lb/>This <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> also, and not any other place of the world beside, doth yeeld Succinum or Electrum, (Amber we call it, the Germanes, Glessum) yet it is not 
    <lb/>found in <placeName ref="#eridianus">Eridianus</placeName>, a river falling into some Northren sea, as <persName ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</persName> doth fabulously report : or in <placeName ref="#padus">Padus</placeName>, a riuer of Italy (Po) as the poets iestingly af-
    <lb/>firme: nor in the Electrides, certaine fained ilands in the <placeName ref="#hadriatic">Hadriaticke sea</placeName>, as some men of better credit, and more diligent searchers out of the <supplied reason="illegible">t</supplied>ruth, as <persName ref="#pliny">Pliny</persName>
</p>
</ab>


</div></body></text>