<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f021"/>
<ab> 
<personalstmt><!--Transcribed and encoded by Nicholas Vitale and Karolina Rosberg--></personalstmt>
<lb/><figure rend="middle-top"><placeName ref="#asia">ASIA</placeName></figure>
<lb/>
<lb/><placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> diuides it selfe from <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> by the river <placeName ref="#tanais">Tanais</placeName>, and a streight line drawen
<lb/>from the fountaines thereof to the <placeName ref="#bayStNicolas">Bay of S. Nicolas</placeName> in the <placeName ref="#northOcean">North Ocean</placeName>:
<lb/>but from <placeName ref="#africa">Africa</placeName>, by the neck-land Ifthmos or narrow place of the earth, which
<lb/>in betweene the <placeName ref="#arabianGulf">Arabian gulfe</placeName> and the <placeName ref="#mediterraneanSea">Mediterran sea</placeName>. The residue thereof the
<lb/>Ocean and other seas do enuiron.
<lb/>
<lb/>This part the ancient Geographers, as <persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName> in his eleuenth booke, and <persName ref="#arrianus">Ar-
<lb/>rianus</persName> in his fift booke, haue dinersly divided. But at this present it may be us not altogether un-
<lb/>fitly be distributed into fine parts, according to the great Empires by which it is gouerned. The first
<lb/>whereof, which bordereth upon <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>, and is subiect to the great <persName ref="#dukeMoscovia">Duke of Mofcouia</persName>, is bounded
<lb/>by the Frozen sea, the riuer <placeName ref="#ob">Ob</placeName>, the lake <placeName ref="#kitaia">Kitaia</placeName>, and a line drawen from thence to the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Caspian sea</placeName>,
<lb/>and by the Isthmus or neck-land between the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Caspian</placeName> and <placeName ref="#euxinSea">Euxin seas</placeName>. The second is that, which
<lb/>yields obedience to the great <persName ref="#greatCham">Cham Emperour</persName> of the <placeName ref="#tartars">Tartars</placeName>, whole Southern borders are the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Caspi-
<lb/>an sea</placeName>, the riuer <placeName ref="#iaxartes">Iaxartest</placeName>, and mount <placeName ref="#imaus">Imaus</placeName>; on the East and North it is begirt with the Ocean;
<lb/>and Westward it confines vpon the dominions of the foresaid great <persName ref="#dukeRussia">Duke of Russia</persName>. The third part,
<lb/>the progeinie of the Ottomans or the <persName ref="#turkishEmperor">Turkish Emperour</persName> enioyes, which containeth whatsoeuer re-
<lb/>gions are situate within the compasse of the <placeName ref="#euxinSea">Euxin sea</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#aegeanSea">aegean sea</placeName> (now called Arcipelago)
<lb/>and the <placeName ref="#mediterraneanSea">Mediterranean sea</placeName>, the land of <placeName ref="#egypt">Egypt</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#arabian">Arabian</placeName> and <placeName ref="#persianSea">Persian seas</placeName>, the riuer <placeName ref="#tigris">Tigris</placeName>, the <placeName ref="#caspianSea">Ca-
<lb/>spian sea</placeName>, and the Isthmos or neck-land between it and the sea <placeName ref="#euxinSea">Euxine</placeName>. Vnder the fourth shalbe com-
<lb/>prised the <placeName ref="#kingdomPersia">Kingdome of Persia</placeName>, now gouerned by the Sophies; Westward it hat the <note type="group of people">Turkes</note>, with
<lb/>whom the Persian for the most part manteineth continuall warres; Northward the Empire of the
<lb/><persName ref="#greatCham">great Cham</persName>; Eastward it extends almost to the riuer <placeName ref="#indus">Indus</placeName>; and on the south it is restrained by the
<lb/>sea, at this present called <placeName ref="#indicum">Indicum</placeName>, but in times past <placeName ref="#mareRubrum">Mare Rubrum</placeName>, or <placeName ref="#redSea">The Red sea</placeName>. Now the
<lb/>sift part takes vp all that remaineth, which as in times past, so at this present, is called <placeName ref="#theIndies">The Indies</placeName>;
<lb/>neither is it gouerned by one only, as the former; but by many pety Kings, euery region almost hauing
<lb/>a peculiar Gouernour, some which are tributarie to the <persName ref="#greatCham">great Cham</persName>. And here it is not to be omitted,
<lb/>that all the sea-coasts from the <placeName ref="#arabianGulf">Arabian gulfe</placeName>, to the <placeName ref="#promontoryChina">Promontory of China</placeName>, commonly called <placeName ref="#caboDeLampo">Cabo
<lb/>de Lampo</placeName>, situate in 30. degrees of Northerly latitude, are in a maner possessed, or made tributary
<lb/>to the <placeName ref="#portugals">Portugals</placeName>. 
<lb/>
<lb/>Amongst infitinte others, the princpall isles ascribed to <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName>, are <placeName ref="#cyprus">Cyprus</placeName> and <placeName ref="#rhodes">Rhodes</placeName> in the
<lb/><placeName ref="#mediterraneanSea">Mediterran</placeName> sea; <placeName ref="#zeilan">Zeilan</placeName> of the vulgar and <placeName ref="#taprobana">Taprobana</placeName> well knowen to the ancients now called <placeName ref="#samotra">Sa-
<lb/>motra</placeName>, but falsly <placeName ref="#sumatra">Sumatra</placeName>, in the <placeName ref="#indickOcean">Indick-Ocean</placeName>, where also within the memory of our fathers, the
<lb/><placeName ref="#portugals">Portugals</placeName> haue discouered the two <placeName ref="#javas">Iauas</placeName>, with the isles of <placeName ref="#borneo">Borneo</placeName>, <placeName ref="#celebes">Celebes</placeName>, <placeName ref="#palohan">Palohan</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#mindanao">Min-
<lb/>danao</placeName>; and here likewise <placeName ref="#gilolo">Gilolo</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="#moluccos">Moluccos</placeName>, at this day famous for abundance of spi-
<lb/>ces which they yeeld. To these may be added the isles of <placeName ref="#japan">Iapan</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#newGuinie">new Guinie</placeName> very lately descried;
<lb/>but this last, whether it be an island, or adioyned to the <placeName ref="#southMaine">South maine</placeName>, it is not yet Certainly knowen.
<lb/>
<lb/>The memorie of this part of the world is most renowmed, not only with prophane authors (as they 
<lb/>terme them) in regard of the first monarchies established by the Assyrians, the Persians, the Babylo-
<lb/>nians, and the Medes; but in the holy Scriptures also it is more famous than the rest: for here man-
<lb/>kinde was not only created by almightie God, deluded and corrupted by the enemie Satan, and resto-
<lb/>red by our Saviour Christ; but we finde almost all the hestories in either Testament to haue beene in
<lb/>this part both written and accomplished.
<lb/><persName ref="#strabo">Strabo</persName> hath described Asia in six books, namely from the 11. booke vnto the 16. <persName ref="#ptolemy">Ptolomey</persName> hath
<lb/>decyphered the fame in three, as in his 5. 6. And 7. books; and likewise in 12. Geographicall Tables,
<lb/>and ascribes unto it 40. prouinces. It is also let foorth by <persName ref="#ammianusMarcellinus">Ammianus Marcellinus</persName> in his 23.
<lb/>booke, and by <persName ref="#diodorusSiculus">Diodorus Siculus</persName> in the beginning of his 18. Of late Writers none haue wholly and
<lb/>particularly described it. <persName ref="#paulusVenetus">M. Paulus Venetus</persName>, <persName ref="#lewesBarthema">Lewes of Barthema</persName>, and <persName ref="#johnMandeville">St. Iohn Mandeuile</persName>,
<lb/>(but this Authour is fraught with fables) haue written so much thereof, as by trauelling the regions,
<lb/>they found worthie of obseruation. Reade also the Epistle of <persName ref="#iacobusNauarca">Iacobus Nauarca</persName> a Fesuite.
<lb/>        I my selfe likewise certaine yeeres past set forth a large Map the description of the same.
</ab>


</div></body></text>