<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f023"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--Transcribed and Encoded by Avery Slavin--></personalstmt>This the Ancients have diuersly distinguished; but at this present it is divided by <persName>John Leo</persName> of
<lb/> <placeName>Africa</placeName>, into foure chiefe parts; <placeName>Barbaria</placeName>, <placeName>Numidia</placeName>, <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and the Land of Negros. <placeName>Barbarie</placeName>, 
<lb/>which is accounted the best, they circumscribe with the <placeName>Atlantick</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Mediterranean seas</placeName>; with 
<lb/>mount Atlas, &amp; whither region of Barca bordering upon <placeName>Ægypt</placeName>. <placeName>Numidia</placeName>, called by the 
<lb/>inhabitants Biledulgerid, and abounding with Dates (for which cause the Arabians call it by no 
<lb/>other name, but the Date-bearing region) is bounded Westward by the <placeName>Atlantick Ocean</placeName>; 
<lb/>Northward by mount Atlas; it stretcheth East as farre as the citie <placeName>Caphsa</placeName>, which is an hundred &amp; 
<lb/>fiftie miles distant from <placeName>Ægypt</placeName>; and the sande <placeName>Deserts of Libya</placeName> embrace it on the South. <placeName>Libya</placeName>
<lb/>the third part, is named in the Arabian tongue Sura, which word signifies a Desert. It begins East 
<lb/>from <placeName>Nilus</placeName>, and thence runneth West as farre as the <placeName>Atlantick sea</placeName>; <placeName>Numidia</placeName> lies to the North of it, 
<lb/>and the Land of Negros to the South. Now followeth the fourth part, which they call <placeName>Nigritarum</placeName> or 
<lb/><placeName>Nigritania</placeName>, either from the inhabitants, who are of a blacke colour, or from the <placeName>river Niger</placeName>, that 
<lb/>runneth thorow the countrey. It is bounded by <placeName>Libya</placeName>, South by the <placeName>Æthiopick Ocean</placeName>; West by 
<lb/><placeName>Guinee</placeName>, and East by the <placeName>Kingdome of Gago</placeName>. And here we are to note, that according unto their 
<lb/>division, all <placeName>Africa</placeName> is included within the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>, <placeName>Atlantick</placeName>, and <placeName>Æthiopick</placeName> seas and the 
<lb/><placeName>river Nilus</placeName>; whereof <placeName>Ægypt</placeName> and <placeName>Abassia</placeName> are accounted parts of it, which we not unworthily 
<lb/>therefore proper to belong to <placeName>Africa</placeName>. For the true <placeName>Africa</placeName> containes at this day <persName>Prester Johns</persName> 
<lb/>Empire, which by all late Writers is ascribed to <placeName>Africa</placeName>. Wherefore with Ptolomy indeed it ought to 
<lb/>be bound by the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName> and Ocean seas, rather than by any river whatsoever; and 
<lb/>it hath the forme of a Peninsula, being joined toward <placeName>Asia</placeName> by an Isthmos of small neck-land, 
<lb/>which lies between the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName> and the <placeName>gulf of Arabia</placeName>. The South part hereof was 
<lb/>unknowne to our ancestors, till the yeere <date when="1497">1497</date>, whereas Vasco de Gama first doubling the <placeName>Cape 
<lb/>of Bona Speranza</placeName>, and passing about all <placeName>Africa</placeName>, came to <placeName>Calecut in East India</placeName>. This Southerne 
<lb/>part by the Persians and Arabians is called <placeName>Zangibar</placeName>.
<lb/>At the fore-sayd Cape of good hope the inhabitants are exceeding blacke; which we thought in 
<lb/>no wise to omit, because all men suppose the cause of blacknesse to be heat, and the 
<lb/>nearnesse of the Sunne; whereas the Sunne of it selfe forceth no more, than about the Streight 
<lb/>of <placeName>Magellan</placeName> (we measure the heat of the place, according to the position of the heavens and 
<lb/>distance from the Equinoctiall line) were now notwithstanding the people are reported to be 
<lb/>marvellous white. But if we will needs ascribe this blacknesse to the scorching of the Sun, let us 
<lb/>consider, that the same makes the Spaniards and Italians looke white; whereas they are equally 
<lb/>distant from the Equinoctiall with the inhabitants of the fore-sayd Cape; namely the one towards 
<lb/>the South, and the other towards the North. <persName>Prester Johns</persName> people are of a browne colour; in 
<lb/><placeName>Zanel</placeName> and <placeName>Mollala</placeName> the inhabitants are cole blacke, yet all in one &amp; the same distance from the 
<lb/>equator, and under the very same parallell of the heavens. And on the contrary, why did 
<lb/><persName>Herodotus</persName> and <persName>Pindarus</persName> describe such as inhabite the same climate with themselves, namely 
<lb/>Colches, to be a blacke people, and curled haired? <persName>Herodotus</persName> in his Thalia makes the Indians 
<lb/>blacke like the Æthiopians; which the experience of our times confirmeth. I know <persName>Herodotus</persName> will 
<lb/>have the cause hereof to be the seede of the parents, which he sayth is not whiter, than of other 
<lb/>people, but blacke. To whom Possidonius also subscribeth, and imputeth the matter of all this 
<lb/>blacknesse unto Canicular heate, against which opinion I have nothing to allege. Let the truth of 
<lb/>the matter rest upon the authors credit. But this as many men thinke more strange; that in all 
<lb/><placeName>America</placeName> there were no black people found besides a few only in one place called by them 
<lb/><placeName>Quarequa</placeName>. What then is the efficient cause of this colour? Is it the drinesse of the heavens, or of 
<lb/>the earth? is it perhaps some hidden propriety of the soile? Or a kind of fat licentious nature in 
<lb/>the nature of men? Or is it all these variances in one? But these things we leave to be 
<lb/>considered by them, who more curiously search into the secrets of nature.
<lb/>This portion of the world is called by the Greeks <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and by the Latines <placeName>Africa</placeName>, because it is 
<lb/>not moistened with extremity of cold: or (if we may credit some) of Afer one of the adventurers 
<lb/>posterity. Another derivation of the name you have (set downe by <persName>John Leo</persName> in the description of 
<lb/>his booke of the Description of <placeName>Africa</placeName>), who deriveth it from one blacke African, springing of the 
<lb/>stocke of Cham, who first inhabited that part of the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName>, from <placeName>Atlas</placeName>, bounded by 
<lb/>the <placeName>river Nilus</placeName>, or rather as the best authors have taught us, the African soile called of the 
<lb/>Greekes Aphrice, Marce rubrum, and red sea. <persName>Herodotus</persName> reporteth, that <placeName>Africa</placeName> was first 
<lb/>unknowne till <persName>Cesars</persName> time, when it was found to be a third part of the inhabited world. Plinie the 
<lb/>like, and so doth Solinus. <persName>Caesar Scaliger</persName> gathereth of the word <placeName>Africa</placeName>, that it is a name of the 
<lb/>same import with aprica, that is, a sunne-shining place; for that this land lying open on every 
<lb/>side to the Sunnes visitation, seemed thereby to have beene named so little other than of 
<lb/>apricity. The principall regions of <placeName>Africa</placeName> have amongst themselves (as it were) a threefold 
<lb/>division: first, from <placeName>Atlas</placeName> in the West to the red sea and <placeName>Arabia</placeName>, whence it took the name of the 
<lb/>first inhabiters, or else from the colour of the people, for the most part blacke and duskie; the 
<lb/>second, to wit, the inner part of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, from <placeName>Nilus</placeName> to the <placeName>Kingdome of Congo</placeName>, is more temperate, 
<lb/>and not so much subject to the Sunnes heate; the third, which is next unto the <placeName>South Pole</placeName>, by 
<lb/>reason of the obliquity of the Zodiack, is more temperate than the former. The islands that 
<lb/>belong to <placeName>Africa</placeName> (some of which are expressed in the table) are <placeName>Madagascar</placeName>, <placeName>the Canaries</placeName>, the 
<lb/><placeName>Isles of Cape Verde</placeName>, and <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> situated under the equinoctiall, which aboundeth with 
<lb/>fruits.
<lb/>Among the ancient Writers none have particularly described this region. But concerning the 
<lb/>same saith Isidore in his Etymologies; <persName>Hanno</persName> his navigation about <placeName>Africa</placeName>, in diversities; and 
<lb/><persName>Iambulus</persName> his voyages, in Diodorus Siculus; and likewise <persName>Herodotus</persName> his Melpomene. 
<lb/><persName>Bartholomeus de Glanvilla</persName> in his Image of the World reporteth the like. Of late Writers reade 
<lb/>also the Commentaries of <persName>Vasco de Gama</persName>, <persName>Franciscus Alvares</persName>, who travelled <placeName>Æthiopia</placeName>. But of 
<lb/>all others <persName>John Leo</persName> hath most exactly described it; as also <persName>Andrew Thevet</persName>, and <persName>Francis Alvarez</persName>, 
<lb/>both travellers of <placeName>Africa</placeName>. Concerning the <placeName>river Nilus</placeName>, the greatest in all the world, you have the 
<lb/>letters of <persName>John Ramusio</persName> and <persName>Jerome Fracastorius</persName>. Of <placeName>Africa itself</placeName>, as by me read at large in the 
<lb/>second volume of <persName>Mr. Richard Hakluyts</persName> English Voyages.
</ab>

</div></body></text>