<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f031"/>
<ab>
<personalstmt> <!--Transcribed and encoded by Tyrell Fuller. --> </personalstmt>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top">The Prouince of <placeName ref="#CVLIACAN">CVLIACAN</placeName></fw>
<lb/>THis Prouince of <placeName ref="#CVLIACAN">CVLIACAN</placeName> is part of the kingdome of <placeName ref="#New Galicia">New Galicia</placeName>. It was discouered
<lb/>vnder the gouernment of [Charles the fifth], in the year <date when="1530">1530</date>. In this region is one only colonie
<lb/>of Spaniards called, The towne of <placeName ref="#S. Michael. Villages">S. Michael. Villages</placeName> here are very many, bujlt by the
<lb/>inhabitants; all which before the Spaniards arriuall were at their own libertie: yeelding obedience
<lb/>to no King or Gouernour. The region is indifferently furnished with things necessary. Out of the
<lb/>mountaines is digged great abundance of siluer. The inhabitants are addicted to war and robbery.
<lb/>They that dwell vpon the coast, employ most of their time in fishing; but the vplandish people
<lb/>liue by hunting. They goe naked, couering only their priuities with a piece of Cotton. They haue
<lb/>many languages. They lodge for the most part in the open air. They are the most beggerly nation
<lb/>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top"><placeName ref="#CVBA">CVBA</placeName> and <placeName ref="#HISPANIOLA">HISPANIOLA</placeName></fw>
<lb/>THis Island of <placeName ref="#Cuba">Cuba</placeName> is so called by the naturall inhabitants; but by the Spaniards <placeName ref="#Fernandina">Fernandina</placeName>
<lb/>and <placeName ref="#Joanna">Joanna</placeName>; and (as <persName ref="#Peter">Peter</persName> Martyr reports) Alpha and Omega. In length it extendeth East and
<lb/>West 300 Spanish leagues. The land is very mountainous, but rich of gold, and excellent copper.
<lb/>Madder, which the Apothecaries, because it is very apt to die wooll and leather, call Diers
<lb/>madder, is heere found in great abundance. It is in all places beautified with thicke woods, with
<lb/>riuers and pooles of fresh water : albeit there are lakes naturally salt. The woods breed vp
<lb/>Hogges and Kine in great plentie : the riuers sometimes yeeld grains of gold. It contains fix
<lb/>colonie or townes of Spaniards : the principall whereof called <placeName ref="#Sant Jago">Sant Jago</placeName>, is the feat of a Bishop.
<lb/>But <placeName ref="#Hauana">Hauana</placeName> is the chiefe mart and hauen towne of all the Isle. Two wonderfull things
<lb/><persName ref="#Gousaluo de Ouiedo">Gousaluo de Ouiedo</persName> describes in this Isle : one, a valley extended betweene two mountaines
<lb/>some three Spanish miles in length : (the Ancients would haue named it, as in <placeName ref="#Gallia Narbonenst">Gallia
<lb/>Narbonenst</placeName>, the now called <placeName ref="#Prouence">Prouence</placeName>, The stony field) which bringeth forth round stones in so
<lb/>great abundance, that a man may lade whole shippes with them, being by nature framed so
<lb/>exactly round, that no Turner can amend them. The other is a mountaine not farre from the sea,
<lb/>whereout issueth a kind of Bitumen or Pitch in so great a quantity, that it runnes into the sea, and
<lb/>there floats farre and wide, according as it is carried by the waues or windes. This Pitch, they say,
<lb/>is very commodious for the calcking and braying of ships. <placeName ref="#HISPANIOLA">HISPANIOLA</placeName> lies to the East of
<lb/><placeName ref="#Cuba">Cuba</placeName>. This Isle by the first inhabitants was called <placeName ref="#Quisqueya">Quisqueya</placeName>, afterwards <placeName ref="#Haiti">Haiti</placeName> and
<lb/><placeName ref="#Cipanga">Cipanga</placeName> likewise. But the Spaniards name it <placeName ref="#Hispaniola">Hispaniola</placeName>, and (of the principall city)
<lb/><placeName ref="#SanDomingo">San Domingo</placeName>. The compasle here of is; 50 leagues. It is an Isle rich in Sugar, and it hath many Gold
<lb/>mines. It is very strange that is reported concerning a little flie very common in this Island, called
<lb/>by the inhabitants <placeName ref="#Cucuyo">Cucuyo</placeName>, and as big almost as one of the ioynts of a mans finger, hauing foure
<lb/>wings, two very thin, and the other two greater and harder, wherewith the thin ones are couered.
<lb/>This shineth in the night as glowe-wormes doe with vs. The force of this light is not only in his
<lb/>eyes, sparckling like fire, but also in his sides, so that by lifting vp his wings, he shines more
<lb/>flying, than when he lies still. By the naturall curtesie of this little creature, all their chambers,
<lb/>they say, are so lightsome euen in the darkest nights, that a man may reade and write very plainly
<lb/>without the helpe of any other light. This light of theirs is augmented by their number ; so that
<lb/>many will giue a greater light than a few. Whoso deires a larger description of these Islands, let
<lb/>him reade the history of the New world written by <persName ref="#Jerome Benzo">Jerome Benzo</persName>, <persName ref="#Peter">Peter</persName> Martyr his Decads of
<lb/>Islands lately discouered, and other writers of <placeName ref="#America">America</placeName>.
</ab>

</div></body></text>