<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription">
<body><div>
    <pb facs="#f000"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.1
</ab>

<pb facs="#f001"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.2
</ab>

<pb facs="#f002"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.3
</ab>

<pb facs="#f003"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.4
</ab>

<pb facs="#f004"/>
<ab>
<lb/>THEA
<lb/>TRVM
<lb/>ORBIS
<lb/>TERRA
<lb/>RVM
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>ABRAHAMI ORTELI ANTVERP.
<lb/>GEOGRAPHI REGII.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>THE THEATRE OF THE WHOLE
<lb/>WORLD: SET FORTH BY THAT
<lb/>Excellent Geographer Abraham Ortelius.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>LONDON,
<lb/>Printed by IOHN NORTON; Printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie in 
<lb/>Hebrew, Greeke, and Latine. 1606.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f005"/>
<ab>
<lb/>The sway, by Sea &amp; Land, grat IAMES doth beare,
<lb/>His Birth, His Bloud, These Kingdomes figure here:
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>But, were his seuerall vertues to be crown'd
<lb/>A World, past thine, Ortelius, must be found.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f006"/>
<ab>
<lb/>ABRAHAMI ORTELII
<lb/>QVEM VRBS VRBIVM ANTVERPIA EDITIT,
<lb/>REX REGVM PHILLIPVS GEOGRAPHVM HABVIT,
<lb/>MONVMENVM HIC VIDES.
<lb/>BREVIS TERRA EVM CAPTIT
<lb/>QVI IPSE ORBEM TERRARVM CEPIT,
<lb/>QVI IPSE ORBEM TERRARVM CEPTIT,
<lb/>STILO ET TABVLIS ILLVSTRAVIT:
<lb/>SED MENTE CONTEMPSIT,
<lb/>QVA CAELVM ET ALTA SVSPEXIT
<lb/>CONSTANS ADVERSVM SPES AVT METVS.
<lb/>AMICITIAE CVLTOR, CANDORE FIDE, OFFICIIS,
<lb/>QVIETIS CVLTOR, SINE LITE, VXORE, PROLE.
<lb/>VITAM HABVIT, QVALE ALIVS, VOTVM.
<lb/>VT NVNC QVOQVE AETERNA EI QVIES SIT
<lb/>VOTIS FAVE LECTOR.
<lb/>OBIIT IIII.KAL. IVLII. ANNO CIƆ.XCIIX.
<lb/>VIXIT ANN. LXXI. MENSS.II. DIES IIXX.
<lb/>COLII EX SORORE NEPOTES B.M.POSS.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>CONTEMNO ET ORNO MENTE, MANV
</ab>

<pb facs="#f007"/>
<ab>
<lb/>TO THE
<lb/>MOST HIGH,
<lb/>MOST MIGHT,
<lb/>AND MOST HAPPY 
<lb/>PRINCE, IAMES BY THE
<lb/>GRACE OF GOD, KING
<lb/>OF GREAT BRITAINE,
<lb/>FRANCE AND IRE-
<lb/>LAND, DEFEN-
<lb/>DER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c.
<lb/>IOHN NORTON
<lb/>HIS MA-
<lb/>IESTIES MOST 
<lb/>HVMBLE AND
<lb/>FAITHFVLL SER-
<lb/>[V]ANT CONSECRATETH
<lb/>THESE IMMORTALL LA-
<lb/>BOVRS OF ABRAHAM
<lb/>[OR]TELIVS, TRANS-
<lb/>[L]ATED INTO
<lb/>ENGLISH
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>[fleurons]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f008"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.9
</ab>

<pb facs="#f009"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.10
</ab>

<pb facs="#f010"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.11
</ab>

<pb facs="#f011"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.12
</ab>

<pb facs="#f012"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.13
</ab>

<pb facs="#f013"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.14
</ab>

<pb facs="#f014"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.15
</ab>

<pb facs="#f015"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.16
</ab>

<pb facs="#f016"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.17
</ab>

<pb facs="#f017"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.18
</ab>

<pb facs="#f018"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt> <!--I, Audrey Gauthier, worked on seq 19 of this text--></personalstmt>
<lb/> [Evrope]
<lb/>In the diuision of the world, diuers haue placed [Africa] in the third part : some few haue made no mere but [Asia] and [Eu
<lb/>rope] only ; and [Africa ] they make a part of [Europe], saith [Salustius]. This is that which [S. 
<lb/>Paulinus] in [Aulonius], out o
<lb/> the opinion of the same Saluit, thus writeth of : Europam Afiamque duo vel maxima terrae Membra, quibus Lybiam
<lb/>dubie Salluitius addit, Europæ admixtram : poffit quum tertia dici : [Europe] and [Asia] vast, the Earthly globe between 
<lb/>them share. Yet whether [Africke] should a part of this our [Europe] be ; or make a third part by it selfe, Saluit doth doubt 
<lb/>I see. But [Phiolstratus] also in [Isocrates] doth diuide the world into [Asia] and [Europe] : yea [Isocrates] himself, in his Pane-
<lb/>gyricos. Moreouer in [Varroes] booke De lingua Latina these words are read ; As all the world is diuided into [Heauen]
<lb/>and [Earth] : so [Heauen] is seuered into his quarters : and the [Earth] into [Asia] and [Europe]. Againe the same author in his 
<lb/>booke of Husbandrie writeth thus : first, when as the world, by [Eratofthenes], was very fuly and naturally divided into 
<lb/>two parts, the one toward the South, |[Asia] doubtlesse he meaneth ] the other in the north [[Europe] we call it.] [S. Augu-
<lb/>stine] in his 16. booke De Ciutiate Dei: [Lucane] in his 9. booke: and [Orosius] in the first booke of his history, haue the like
<lb/>wordes to the same sense. Notwithstanding custome since hath preuailed with all historiographers and cosmographers which haue written either in Latine 
<lb/>or Greeke, ioinly to diuide the globe of the earth into these three parts: [Asia], [Africke] and [Europe]: the last of which we have taken vpon vs to describe in 
<lb/>this place, not only in forme of a mappe or chart, like a Geographer: but in this present discourse, like an historian. Concerning the forme of it therefore, it 
<lb/>is manifold, as [Strabo] writeth. It is a Peninsula or demy-isle, and not an island; although [Silenus], as [Elianus] writeth, did sometime to [Midas] so relate of
<lb/>it. For it is on all sides, as you may see in the mappe, bounded and beaten with the salt sea, but only upon the East, where it is by a small necke ioined to the 
<lb/>greater [Asia]. Yet by vhat limis they are there distinguished, the ancient and the later writers do not altogether agree. For those which are more ancient 
<lb/>as [Aristotle], [Plato], [Herodotus], and others which do follow their opinion, do diuide [Europe] from [Asia], by the riuer [Phasis], (a riuer of Colchis falling 
<lb/>into the [Euxine sea], Mar maiore, or Maurothalassa, as the greeks call it) neere [Trapezonda] : some mappes do now call that riuer Faffo, others Phaz-
<lb/>zeth: the Scythians, (as [Theuet] reporteth, Debbaffethca) or which is all one, by that ithmos or neckland which is between the forefaid Mar maiore or 
<lb/>Pontus Euxinus, and the [Caspian sea] (Mar de Cachu, the ancient called it Mare Hyrcanum, the Hyrcanie sea) which formerly all old writers thought to 
<lb/>be but a bay or gulfe of the Scythian or Northren ocean, as [Strabo], [Pliny], [Mela], [Dionysius], [Plutarch] (in the life of [Alexander] and in his discourse of the 
<lb/>face in the sphere of the Moone) and [Iornandes] a more late writer, have I ft recorded. Yet all of them were deceiued. Only [Herodotus] truly (as this 
<lb/>our latter age doth approve and find to be so) doth affirme this to be a sea of it selfe, and to have neither in-let nor out-let, or to be intermeddled with any other 
<lb/>sea. [Dionysius], [Arrianus], [Diodorus], [Polybius], [Iornandes] and [Ptolemey] have diuided it from [Asia] by the riuer [Tanais] (Don or Tana, as now the 
<lb/>Italians name it) who think that both the rife of this riuer, and the land Northward from where it commeth, are both unknown and uncertaine. All 
<lb/>doubt where to place and lay their bounds : as indeed who never perfectly knew thoseplaces toward the East and North, not being then discovered, but only 
<lb/>described by them, from the fabulous reports of others: as for example, the Riphæan and Hyperboræan mountaines, which are feined inuentions of the 
<lb/>Greekes, a Strabo writeth: together with Aluani montes, heere described by Ptolemey, where not only these mountaines, but also no other at this 
<lb/>day, are to be seene: but in their places diuers huge and vast woods, great fennes and bogges, or large champion plaines.Orpheus also long since described 
<lb/>in this part of the continent I meane, between Mæotis palus, the fenne Mæotis, (now called Mar delleZabbache, and Mardella Tana) and the sea
<lb/>Cronium, an hugewood. Lifewise, Dionysius After heereabouts placeth an Infinite wood, as he termeth it, from whence he faith Tanais or Don doth
<lb/>Spring, which after many windings and turnings at lift falleth into the forenamed fenne Maeotis. Ifidorus heere hath the Riphaean woods, in which he
<lb/>saith Tanais doth first take the beginning. That Donaw (Danubis) doth diuide Asia from Europe, Seneca in the sixth booke Natural. doth manifestly
<lb/>Affirme; of which his opinion, what do we thinke, we will, God willing, set downe in the discourse to the Mappe of Dacia. Hitherto we see the forenamed au-
<lb/>thours to doubt and disagree between themselues of the limittes of these two parts of the world: if therefore they shall find me a meet vmpier and arbitratour
<lb/>in this matter, I would, not vnfitly, and as I hope to the liking of all parties, decide the controuer thus: I would make the bounds, to be Tanais, or the ri-
<lb/>uer Don; the straights or narrow peece of the maine land that is between riuer and the riuer Rha, (Athel) which emptieth it selfe into the Caspian sea:
<lb/>the East branch of the same Athel: then from his head vnto the riuer Oby, and so even vnto his mouth or fall into the Northren sea: For by this mouth, I
<lb/>do easily perswade my selfe, that antiquity did verily beleeue that the Caspian sea did vnlade it selfe into the maine Ocean. For that the name of this riuer O-
<lb/>by is ancient, it is very likely, for that montes Obij, certaine mountaines called Obij are placed heere about in this in this tract, by Athenaeus, which he saith for-
<lb/>merly were called of the ancient montes Riphæi, the Riphæan hils: but then in his daies montes Alpes, the Alpes. Againe Iornandes in this continent,
<lb/>not farre from hence, describeth Ouim, or Obim, a Scythian nation or family. And that these foresaid mountaines, are in this place (not where Ptolemey
<lb/>and Pomponius Mela haue placed them) very many men, of great credit and learning in these our daies, sufficient witnesses do stoutly auouch. Amongst
<lb/>which Baro Herberftein, in his history of Mofcouy, is one: Paul Oderborne, in his treatise written of the life of Bafilides, is another: lastly, Antony
<lb/>Wied, in his mappe of Mofcouy may be the third. Now they name it vulgarly by diuers and sundrie names, but commonly they call it Cingulum mundi,
<lb/>The girdle of the world, as the said Herberftein doth affirme. In a mappe of these countries set out by Master Ienkinfon, an Englishman, who travelled
<lb/>through these parts, it is called Zona Orbis, The girdle of the Earth. Moreouer I haue in some sort for this diuision, Iornandes and AEthicus, upon my 
<lb/>side, where they say that the Riphaan mountaines do part Asia and Europe. Againe these selfe same hils, yea, and in this tract, are the montes Hyperbo-
<lb/>rei; not where Ptolemey placeth them. And they are the same with montes Riphæi, Obij, and Alpes. Thus farre of the diusion of Asia from Europe.
<lb/>        [Pliny] calleth this part of the world, The Nurce of all Nations; [Mardonius], as [Herodotus] doth tell of him, auoucheth it to [Xerxes], to be by farre 
<lb/>the beautifulleft of all places of the World, to be a most goodly and gallant country, yielding all maner of fruits and fruitfull trees and those
<lb/>in their kindes and best; and to be such that it were pity that any king in the World should haue ought to do in but he. Varro in his bo kes Dere 
<lb/>Rustica, of Husbandrie writeth, That it is a more temperate and healthful soile than [Asia]. [Statius] in his Achilleidos, more than once or twice, calleth
<lb/>it, The Mighty prouince of the World. Maximaterra viris &amp; fœcundissima doctis Vrbibus, Europe for multitude of warlike men and scholers 
<lb/>deeply learned, doth farre excell thus [Mamilius] writeth of it. [Aristotle], the prince of Philospophers, maketh the inhabiters of this part of the world, to be, 
<lb/>A very stout and couragious people. The same authour affirmeth, that, All kind of beasts and cattell heere, are in their kind, greater, and stronger 
<lb/>than in [Asia] and [Africke]. But of the nature of this country, the maners and customes of the people, let vs heare what [Strabo] that excellent Geographer saith
<lb/>in his second book ; This part is most fertile of valiant and prudent men. It is all generally habitable, excepting only a very small portion toward 
<lb/>the North, and abutting vpon the Hamaxici, which dwell vpon [Tanais], (Don) Meo'is Palus (Mar delle Zabacche) and Borysthenes (Nieper or
<lb/>Dnester) which place, by reason of the extream cold, is not habitable. Yet certaine bleake and mountainous places inhabited, although in re-
<lb/>spect of the nature of the soile they are tilled and manured with greater difficulty, yet having gotten good skilull and industrious husbands,
<lb/>those also are tamed and much bettered, which heeretofore were badly vsed, and kept only by theeues and out-lawes. And indeed the Greekes
<lb/>when they dwelt vpon the rocks and mountaines, dwelt well and conueniently, by reason of their wife cariage in ciuill matters, arts, sciences and 
<lb/>knowledge of those things, which necessarily are required to the maintenance of mans life. In like maner the Romanes, hauing brought many 
<lb/>sauage and fierce Nations vnder their seruile yoke, seated, I meane, in places not very conuenient to dwell in, in respect of the nature of the coun- 
<lb/>try, either for that it was rough and craggy, or wanted hauens, or was too bleake and cold, or for other causes, taught them to vse merchandise
<lb/>before vnknowen, and haue brought them from a sauage and brutish life, to live ciuilly and more humanely. But those parts which are situate in
<lb/>an equall and temperat climate, there nature administreth all things necessary for the maintenance of man and beast. Now when as those Nations
<lb/>which do inhabite and dwell in fertile and rich countries, are maintainers of peace and quietnesse ; and those which are seated in barren and vn-
<lb/>fruitfull countries, are most hardy and stout : it commeth to passe that both are helpfull one to another ; while these do vle their weapons for 
<lb/>their countries defence, those againe do help and maintaine them by the profits that they raise out of the earth, by their arts and mysteries, as also
<lb/>by their learning, wisedome and policy : euen as in like maner also the dammage is mutuall and either side feeleth a sensible hurt, when the one
<lb/>part doth not helpe the other : yet the estate of the souldier and warlike man is somewhat better, if they be not ouercome with multitude. And
<lb/>the nature of [Europe] serueth very fitly for this purpose : for it is all diuersly distinguished by lofty mountaines and lowly plaines ; so that euery
<lb/>where the husbandmen and soldiers ; the politicians and the martiall warriers do dwell together : yet so as the greatest number are peaceable
<lb/>men : which kind of life they enjoy especially by the meanes and labour of their captaines, first of the Greekes, then of the Macedonians, and
<lb/>lastly of the Romanes. Therefore both in peace and warre it is sufficient of itselfe to maintaine and defend itselfe : for it hath great plenty both
<lb/>of stout soldiers, painfull husbandmen, and politique statesmen. In this also it doth, excell, that it bringeth foorth passing good fruits, such I
<lb/>meane, as are necessary for the maintenance of mans life: with all sorts of mettall, for what vse soeuer. Spices or sweet smelling things and preti- 
<lb/>ous stones, are brought hither from forren countries, WHICH THINGS WHOSOEVER HAVE NOT, THEY LIVE NEVER A WHIT 
<lb/>WORSE THAN THOSE DO THAT HAVE THEM. Moreouer this is especially worth the noting, that hauing wonderfull store of cattell, 
<lb/>sheep and oxen ; it breedeth very few dangerous wild beasts. Thus farre the learned [Strabo]. Many other things thou maist read of this [Europe],
<lb/>together with the nature and condition of the people of the same, in that treatise which [Hippocrates], the prince of Physitions, wrote of the aire and waters.
<lb/>This [Europe] also, and not any other place of the world beside, doth yeeld Succinum or Electrum, (Amber we call it, the Germanes, Glessum) yet it is not 
<lb/>found in Eridianus, a river falling into some Northren sea, as [Herodotus] doth fabulously report : or in Padus, a riuer of Italy (Po) as the poets iestingly af-
<lb/>firme: nor in the Electrides, certaine fained ilands in the Hadriaticke sea, as some men of better credit, and ore diligent searchers out of the [t]ruth, as [Pliny]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f019"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.20
</ab>

<pb facs="#f020"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--saith, have seriously thought: nor in [Spaine], as [[AE]schylus] beleeued: nor in certaine rockes at the further end of the gulfe of [Venice, (mare Hadriaticum)]
<lb/>as some mere suber men haue giuen out: nor in [Liguria,] as [Sudinus, Metrodorus,] and [Theophraftus] would haue men thinke: nor in [Ethiopia,] neere [Iu-
<lb/>piter Ammons] temple, or in [Scythia,] as [Philemon] imagined: nor in [Britaine,] as [Socatus]: nor in the [Gleflari[ae],] ilands in the Germane ocean, as [Pliny]
<lb/>hathtaught: nor in [Bannonia] or [Baltia,] (a certain iland) as [Tim[ae]us] hath broached: nor in a certain riuer, as [Dion Prul[ae]us] hath taught: but neere vnto the
<lb/>neckland or peninsula [H[ae]ltarum,] in the bay [Pautzkerwicke] and [Frifch-haff, (Sinus Clilipenus)] in the Balticke or East Sea, not farre from [Dantzk] in
<lb/>[Pomerell] or [Sprufe]: where hitherto it hath been taken (a thing wholly hidden from the ancients) to the great gaine and enriching of the Nations neere inha-
<lb/>biting: and not in any other place of the world beside.  In the same [Europe] are there many goodly and stately cities, among[st] the [w]hich the most famous, in all
<lb/>ages, are [Rome] and [Constantinople,] (which afterward was called [New-Rome)] and now are [London, Venice] and [Paris.]  The riuers of greater note
<lb/>are [Rhein, Isther] or [Donaw,] and the [Thames]: the [m]oods more notable are [Ardene] in [Gallia,] 500.miles of length, reaching from the riuer of [Rhein] vn-
<lb/>to [Tourney] in [France;] and [Hercynia] in [Germany,] 40.daies iourney long, as [Pomponius] writeth, and 9.daies iourney broad, as [C[ae]ser] in his Commen-
<lb/>taries reporteth: a greater woodth in which, or more vast, there is no history maketh mention of. Thus much of [Europe.] But whereof it tooke the name
<lb/>and was so called, or who first gave it that name, I thinke saith [Herodotius,] there is no man vnder heauen !!!! doth certainly know or can vpon any probalibity
<lb/>gesse, except one should think it so called of Europa Tyria.  But wherefore it should so of her be named, I am whollt ignorant, and I perswade my selfe and do
<lb/>verily beleeue, that no man in the world truly know.  For that she, as we read in the fabulous stories of the poets, was violently taken out of Phoe]nicia, a
<lb/>country of Asia, and caried from thence into Cyprus, or as others write, into the iland Creta (Candy) all men do know well enough: where, as Eusebius his
<lb/>Chronicle doth witnesse, being taken of Asterius king of Creta to wife, she bare him Minoes, Rhadamanthus and Sarpedon: from whence she went not into
<lb/>Europe, but into Asia, as Herodotus hath left recorded.  But what is that to Europe this part of the world?  One might easilier beleeue it to haue been so
<lb/>named of Europus, who, as Trogus Pompeius witnesseth, sometime in these parts possessed a large kingdome: which also I do see to be auouched by Eusta-
<lb/>thius vpon Lycophron, who maketh this Europis to be the sonne of one Himerus.  Pausanias saith that one Eurpoa was king of Sicyonia, a prouince of
<lb/>Peloponnelius in Greece: to him Eusebius in his Chronicle doth ascribe, who makeuth him equall to the Patriarke Abraham, &amp; to hauve liued aboue 3550.
<lb/>years since, about 1950. yeares before the birth of Christ.  There be some, as Festus writeth, that thinke it so named of the beautifulnesse and excellency
<lb/>of the country.  These we are sure are fabulous or vncertaine: may we not therefore, as they haue formed of Phrat, Euphrates, and of Koft, [AE]gyptus (as
<lb/>we have shewed before) thinke that of Riphath (the sonne of Gomer, Iapheths sonne, to whom this part of the world was presently after the confusion at Ba-
<lb/>bel, assigned) they haue likewise formed Europa? And surely the name Riphath, doth very manifestly shew it selfe in Rhip[ae]is montibus, the Ripheanhils:
<lb/>item in Riph[ae]o fluuio, now called the river Oby, in Ripe, a city of Peloponneses, in Rhiphat[ae]is, the people of Paphlagonia, as Iosephus writeth. Pto-
<lb/>lemey in the second booke of his Quadripartite, in my opinion much more truly, writeth that it was sometime called by a common name, C E L T I C A, name-
<lb/>ly of a principall Nation that first did inhabite it.  For there is almost no prouince in all this part, in which in time past the C E L T A E did not inhabit.  For in 
<lb/>Spaine toward the West, and beyond Hercules pillars are the Celt[ae] as Herodotus affirmeth, Item, abouthe riuer B[ae]tis, as Strabo auoucheth, the
<lb/>Celtici Pre[ae]samarci, are in the prouince of Lucensis, and others otherwise named Nerij[?] as Pliny saith: Dion and Xiphilinus do shew that the Canta-
<lb/>bri and Astures are the same with the Celt[ae]: Pliny nameth the city Celtica, in the prouince Hispalensis. Antonius hath the Celti: item Celticum 
<lb/>promontorium, is the same that Cantabrum promontorium, which now is called Cabo de finis terre. What Geographer or Historian is he amongst the anci-
<lb/>ents that hath not made mention of the Celtebri? In France were the Celt[ae] and Celtogalat[ae]: and from thence are those in Britaine. For that this iland
<lb/>was first peopled from hence, lying so neere oueragainstit, it is a common opinion and very probable. That the Gauls Germanes were vulgarly called Celt[ae], 
<lb/>all Historiographers do iointly agree: and indeed Dion doth affirme, that the Celt[ae] did dwell vpon either side of the riuer Rhem: the Celt[ae] dwelt in Gal-
<lb/>lia Cisalpina (Lombardy) or Italy, as Appianus writeth. And again vpon the Ionian sea, (that is, the Hadriaticke), which also Strabo doth auerre.
<lb/>Silius Italicus placeth them about the riuer Eridianus (Po). In Epirus sometime dwelled the Celt[ae], as Antonius Liberalis bath giuen out: Stepha-
<lb/>nus placeth the same about the mount H[oe]mus: Arrianus, neere the mouth of the riuer Donaw: as also Strabo in M[oe]fia. The same author writeth,
<lb/>that the Celt[ae] are intermedled with the Illyrij and Thraces. Who also placeth them vpon the riuer Borysthenes. Moreouer Aristotle in his booke De
<lb/>mundo, ioineth the Celt[ae] with the Scythians. Heere hence the same Strabo and Plutarch do make their Celtoscyth[ae]. In Plutarch, in the life of Camil-
<lb/>us, I read that the Galat[ae] (which he maketh to haue come of the stocke of the Celt[ae]) passing the Northren dea came vnto the Riph[ae]an mountains. 
<lb/>Againe out of the forenamed Strabo I learne that the nations dwelling Northward were in his time called Calt[ae]. The which also their ancient lan-
<lb/>guage, which is called the Celticke or Germane tongue, doth at this day sufficiently demonstrate: which is the same (only differing a little in dialect) 
<lb/>with that which is vsed in the ilands neere adioining to these places, as in Island, Groenland, Friesland and others in this ocean. Plutarke in Marius wri
<lb/>teth, that Celtica doth begin at the outmost sea (that is, the Atlanticke Sea) and so stretcheth itselfe out farre into the North and from thence vn-
<lb/>to the fenne M[ae]Otis, (Mare delle Zabacche.) Pomponius Mela calleth the Cassiterides (which in another place we haue proued to belong to great Britaine, 
<lb/>or to be the number of those which are named Brittanic[ae]) Celticke Ilands. What is this else, I pray you, than plainly to affirme that T H E  C E L T [AE]  D O  
<lb/>P O S S E S S E   A L L  E V R O P E ? Which indeed is that which Ephorus in Strabo did see so many years since: when as he diuiding all the world into 4. quar-
<lb/>ters, saith that, That part which is toward the East, is inhabited of the  Indians: that which is in the South, of the [AE]thiopians: the North parts, of 
<lb/>the Scythians: and the West, of the Celt[ae]. The scholiast of Appollonius nameth the Hadriaticke sea, Mare Celticum, the Celticke Sea. And Lyco-
<lb/>phron describeth Celtos, a certain poole, about the mouth of the riuer Ister. [Item he placeth] Leuce an iland of Mar maiore ([Pontus Euxinus]) o-
<lb/>ueragainst the mouth of the riuer Donaw. [May we not therefore properly, as they call those that inhabit Asia, Asians: and those which dwell in Africa,
<lb/>Africanes: call these which dwell in Celtica, Celtickes[.] He that out of all ancient stories, penned either in Latine or Greeke doth not know that the Celt[ae] are
<lb/>the Germanes, let him haue recourse to the 22. chapter of Hadrianus Iunius his Batauia, and I doubt not but, hauing throughly waied those many sound ar-
<lb/>guments, and sufficient testimonies of ancient graue writers, shall rest satisfied and sweare to our opinion. If not, let him listen to the] D[utchmen, and he shall
<lb/>heare them call one another in their familiar communication,] Kelt. [The French also or Gauls I call a German nation. And I can proue by good arguments, if it
<lb/>were a matter pertaining to this our purpose, that the Germane or Dutch tongue is the ancient language of the Celt[ae], and to be the same which [hithertothcy]
<lb/>haue vsed in all places and now is spoken, except in some places where the power of the Romanes so preuailed, that they banished this, and seated theirs in the 
<lb/>roome. It is likely therefore that the etymology and reason of the deriuation of the word] Eurpoe, [which was vnknowen vnto the old writers, is to be sought
<lb/>and fetched from no other language else, but from that which was most [vsuall] in this part of the world. For that the inh[a]bitants of any country should take
<lb/>the name of their natiue soile from strangers, it is so absurd and hard to be beleeued, that there cannot any thing more foolish or contrary to truth be inuen-
<lb/>ted or deuised. Wherefore I thinke it good, concerning this matter, heere to lay downe the iudgement of] Goropius Becanus, [our countryman, who thinketh
<lb/>it to be so named, not of a woman, (which is probable, either neuer was, or neuer came heere) but] [a] latitudine videndi, [of the largenesse of his prospe[ct] (as
<lb/>he speaketh) namely, because (I do cite his owne words out of the 9. booke of his] Origines) [it doth not only looke toward Asia, on the East and South: [Africa],
<lb/>on the South and West: but also the New-found-world beyond the Hyperborei, on the West and North. Neither shall any man perswade me, that] Europe
<lb/>[had the name from] Greece [or the Greeke language, seeing that is was first inhabited of the Cimbers] (Cimmerij,[descended from] Gomer, [the elder brother) before it was possessed of the Greeks] (Iones, [come from] Iawan [a yonger brother, [?] but the 4. son of] Yapheth) [we make a dipthong by setting the 5. vowel of the 
<lb/>Latins before the 2. which neither the Latins nor Greeks do admit. Therefore if so be at any time they change the words in which this did light, for] We,
<lb/>[they put] Eu; [turning it backward. Therefore our men do term it] Verop, [not] Europ, [whereby they vnderstand a worthy] company of men: [for] Wer [(a mono-
<lb/>syllable pronounced like a dipthong) signifieth] lofty, great, excellent &amp; that which is best in euery kind of thing: [which not withstanding some do write] ur, 
<lb/>[without a dipthong, yet with a long vowell. Therefore, as of] Terues, [they formed] Tereus, [loof] Werop, [the Latines [&amp;] Greeks haue made] Europe: [so named of
<lb/>the excellency of the Nation, which doth farre surpasse all the other men of the World. For] Hop, [as I haue shewed before, signifieth a company or multitude of men.
<lb/>More of this word thou maist see in his] 8. [booke Thus farre out of his workes which are foorth in print: that which followeth, is taken out of a booke of his
<lb/>which he also hath set foorth, yet not imprinted, but such as he vsed priua[t]ly, and hath many additions in sundrie places in the margin written with his owne
<lb/>hand, which he had prepared against the second edition. But I waighing, saith he, and comparing this name with that which I haue read in holy Scripture, a-
<lb/>nother reason farre more excellent, and better commeth into my mind. We see that to] Yaphet [was promised enlargement or a farre spreading of his posterity,
<lb/>or as some other interpret the word, ioy and gladnesse: which then he truly had enioied, when as Christ had redeemed vs by his death and pretious [bloud] (which
<lb/>blessing doth agree to this part of the world, rather than to any other vnder heuven beside: and therefore all other countries generali do call] Europe: THE
<lb/>KINGDOME OF THE CHRISTIANS [: and the Europeans, are called of the Turkes and Arabians,] GAIVVR, [that is, Christians.)] E [, therefore
<lb/>doth signifie a lawfull contra[c]t and mariage:] VR, [excellent: and] HOP, [hope: whereupon it commeth to passe, that] Europe [signifieth] The excellent hope
<lb/>of a lawfull mariage. [which is proper to this portion of the world which] Noah [gaue to] Iapheth [ his sonne to inhabite. For although that the posterity of] Sem
<lb/>[was by] Abraham, [for many ages wedded to God, yet at length he put her away and diuorced her from him. But the wedlocke whereby God, by Christ is wed-
<lb/>ded to] Europe [his Church, shall neuer be dissolued: so that] Europe [may most properly be said to be] Iaphets [portion. But of this word we will speake more in
<lb/>our] Francica. [Thus farre] Goropius. [Which I haue very willingly communicated to the curtuous Reader, leauing it to the censure of the learned to be ind-
<lb/>ged. Yet I know that these things haue been very bitterly skoffed at already by a certaine learned man, but one wholly ignorant of this tongue, and therefore of
<lb/>lesse [iudgement] in this argument. There are some which do think that this] Europe [was in the holy Scripture called] IAPETIA. [Thus farre of] Europe, [to
<lb/>which before I do altogether leaue, I will adiout of] Herodotus [in his] Polymnia, [the words of] Mardonius [to] Darius [spoken of this country.] That it is a 
<lb/>country most goodly and beautifull, bearing all maner of excellent fruitefull trees, and those in their kind the best: and to be such that it were pi-
<lb/>ty that any man but a king only should possesse.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f021"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.22
</ab>

<pb facs="#f022"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.23
</ab>

<pb facs="#f023"/>
<ab>
<lb/>This the Ancients have diuersly distinguished; but at this present it is divided by John Leo of
<lb/>Africa, into foure chiefe parts; Barbaria, Numidia, Libya, and the Land of Negros. Barbarie, 
<lb/>which is accounted the best, they circumscribe with the Atlantick &amp; Mediterranean seas; with 
<lb/>mount Atlas, &amp; whither region of Barca bordering upon Ægypt. Numidia, called by the 
<lb/>inhabitants Biledulgerid, and abounding with Dates (for which cause the Arabians call it by no 
<lb/>other name, but the Date-bearing region) is bounded Westward by the Atlantick Ocean; 
<lb/>Northward by mount Atlas; it stretcheth East as farre as the citie Caphsa, which is an hundred &amp; 
<lb/>fiftie miles distant from Ægypt; and the sande Deserts of Libya embrace it on the South. Libya 
<lb/>the third part, is named in the Arabian tongue Sura, which word signifies a Desert. It begins East 
<lb/>from Nilus, and thence runneth West as farre as the Atlantick sea; Numidia lies to the North of it, 
<lb/>and the Land of Negros to the South. Now followeth the fourth part, which they call Nigritarum or 
<lb/>Nigritania, either from the inhabitants, who are of a blacke colour, or from the river Niger, that 
<lb/>runneth thorow the countrey. It is bounded by Libya, South by the Æthiopick Ocean; West by 
<lb/>Guinee, and East by the Kingdome of Gago. And here we are to note, that according unto their 
<lb/>division, all Africa is included within the Mediterranean, Atlantick, and Æthiopick seas and the 
<lb/>river Nilus; whereof Ægypt and Abassia are accounted parts of it, which we not unworthily 
<lb/>therefore proper to belong to Africa. For the true Africa containes at this day Prester Johns 
<lb/>Empire, which by all late Writers is ascribed to Africa. Wherefore with Ptolomy indeed it ought to 
<lb/>be bound by the Mediterranean sea and Ocean seas, rather than by any river whatsoever; and 
<lb/>it hath the forme of a Peninsula, being joined toward Asia by an Isthmos of small neck-land, 
<lb/>which lies between the Mediterranean sea and the gulf of Arabia. The South part hereof was 
<lb/>unknowne to our ancestors, till the yeere 1497, whereas Vasco de Gama first doubling the Cape 
<lb/>of Bona Speranza, and passing about all Africa, came to Calecut in East India. This Southerne 
<lb/>part by the Persians and Arabians is called Zangibar.
<lb/>At the fore-sayd Cape of good hope the inhabitants are exceeding blacke; which we thought in 
<lb/>no wise to omit, because all men suppose the cause of blacknesse to be heat, and the 
<lb/>nearnesse of the Sunne; whereas the Sunne of it selfe forceth no more, than about the Streight 
<lb/>of Magellan (we measure the heat of the place, according to the position of the heavens and 
<lb/>distance from the Equinoctiall line) were now notwithstanding the people are reported to be 
<lb/>marvellous white. But if we will needs ascribe this blacknesse to the scorching of the Sun, let us 
<lb/>consider, that the same makes the Spaniards and Italians looke white; whereas they are equally 
<lb/>distant from the Equinoctiall with the inhabitants of the fore-sayd Cape; namely the one towards 
<lb/>the South, and the other towards the North. Prester Johns people are of a browne colour; in 
<lb/>Zanel and Mollala the inhabitants are cole blacke, yet all in one &amp; the same distance from the 
<lb/>equator, and under the very same parallell of the heavens. And on the contrary, why did 
<lb/>Herodotus and Pindarus describe such as inhabite the same climate with themselves, namely 
<lb/>Colches, to be a blacke people, and curled haired? Herodotus in his Thalia makes the Indians 
<lb/>blacke like the Æthiopians; which the experience of our times confirmeth. I know Herodotus will 
<lb/>have the cause hereof to be the seede of the parents, which he sayth is not whiter, than of other 
<lb/>people, but blacke. To whom Possidonius also subscribeth, and imputeth the matter of all this 
<lb/>blacknesse unto Canicular heate, against which opinion I have nothing to allege. Let the truth of 
<lb/>the matter rest upon the authors credit. But this as many men thinke more strange; that in all 
<lb/>America there were no black people found besides a few only in one place called by them 
<lb/>Quarequa. What then is the efficient cause of this colour? Is it the drinesse of the heavens, or of 
<lb/>the earth? is it perhaps some hidden propriety of the soile? Or a kind of fat licentious nature in 
<lb/>the nature of men? Or is it all these variances in one? But these things we leave to be 
<lb/>considered by them, who more curiously search into the secrets of nature.
<lb/>This portion of the world is called by the Greeks Libya, and by the Latines Africa, because it is 
<lb/>not moistened with extremity of cold: or (if we may credit some) of Afer one of the adventurers 
<lb/>posterity. Another derivation of the name you have (set downe by John Leo in the description of 
<lb/>his booke of the Description of Africa), who deriveth it from one blacke African, springing of the 
<lb/>stocke of Cham, who first inhabited that part of the Mediterranean sea, from Atlas, bounded by 
<lb/>the river Nilus, or rather as the best authors have taught us, the African soile called of the 
<lb/>Greekes Aphrice, Marce rubrum, and red sea. Herodotus reporteth, that Africa was first 
<lb/>unknowne till Cesars time, when it was found to be a third part of the inhabited world. Plinie the 
<lb/>like, and so doth Solinus. Caesar Scaliger gathereth of the word Africa, that it is a name of the 
<lb/>same import with aprica, that is, a sunne-shining place; for that this land lying open on every 
<lb/>side to the Sunnes visitation, seemed thereby to have beene named so little other than of 
<lb/>apricity. The principall regions of Africa have amongst themselves (as it were) a threefold 
<lb/>division: first, from Atlas in the West to the red sea and Arabia, whence it took the name of the 
<lb/>first inhabiters, or else from the colour of the people, for the most part blacke and duskie; the 
<lb/>second, to wit, the inner part of Africa, from Nilus to the Kingdome of Congo, is more temperate, 
<lb/>and not so much subject to the Sunnes heate; the third, which is next unto the South Pole, by 
<lb/>reason of the obliquity of the Zodiack, is more temperate than the former. The islands that 
<lb/>belong to Africa (some of which are expressed in the table) are Madagascar, the Canaries, the 
<lb/>Isles of Cape Verde, and St. Thomas situated under the equinoctiall, which aboundeth with 
<lb/>fruits.
<lb/>Among the ancient Writers none have particularly described this region. But concerning the 
<lb/>same saith Isidore in his Etymologies; Hanno his navigation about Africa, in diversities; and 
<lb/>Iambulus his voyages, in Diodorus Siculus; and likewise Herodotus his Melpomene. 
<lb/>Bartholomeus de Glanvilla in his Image of the World reporteth the like. Of late Writers reade 
<lb/>also the Commentaries of Vasco de Gama, Franciscus Alvares, who travelled Æthiopia. But of 
<lb/>all others John Leo hath most exactly described it; as also Andrew Thevet, and Francis Alvarez, 
<lb/>both travellers of Africa. Concerning the river Nilus, the greatest in all the world, you have the 
<lb/>letters of John Ramusio and Jerome Fracastorius. Of Africa itself, as by me read at large in the 
<lb/>second volume of Mr. Richard Hakluyts English Voyages.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f024"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.25
</ab>

<pb facs="#f025"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.26
</ab>

<pb facs="#f026"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.27
</ab>

<pb facs="#f027"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.28
</ab>

<pb facs="#f028"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.29
</ab>

<pb facs="#f029"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.30
</ab>

<pb facs="#f030"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.31
</ab>

<pb facs="#f031"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.32
</ab>

<pb facs="#f032"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.33
</ab>

<pb facs="#f033"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.34
</ab>

<pb facs="#f034"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.35
</ab>

<pb facs="#f035"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.36
</ab>

<pb facs="#f036"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.37
</ab>

<pb facs="#f037"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.38
</ab>

<pb facs="#f038"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.39
</ab>

<pb facs="#f039"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.40
</ab>

<pb facs="#f040"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.41
</ab>

<pb facs="#f041"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.42
</ab>

<pb facs="#f042"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.43
</ab>

<pb facs="#f043"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.44
</ab>

<pb facs="#f044"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.45
</ab>

<pb facs="#f045"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.46
</ab>

<pb facs="#f046"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.47
</ab>

<pb facs="#f047"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.48
</ab>

<pb facs="#f048"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.49
</ab>

<pb facs="#f049"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.50
</ab>

  </div></body>
      </text>