<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription">
<body><div>
    <pb facs="#f000"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.1
</ab>

<pb facs="#f001"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.2
</ab>

<pb facs="#f002"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.3
</ab>

<pb facs="#f003"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.4
</ab>

<pb facs="#f004"/>
<ab>
<lb/>THEA
<lb/>TRVM
<lb/>ORBIS
<lb/>TERRA
<lb/>RVM
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>ABRAHAMI ORTELI ANTVERP.
<lb/>GEOGRAPHI REGII.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>THE THEATRE OF THE WHOLE
<lb/>WORLD: SET FORTH BY THAT
<lb/>Excellent Geographer Abraham Ortelius.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>LONDON,
<lb/>Printed by IOHN NORTON; Printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie in 
<lb/>Hebrew, Greeke, and Latine. 1606.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f005"/>
<ab>
<lb/>The sway, by Sea &amp; Land, grat IAMES doth beare,
<lb/>His Birth, His Bloud, These Kingdomes figure here:
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>But, were his seuerall vertues to be crown'd
<lb/>A World, past thine, Ortelius, must be found.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f006"/>
<ab>
<lb/>ABRAHAMI ORTELII
<lb/>QVEM VRBS VRBIVM ANTVERPIA EDITIT,
<lb/>REX REGVM PHILLIPVS GEOGRAPHVM HABVIT,
<lb/>MONVMENVM HIC VIDES.
<lb/>BREVIS TERRA EVM CAPTIT
<lb/>QVI IPSE ORBEM TERRARVM CEPIT,
<lb/>QVI IPSE ORBEM TERRARVM CEPTIT,
<lb/>STILO ET TABVLIS ILLVSTRAVIT:
<lb/>SED MENTE CONTEMPSIT,
<lb/>QVA CAELVM ET ALTA SVSPEXIT
<lb/>CONSTANS ADVERSVM SPES AVT METVS.
<lb/>AMICITIAE CVLTOR, CANDORE FIDE, OFFICIIS,
<lb/>QVIETIS CVLTOR, SINE LITE, VXORE, PROLE.
<lb/>VITAM HABVIT, QVALE ALIVS, VOTVM.
<lb/>VT NVNC QVOQVE AETERNA EI QVIES SIT
<lb/>VOTIS FAVE LECTOR.
<lb/>OBIIT IIII.KAL. IVLII. ANNO CIƆ.XCIIX.
<lb/>VIXIT ANN. LXXI. MENSS.II. DIES IIXX.
<lb/>COLII EX SORORE NEPOTES B.M.POSS.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>CONTEMNO ET ORNO MENTE, MANV
</ab>

<pb facs="#f007"/>
<ab>
<lb/>TO THE
<lb/>MOST HIGH,
<lb/>MOST MIGHT,
<lb/>AND MOST HAPPY 
<lb/>PRINCE, IAMES BY THE
<lb/>GRACE OF GOD, KING
<lb/>OF GREAT BRITAINE,
<lb/>FRANCE AND IRE-
<lb/>LAND, DEFEN-
<lb/>DER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c.
<lb/>IOHN NORTON
<lb/>HIS MA-
<lb/>IESTIES MOST 
<lb/>HVMBLE AND
<lb/>FAITHFVLL SER-
<lb/>[V]ANT CONSECRATETH
<lb/>THESE IMMORTALL LA-
<lb/>BOVRS OF ABRAHAM
<lb/>[OR]TELIVS, TRANS-
<lb/>[L]ATED INTO
<lb/>ENGLISH
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>[fleurons]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f008"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.9
</ab>

<pb facs="#f009"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.10
</ab>

<pb facs="#f010"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.11
</ab>

<pb facs="#f011"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.12
</ab>

<pb facs="#f012"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.13
</ab>

<pb facs="#f013"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.14
</ab>

<pb facs="#f014"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.15
</ab>

<pb facs="#f015"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.16
</ab>

<pb facs="#f016"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.17
</ab>

<pb facs="#f017"/>
<ab>
<lb/> <personalstmt><!--I, Haley Jensen, worked on seq. 18 of this text--></personalstmt>
<lb/> TYPVS ORBIS TERRAVM.

<lb/>HOMI 
<lb/>NES HAC LEGE 
<lb/>SVNT GENERATI, 
<lb/>QVI TVERENTVR
<lb/>ILLVM GLOBVM,
<lb/>QVEM IN HOC TEM 
<lb/>PLO MEDIVM VI
<lb/>DES, QVAE TER 
<lb/>RA DICITVR. 
<lb/>[Cicero].

<lb/>EQVS 
<lb/>VEHENDI 
<lb/>CAVSA, ARANDI 
<lb/>BOS, VENAN’DI
<lb/>ET CVSTODIENDI 
<lb/>CANIS, HOMO AV 
<lb/>TEM ORTVS AD 
<lb/>MVNDVM CON 
<lb/>TEMPLANDVM. 
<lb/>[Cicero].

<lb/>HOC 
<lb/>EST PVNCTVM, 
<lb/>QVOD INTER TOT. 
<lb/>GENTES FERRO 
<lb/>ET IGNI DIVIDI 
<lb/>TVR,O QVAM RIDI 
<lb/>CVLI SVNT MOR 
<lb/>TALIVM TER
<lb/>MINI [?]
<lb/>[Seneca].

<lb/>QVID EI POTEST VIDERI MAGNV [ ] IN REBVS HVMANIS, CVI AETER
<lb/>NITAS OMNIS, TOTIVSQVE MVNDI [ ] NOTA SIT MAGNITVDO. [CICERO]

<lb/>VTINAM 
<lb/>QVEMADMO 
<lb/>DVM VNIVERSA 
<lb/>MVNDI FACIES 
<lb/>IN CONSPECTVM 
<lb/>VENIT, ITA PHI 
<lb/>LOSOPHIA TOTA 
<lb/>NOBIS POSSET 
<lb/>OCCVRRERE. 
<lb/>[Seneca].
</ab>

<pb facs="#f018"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt> <!--I, Audrey Gauthier, worked on seq 19 of this text--></personalstmt>
<lb/> [Evrope]
<lb/>In the diuision of the world, diuers haue placed [Africa] in the third part : some few haue made no mere but [Asia] and [Eu
<lb/>rope] only ; and [Africa ] they make a part of [Europe], saith [Salustius]. This is that which [S. 
<lb/>Paulinus] in [Aulonius], out o
<lb/> the opinion of the same Saluit, thus writeth of : Europam Afiamque duo vel maxima terrae Membra, quibus Lybiam
<lb/>dubie Salluitius addit, Europæ admixtram : poffit quum tertia dici : [Europe] and [Asia] vast, the Earthly globe between 
<lb/>them share. Yet whether [Africke] should a part of this our [Europe] be ; or make a third part by it selfe, Saluit doth doubt 
<lb/>I see. But [Phiolstratus] also in [Isocrates] doth diuide the world into [Asia] and [Europe] : yea [Isocrates] himself, in his Pane-
<lb/>gyricos. Moreouer in [Varroes] booke De lingua Latina these words are read ; As all the world is diuided into [Heauen]
<lb/>and [Earth] : so [Heauen] is seuered into his quarters : and the [Earth] into [Asia] and [Europe]. Againe the same author in his 
<lb/>booke of Husbandrie writeth thus : first, when as the world, by [Eratofthenes], was very fuly and naturally divided into 
<lb/>two parts, the one toward the South, |[Asia] doubtlesse he meaneth ] the other in the north [[Europe] we call it.] [S. Augu-
<lb/>stine] in his 16. booke De Ciutiate Dei: [Lucane] in his 9. booke: and [Orosius] in the first booke of his history, haue the like
<lb/>wordes to the same sense. Notwithstanding custome since hath preuailed with all historiographers and cosmographers which haue written either in Latine 
<lb/>or Greeke, ioinly to diuide the globe of the earth into these three parts: [Asia], [Africke] and [Europe]: the last of which we have taken vpon vs to describe in 
<lb/>this place, not only in forme of a mappe or chart, like a Geographer: but in this present discourse, like an historian. Concerning the forme of it therefore, it 
<lb/>is manifold, as [Strabo] writeth. It is a Peninsula or demy-isle, and not an island; although [Silenus], as [Elianus] writeth, did sometime to [Midas] so relate of
<lb/>it. For it is on all sides, as you may see in the mappe, bounded and beaten with the salt sea, but only upon the East, where it is by a small necke ioined to the 
<lb/>greater [Asia]. Yet by vhat limis they are there distinguished, the ancient and the later writers do not altogether agree. For those which are more ancient 
<lb/>as [Aristotle], [Plato], [Herodotus], and others which do follow their opinion, do diuide [Europe] from [Asia], by the riuer [Phasis], (a riuer of Colchis falling 
<lb/>into the [Euxine sea], Mar maiore, or Maurothalassa, as the greeks call it) neere [Trapezonda] : some mappes do now call that riuer Faffo, others Phaz-
<lb/>zeth: the Scythians, (as [Theuet] reporteth, Debbaffethca) or which is all one, by that ithmos or neckland which is between the forefaid Mar maiore or 
<lb/>Pontus Euxinus, and the [Caspian sea] (Mar de Cachu, the ancient called it Mare Hyrcanum, the Hyrcanie sea) which formerly all old writers thought to 
<lb/>be but a bay or gulfe of the Scythian or Northren ocean, as [Strabo], [Pliny], [Mela], [Dionysius], [Plutarch] (in the life of [Alexander] and in his discourse of the 
<lb/>face in the sphere of the Moone) and [Iornandes] a more late writer, have I ft recorded. Yet all of them were deceiued. Only [Herodotus] truly (as this 
<lb/>our latter age doth approve and find to be so) doth affirme this to be a sea of it selfe, and to have neither in-let nor out-let, or to be intermeddled with any other 
<lb/>sea. [Dionysius], [Arrianus], [Diodorus], [Polybius], [Iornandes] and [Ptolemey] have diuided it from [Asia] by the riuer [Tanais] (Don or Tana, as now the 
<lb/>Italians name it) who think that both the rife of this riuer, and the land Northward from where it commeth, are both unknown and uncertaine. All 
<lb/>doubt where to place and lay their bounds : as indeed who never perfectly knew thoseplaces toward the East and North, not being then discovered, but only 
<lb/>described by them, from the fabulous reports of others: as for example, the Riphæan and Hyperboræan mountaines, which are feined inuentions of the 
<lb/>Greekes, a Strabo writeth: together with Aluani montes, heere described by Ptolemey, where not only these mountaines, but also no other at this 
<lb/>day, are to be seene: but in their places diuers huge and vast woods, great fennes and bogges, or large champion plaines.Orpheus also long since described 
<lb/>in this part of the continent I meane, between Mæotis palus, the fenne Mæotis, (now called Mar delleZabbache, and Mardella Tana) and the sea
<lb/>Cronium, an hugewood. Lifewise, Dionysius After heereabouts placeth an Infinite wood, as he termeth it, from whence he faith Tanais or Don doth
<lb/>Spring, which after many windings and turnings at lift falleth into the forenamed fenne Maeotis. Ifidorus heere hath the Riphaean woods, in which he
<lb/>saith Tanais doth first take the beginning. That Donaw (Danubis) doth diuide Asia from Europe, Seneca in the sixth booke Natural. doth manifestly
<lb/>Affirme; of which his opinion, what do we thinke, we will, God willing, set downe in the discourse to the Mappe of Dacia. Hitherto we see the forenamed au-
<lb/>thours to doubt and disagree between themselues of the limittes of these two parts of the world: if therefore they shall find me a meet vmpier and arbitratour
<lb/>in this matter, I would, not vnfitly, and as I hope to the liking of all parties, decide the controuer thus: I would make the bounds, to be Tanais, or the ri-
<lb/>uer Don; the straights or narrow peece of the maine land that is between riuer and the riuer Rha, (Athel) which emptieth it selfe into the Caspian sea:
<lb/>the East branch of the same Athel: then from his head vnto the riuer Oby, and so even vnto his mouth or fall into the Northren sea: For by this mouth, I
<lb/>do easily perswade my selfe, that antiquity did verily beleeue that the Caspian sea did vnlade it selfe into the maine Ocean. For that the name of this riuer O-
<lb/>by is ancient, it is very likely, for that montes Obij, certaine mountaines called Obij are placed heere about in this in this tract, by Athenaeus, which he saith for-
<lb/>merly were called of the ancient montes Riphæi, the Riphæan hils: but then in his daies montes Alpes, the Alpes. Againe Iornandes in this continent,
<lb/>not farre from hence, describeth Ouim, or Obim, a Scythian nation or family. And that these foresaid mountaines, are in this place (not where Ptolemey
<lb/>and Pomponius Mela haue placed them) very many men, of great credit and learning in these our daies, sufficient witnesses do stoutly auouch. Amongst
<lb/>which Baro Herberftein, in his history of Mofcouy, is one: Paul Oderborne, in his treatise written of the life of Bafilides, is another: lastly, Antony
<lb/>Wied, in his mappe of Mofcouy may be the third. Now they name it vulgarly by diuers and sundrie names, but commonly they call it Cingulum mundi,
<lb/>The girdle of the world, as the said Herberftein doth affirme. In a mappe of these countries set out by Master Ienkinfon, an Englishman, who travelled
<lb/>through these parts, it is called Zona Orbis, The girdle of the Earth. Moreouer I haue in some sort for this diuision, Iornandes and AEthicus, upon my 
<lb/>side, where they say that the Riphaan mountaines do part Asia and Europe. Againe these selfe same hils, yea, and in this tract, are the montes Hyperbo-
<lb/>rei; not where Ptolemey placeth them. And they are the same with montes Riphæi, Obij, and Alpes. Thus farre of the diusion of Asia from Europe.
<lb/>        [Pliny] calleth this part of the world, The Nurce of all Nations; [Mardonius], as [Herodotus] doth tell of him, auoucheth it to [Xerxes], to be by farre 
<lb/>the beautifulleft of all places of the World, to be a most goodly and gallant country, yielding all maner of fruits and fruitfull trees and those
<lb/>in their kindes and best; and to be such that it were pity that any king in the World should haue ought to do in but he. Varro in his bo kes Dere 
<lb/>Rustica, of Husbandrie writeth, That it is a more temperate and healthful soile than [Asia]. [Statius] in his Achilleidos, more than once or twice, calleth
<lb/>it, The Mighty prouince of the World. Maximaterra viris &amp; fœcundissima doctis Vrbibus, Europe for multitude of warlike men and scholers 
<lb/>deeply learned, doth farre excell thus [Mamilius] writeth of it. [Aristotle], the prince of Philospophers, maketh the inhabiters of this part of the world, to be, 
<lb/>A very stout and couragious people. The same authour affirmeth, that, All kind of beasts and cattell heere, are in their kind, greater, and stronger 
<lb/>than in [Asia] and [Africke]. But of the nature of this country, the maners and customes of the people, let vs heare what [Strabo] that excellent Geographer saith
<lb/>in his second book ; This part is most fertile of valiant and prudent men. It is all generally habitable, excepting only a very small portion toward 
<lb/>the North, and abutting vpon the Hamaxici, which dwell vpon [Tanais], (Don) Meo'is Palus (Mar delle Zabacche) and Borysthenes (Nieper or
<lb/>Dnester) which place, by reason of the extream cold, is not habitable. Yet certaine bleake and mountainous places inhabited, although in re-
<lb/>spect of the nature of the soile they are tilled and manured with greater difficulty, yet having gotten good skilull and industrious husbands,
<lb/>those also are tamed and much bettered, which heeretofore were badly vsed, and kept only by theeues and out-lawes. And indeed the Greekes
<lb/>when they dwelt vpon the rocks and mountaines, dwelt well and conueniently, by reason of their wife cariage in ciuill matters, arts, sciences and 
<lb/>knowledge of those things, which necessarily are required to the maintenance of mans life. In like maner the Romanes, hauing brought many 
<lb/>sauage and fierce Nations vnder their seruile yoke, seated, I meane, in places not very conuenient to dwell in, in respect of the nature of the coun- 
<lb/>try, either for that it was rough and craggy, or wanted hauens, or was too bleake and cold, or for other causes, taught them to vse merchandise
<lb/>before vnknowen, and haue brought them from a sauage and brutish life, to live ciuilly and more humanely. But those parts which are situate in
<lb/>an equall and temperat climate, there nature administreth all things necessary for the maintenance of man and beast. Now when as those Nations
<lb/>which do inhabite and dwell in fertile and rich countries, are maintainers of peace and quietnesse ; and those which are seated in barren and vn-
<lb/>fruitfull countries, are most hardy and stout : it commeth to passe that both are helpfull one to another ; while these do vle their weapons for 
<lb/>their countries defence, those againe do help and maintaine them by the profits that they raise out of the earth, by their arts and mysteries, as also
<lb/>by their learning, wisedome and policy : euen as in like maner also the dammage is mutuall and either side feeleth a sensible hurt, when the one
<lb/>part doth not helpe the other : yet the estate of the souldier and warlike man is somewhat better, if they be not ouercome with multitude. And
<lb/>the nature of [Europe] serueth very fitly for this purpose : for it is all diuersly distinguished by lofty mountaines and lowly plaines ; so that euery
<lb/>where the husbandmen and soldiers ; the politicians and the martiall warriers do dwell together : yet so as the greatest number are peaceable
<lb/>men : which kind of life they enjoy especially by the meanes and labour of their captaines, first of the Greekes, then of the Macedonians, and
<lb/>lastly of the Romanes. Therefore both in peace and warre it is sufficient of itselfe to maintaine and defend itselfe : for it hath great plenty both
<lb/>of stout soldiers, painfull husbandmen, and politique statesmen. In this also it doth, excell, that it bringeth foorth passing good fruits, such I
<lb/>meane, as are necessary for the maintenance of mans life: with all sorts of mettall, for what vse soeuer. Spices or sweet smelling things and preti- 
<lb/>ous stones, are brought hither from forren countries, WHICH THINGS WHOSOEVER HAVE NOT, THEY LIVE NEVER A WHIT 
<lb/>WORSE THAN THOSE DO THAT HAVE THEM. Moreouer this is especially worth the noting, that hauing wonderfull store of cattell, 
<lb/>sheep and oxen ; it breedeth very few dangerous wild beasts. Thus farre the learned [Strabo]. Many other things thou maist read of this [Europe],
<lb/>together with the nature and condition of the people of the same, in that treatise which [Hippocrates], the prince of Physitions, wrote of the aire and waters.
<lb/>This [Europe] also, and not any other place of the world beside, doth yeeld Succinum or Electrum, (Amber we call it, the Germanes, Glessum) yet it is not 
<lb/>found in Eridianus, a river falling into some Northren sea, as [Herodotus] doth fabulously report : or in Padus, a riuer of Italy (Po) as the poets iestingly af-
<lb/>firme: nor in the Electrides, certaine fained ilands in the Hadriaticke sea, as some men of better credit, and ore diligent searchers out of the [t]ruth, as [Pliny]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f019"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.20
</ab>

<pb facs="#f020"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--saith, have seriously thought: nor in [Spaine], as [[AE]schylus] beleeued: nor in certaine rockes at the further end of the gulfe of [Venice, (mare Hadriaticum)]
<lb/>as some mere suber men haue giuen out: nor in [Liguria,] as [Sudinus, Metrodorus,] and [Theophraftus] would haue men thinke: nor in [Ethiopia,] neere [Iu-
<lb/>piter Ammons] temple, or in [Scythia,] as [Philemon] imagined: nor in [Britaine,] as [Socatus]: nor in the [Gleflari[ae],] ilands in the Germane ocean, as [Pliny]
<lb/>hathtaught: nor in [Bannonia] or [Baltia,] (a certain iland) as [Tim[ae]us] hath broached: nor in a certain riuer, as [Dion Prul[ae]us] hath taught: but neere vnto the
<lb/>neckland or peninsula [H[ae]ltarum,] in the bay [Pautzkerwicke] and [Frifch-haff, (Sinus Clilipenus)] in the Balticke or East Sea, not farre from [Dantzk] in
<lb/>[Pomerell] or [Sprufe]: where hitherto it hath been taken (a thing wholly hidden from the ancients) to the great gaine and enriching of the Nations neere inha-
<lb/>biting: and not in any other place of the world beside.  In the same [Europe] are there many goodly and stately cities, among[st] the [w]hich the most famous, in all
<lb/>ages, are [Rome] and [Constantinople,] (which afterward was called [New-Rome)] and now are [London, Venice] and [Paris.]  The riuers of greater note
<lb/>are [Rhein, Isther] or [Donaw,] and the [Thames]: the [m]oods more notable are [Ardene] in [Gallia,] 500.miles of length, reaching from the riuer of [Rhein] vn-
<lb/>to [Tourney] in [France;] and [Hercynia] in [Germany,] 40.daies iourney long, as [Pomponius] writeth, and 9.daies iourney broad, as [C[ae]ser] in his Commen-
<lb/>taries reporteth: a greater woodth in which, or more vast, there is no history maketh mention of. Thus much of [Europe.] But whereof it tooke the name
<lb/>and was so called, or who first gave it that name, I thinke saith [Herodotius,] there is no man vnder heauen !!!! doth certainly know or can vpon any probalibity
<lb/>gesse, except one should think it so called of Europa Tyria.  But wherefore it should so of her be named, I am whollt ignorant, and I perswade my selfe and do
<lb/>verily beleeue, that no man in the world truly know.  For that she, as we read in the fabulous stories of the poets, was violently taken out of Phoe]nicia, a
<lb/>country of Asia, and caried from thence into Cyprus, or as others write, into the iland Creta (Candy) all men do know well enough: where, as Eusebius his
<lb/>Chronicle doth witnesse, being taken of Asterius king of Creta to wife, she bare him Minoes, Rhadamanthus and Sarpedon: from whence she went not into
<lb/>Europe, but into Asia, as Herodotus hath left recorded.  But what is that to Europe this part of the world?  One might easilier beleeue it to haue been so
<lb/>named of Europus, who, as Trogus Pompeius witnesseth, sometime in these parts possessed a large kingdome: which also I do see to be auouched by Eusta-
<lb/>thius vpon Lycophron, who maketh this Europis to be the sonne of one Himerus.  Pausanias saith that one Eurpoa was king of Sicyonia, a prouince of
<lb/>Peloponnelius in Greece: to him Eusebius in his Chronicle doth ascribe, who makeuth him equall to the Patriarke Abraham, &amp; to hauve liued aboue 3550.
<lb/>years since, about 1950. yeares before the birth of Christ.  There be some, as Festus writeth, that thinke it so named of the beautifulnesse and excellency
<lb/>of the country.  These we are sure are fabulous or vncertaine: may we not therefore, as they haue formed of Phrat, Euphrates, and of Koft, [AE]gyptus (as
<lb/>we have shewed before) thinke that of Riphath (the sonne of Gomer, Iapheths sonne, to whom this part of the world was presently after the confusion at Ba-
<lb/>bel, assigned) they haue likewise formed Europa? And surely the name Riphath, doth very manifestly shew it selfe in Rhip[ae]is montibus, the Ripheanhils:
<lb/>item in Riph[ae]o fluuio, now called the river Oby, in Ripe, a city of Peloponneses, in Rhiphat[ae]is, the people of Paphlagonia, as Iosephus writeth. Pto-
<lb/>lemey in the second booke of his Quadripartite, in my opinion much more truly, writeth that it was sometime called by a common name, C E L T I C A, name-
<lb/>ly of a principall Nation that first did inhabite it.  For there is almost no prouince in all this part, in which in time past the C E L T A E did not inhabit.  For in 
<lb/>Spaine toward the West, and beyond Hercules pillars are the Celt[ae] as Herodotus affirmeth, Item, abouthe riuer B[ae]tis, as Strabo auoucheth, the
<lb/>Celtici Pre[ae]samarci, are in the prouince of Lucensis, and others otherwise named Nerij[?] as Pliny saith: Dion and Xiphilinus do shew that the Canta-
<lb/>bri and Astures are the same with the Celt[ae]: Pliny nameth the city Celtica, in the prouince Hispalensis. Antonius hath the Celti: item Celticum 
<lb/>promontorium, is the same that Cantabrum promontorium, which now is called Cabo de finis terre. What Geographer or Historian is he amongst the anci-
<lb/>ents that hath not made mention of the Celtebri? In France were the Celt[ae] and Celtogalat[ae]: and from thence are those in Britaine. For that this iland
<lb/>was first peopled from hence, lying so neere oueragainstit, it is a common opinion and very probable. That the Gauls Germanes were vulgarly called Celt[ae], 
<lb/>all Historiographers do iointly agree: and indeed Dion doth affirme, that the Celt[ae] did dwell vpon either side of the riuer Rhem: the Celt[ae] dwelt in Gal-
<lb/>lia Cisalpina (Lombardy) or Italy, as Appianus writeth. And again vpon the Ionian sea, (that is, the Hadriaticke), which also Strabo doth auerre.
<lb/>Silius Italicus placeth them about the riuer Eridianus (Po). In Epirus sometime dwelled the Celt[ae], as Antonius Liberalis bath giuen out: Stepha-
<lb/>nus placeth the same about the mount H[oe]mus: Arrianus, neere the mouth of the riuer Donaw: as also Strabo in M[oe]fia. The same author writeth,
<lb/>that the Celt[ae] are intermedled with the Illyrij and Thraces. Who also placeth them vpon the riuer Borysthenes. Moreouer Aristotle in his booke De
<lb/>mundo, ioineth the Celt[ae] with the Scythians. Heere hence the same Strabo and Plutarch do make their Celtoscyth[ae]. In Plutarch, in the life of Camil-
<lb/>us, I read that the Galat[ae] (which he maketh to haue come of the stocke of the Celt[ae]) passing the Northren dea came vnto the Riph[ae]an mountains. 
<lb/>Againe out of the forenamed Strabo I learne that the nations dwelling Northward were in his time called Calt[ae]. The which also their ancient lan-
<lb/>guage, which is called the Celticke or Germane tongue, doth at this day sufficiently demonstrate: which is the same (only differing a little in dialect) 
<lb/>with that which is vsed in the ilands neere adioining to these places, as in Island, Groenland, Friesland and others in this ocean. Plutarke in Marius wri
<lb/>teth, that Celtica doth begin at the outmost sea (that is, the Atlanticke Sea) and so stretcheth itselfe out farre into the North and from thence vn-
<lb/>to the fenne M[ae]Otis, (Mare delle Zabacche.) Pomponius Mela calleth the Cassiterides (which in another place we haue proued to belong to great Britaine, 
<lb/>or to be the number of those which are named Brittanic[ae]) Celticke Ilands. What is this else, I pray you, than plainly to affirme that T H E  C E L T [AE]  D O  
<lb/>P O S S E S S E   A L L  E V R O P E ? Which indeed is that which Ephorus in Strabo did see so many years since: when as he diuiding all the world into 4. quar-
<lb/>ters, saith that, That part which is toward the East, is inhabited of the  Indians: that which is in the South, of the [AE]thiopians: the North parts, of 
<lb/>the Scythians: and the West, of the Celt[ae]. The scholiast of Appollonius nameth the Hadriaticke sea, Mare Celticum, the Celticke Sea. And Lyco-
<lb/>phron describeth Celtos, a certain poole, about the mouth of the riuer Ister. [Item he placeth] Leuce an iland of Mar maiore ([Pontus Euxinus]) o-
<lb/>ueragainst the mouth of the riuer Donaw. [May we not therefore properly, as they call those that inhabit Asia, Asians: and those which dwell in Africa,
<lb/>Africanes: call these which dwell in Celtica, Celtickes[.] He that out of all ancient stories, penned either in Latine or Greeke doth not know that the Celt[ae] are
<lb/>the Germanes, let him haue recourse to the 22. chapter of Hadrianus Iunius his Batauia, and I doubt not but, hauing throughly waied those many sound ar-
<lb/>guments, and sufficient testimonies of ancient graue writers, shall rest satisfied and sweare to our opinion. If not, let him listen to the] D[utchmen, and he shall
<lb/>heare them call one another in their familiar communication,] Kelt. [The French also or Gauls I call a German nation. And I can proue by good arguments, if it
<lb/>were a matter pertaining to this our purpose, that the Germane or Dutch tongue is the ancient language of the Celt[ae], and to be the same which [hithertothcy]
<lb/>haue vsed in all places and now is spoken, except in some places where the power of the Romanes so preuailed, that they banished this, and seated theirs in the 
<lb/>roome. It is likely therefore that the etymology and reason of the deriuation of the word] Eurpoe, [which was vnknowen vnto the old writers, is to be sought
<lb/>and fetched from no other language else, but from that which was most [vsuall] in this part of the world. For that the inh[a]bitants of any country should take
<lb/>the name of their natiue soile from strangers, it is so absurd and hard to be beleeued, that there cannot any thing more foolish or contrary to truth be inuen-
<lb/>ted or deuised. Wherefore I thinke it good, concerning this matter, heere to lay downe the iudgement of] Goropius Becanus, [our countryman, who thinketh
<lb/>it to be so named, not of a woman, (which is probable, either neuer was, or neuer came heere) but] [a] latitudine videndi, [of the largenesse of his prospe[ct] (as
<lb/>he speaketh) namely, because (I do cite his owne words out of the 9. booke of his] Origines) [it doth not only looke toward Asia, on the East and South: [Africa],
<lb/>on the South and West: but also the New-found-world beyond the Hyperborei, on the West and North. Neither shall any man perswade me, that] Europe
<lb/>[had the name from] Greece [or the Greeke language, seeing that is was first inhabited of the Cimbers] (Cimmerij,[descended from] Gomer, [the elder brother) before it was possessed of the Greeks] (Iones, [come from] Iawan [a yonger brother, [?] but the 4. son of] Yapheth) [we make a dipthong by setting the 5. vowel of the 
<lb/>Latins before the 2. which neither the Latins nor Greeks do admit. Therefore if so be at any time they change the words in which this did light, for] We,
<lb/>[they put] Eu; [turning it backward. Therefore our men do term it] Verop, [not] Europ, [whereby they vnderstand a worthy] company of men: [for] Wer [(a mono-
<lb/>syllable pronounced like a dipthong) signifieth] lofty, great, excellent &amp; that which is best in euery kind of thing: [which not withstanding some do write] ur, 
<lb/>[without a dipthong, yet with a long vowell. Therefore, as of] Terues, [they formed] Tereus, [loof] Werop, [the Latines [&amp;] Greeks haue made] Europe: [so named of
<lb/>the excellency of the Nation, which doth farre surpasse all the other men of the World. For] Hop, [as I haue shewed before, signifieth a company or multitude of men.
<lb/>More of this word thou maist see in his] 8. [booke Thus farre out of his workes which are foorth in print: that which followeth, is taken out of a booke of his
<lb/>which he also hath set foorth, yet not imprinted, but such as he vsed priua[t]ly, and hath many additions in sundrie places in the margin written with his owne
<lb/>hand, which he had prepared against the second edition. But I waighing, saith he, and comparing this name with that which I haue read in holy Scripture, a-
<lb/>nother reason farre more excellent, and better commeth into my mind. We see that to] Yaphet [was promised enlargement or a farre spreading of his posterity,
<lb/>or as some other interpret the word, ioy and gladnesse: which then he truly had enioied, when as Christ had redeemed vs by his death and pretious [bloud] (which
<lb/>blessing doth agree to this part of the world, rather than to any other vnder heuven beside: and therefore all other countries generali do call] Europe: THE
<lb/>KINGDOME OF THE CHRISTIANS [: and the Europeans, are called of the Turkes and Arabians,] GAIVVR, [that is, Christians.)] E [, therefore
<lb/>doth signifie a lawfull contra[c]t and mariage:] VR, [excellent: and] HOP, [hope: whereupon it commeth to passe, that] Europe [signifieth] The excellent hope
<lb/>of a lawfull mariage. [which is proper to this portion of the world which] Noah [gaue to] Iapheth [ his sonne to inhabite. For although that the posterity of] Sem
<lb/>[was by] Abraham, [for many ages wedded to God, yet at length he put her away and diuorced her from him. But the wedlocke whereby God, by Christ is wed-
<lb/>ded to] Europe [his Church, shall neuer be dissolued: so that] Europe [may most properly be said to be] Iaphets [portion. But of this word we will speake more in
<lb/>our] Francica. [Thus farre] Goropius. [Which I haue very willingly communicated to the curtuous Reader, leauing it to the censure of the learned to be ind-
<lb/>ged. Yet I know that these things haue been very bitterly skoffed at already by a certaine learned man, but one wholly ignorant of this tongue, and therefore of
<lb/>lesse [iudgement] in this argument. There are some which do think that this] Europe [was in the holy Scripture called] IAPETIA. [Thus farre of] Europe, [to
<lb/>which before I do altogether leaue, I will adiout of] Herodotus [in his] Polymnia, [the words of] Mardonius [to] Darius [spoken of this country.] That it is a 
<lb/>country most goodly and beautifull, bearing all maner of excellent fruitefull trees, and those in their kind the best: and to be such that it were pi-
<lb/>ty that any man but a king only should possesse.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f021"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--Transcribed and encoded by Nicholas Vitale and Karolina Rosberg--></personalstmt><placeName>ASIA</placeName>
<lb/>
<lb/><placeName>Asia</placeName> diuides it selfe from <placeName>Europe</placeName> by the river <placeName>Tanais</placeName>, and a streight line drawen
<lb/>from the fountaines thereof to the <placeName>Bay of S. Nicolas</placeName> in the <placeName>North Ocean</placeName>:
<lb/>but from <placeName>Africa</placeName>, by the neck-land Ifthmos or narrow place of the earth, which
<lb/>in betweene the <placeName>Arabian gulfe</placeName> and the <placeName>Mediterran sea</placeName>. The residue thereof the
<lb/>Ocean and other seas do enuiron.
<lb/>
<lb/>This part the ancient Geographers, as <persName>Strabo</persName> in his eleuenth booke, and <persName>Ar-
<lb/>rianus</persName> in his fift booke, haue dinersly divided. But at this present it may be us not altogether un-
<lb/>fitly be distributed into fine parts, according to the great Empires by which it is gouerned. The first
<lb/>whereof, which bordereth upon <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and is subiect to the great <persName>Duke of Mofcouia</persName>, is bounded
<lb/>by the Frozen sea, the riuer <placeName>Ob</placeName>, the lake <placeName>Kitaia</placeName>, and a line drawen from thence to the <placeName>Caspian sea</placeName>,
<lb/>and by the Isthmus or neck-land between the <placeName>Caspian</placeName> and <placeName>Euxin seas</placeName>. The second is that, which
<lb/>yields obedience to the great <persName>Cham Emperour</persName> of the <placeName>Tartars</placeName>, whole Southern borders are the <placeName>Caspi-
<lb/>an sea</placeName>, the riuer <placeName>Iaxartest</placeName>, and mount <placeName>Imaus</placeName>; on the East and North it is begirt with the Ocean;
<lb/>and Westward it confines vpon the dominions of the foresaid great <persName>Duke of Russia</persName>. The third part,
<lb/>the progeinie of the Ottomans or the <persName>Turkish Emperour</persName> enioyes, which containeth whatsoeuer re-
<lb/>gions are situate within the compasse of the <placeName>Euxin sea</placeName>, the <placeName>aegean sea</placeName> (now called Arcipelago)
<lb/>and the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName>, the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, the <placeName>Arabian</placeName> and <placeName>Persian seas</placeName>, the riuer <placeName>Tigris</placeName>, the <placeName>Ca-
<lb/>spian sea</placeName>, and the Isthmos or neck-land between it and the sea <placeName>Euxine</placeName>. Vnder the fourth shalbe com-
<lb/>prised the <placeName>Kingdome of Persia</placeName>, now gouerned by the Sophies; Westward it hat the <placeName>Turkes</placeName>, with
<lb/>whom the Persian for the most part manteineth continuall warres; Northward the Empire of the
<lb/><persName>great Cham</persName>; Eastward it extends almost to the riuer <placeName>Indus</placeName>; and on the south it is restrained by the
<lb/>sea, at this present called <placeName>Indicum</placeName>, but in times past <placeName>Mare Rubrum</placeName>, or <placeName>The Red sea</placeName>. Now the
<lb/>sift part takes vp all that remaineth, which as in times past, so at this present, is called <placeName>The Indies</placeName>;
<lb/>neither is it gouerned by one only, as the former; but by many pety Kings, euery region almost hauing
<lb/>a peculiar Gouernour, some which are tributarie to the <persName>great Cham</persName>. And here it is not to be omitted,
<lb/>that all the sea-coasts from the <placeName>Arabian gulfe</placeName>, to the <placeName>Promontory of China</placeName>, commonly called <placeName>Cabo
<lb/>de Lampo</placeName>, situate in 30. degrees of Northerly latitude, are in a maner possessed, or made tributary
<lb/>to the <placeName>Portugals</placeName>. 
<lb/>
<lb/>Amongst infitinte others, the princpall isles ascribed to <placeName>Asia</placeName>, are <placeName>Cyprus</placeName> and <placeName>Rhodes</placeName> in the
<lb/><placeName>Mediterran</placeName> sea; <placeName>Zeilan</placeName> of the vulgar and <placeName>Taprobana</placeName> well knowento the ancients now called <placeName>Sa-
<lb/>motra</placeName>, but falsly <placeName>Sumatra</placeName>, in the <placeName>Indick-Ocean</placeName>, where also within the memory of our fathers, the
<lb/><placeName>Portugals</placeName> haue discouered the two <placeName>Iauas</placeName>, with the isles of <placeName>Borneo</placeName>, <placeName>Celebes</placeName>, <placeName>Palohan</placeName>, and<placeName>Min-
<lb/>danao</placeName>; and here likewise <placeName>Gilolo</placeName>, and the <placeName>Moluccos</placeName>, at this day famous for abundance of spi-
<lb/>ces which they yeeld. To these may be added the isles of <placeName>Iapan</placeName>, and <placeName>new Guinie</placeName> very lately descried;
<lb/>but this last, whether it be an island, or adioyned to the <placeName>South maine</placeName>, it is not yet Certainly knowen.
<lb/>
<lb/>The memorie of this part of the world is most renowmed, not only with prophane authors (as they 
<lb/>terme them) in regard of the first monarchies established by the Assyrians, the Persians, the Babylo-
<lb/>nians, and the Medes; but in the holy Scriptures also it is more famous than the rest: for here man-
<lb/>kinde was not only created by almightie God, deluded and corrupted by the enemie Satan, and resto-
<lb/> by our Saviour Christ; but we finde almost all the hestories in either Testament to haue beene in
<lb/>this part both written and accomplished.
<lb/><persName>Strabo</persName> hath described Asia in six books, namely from the 11. booke vnto the 16. <persName>Ptolomey</persName> hath
<lb/>decyphered the fame in three, as in his 5. 6. And 7. books; and likewise in 12. Geographicall Tables,
<lb/>and ascribes unto it 40. prouinces. It is also let foorth by <persName>Ammianus Marcellinus</persName> in his 23.
<lb/>booke, and by <persName>Diodorus Siculus</persName> in the beginning of his 18. Of late Writers none haue wholly and
<lb/>particularly described it. <persName>M. Paulus Venetus</persName>, <persName>Lewes of Barthema</persName>, and <persName>St. Iohn Mandeuile</persName>,
<lb/>(but this Authour is fraught with tables) haue written so much thereof, as by trauelling the regions,
<lb/>they found worthie of obseruation. Reade also the Epistle of <persName>Iacobus Nauarca</persName> a Fesuite.
<lb/>        I my selfe likewise certaine yeeres past set forth a large Map the description of the same.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f022"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.23
</ab>

<pb facs="#f023"/>
<ab>
<lb/>This the Ancients have diuersly distinguished; but at this present it is divided by John Leo of
<lb/>Africa, into foure chiefe parts; Barbaria, Numidia, Libya, and the Land of Negros. Barbarie, 
<lb/>which is accounted the best, they circumscribe with the Atlantick &amp; Mediterranean seas; with 
<lb/>mount Atlas, &amp; whither region of Barca bordering upon Ægypt. Numidia, called by the 
<lb/>inhabitants Biledulgerid, and abounding with Dates (for which cause the Arabians call it by no 
<lb/>other name, but the Date-bearing region) is bounded Westward by the Atlantick Ocean; 
<lb/>Northward by mount Atlas; it stretcheth East as farre as the citie Caphsa, which is an hundred &amp; 
<lb/>fiftie miles distant from Ægypt; and the sande Deserts of Libya embrace it on the South. Libya 
<lb/>the third part, is named in the Arabian tongue Sura, which word signifies a Desert. It begins East 
<lb/>from Nilus, and thence runneth West as farre as the Atlantick sea; Numidia lies to the North of it, 
<lb/>and the Land of Negros to the South. Now followeth the fourth part, which they call Nigritarum or 
<lb/>Nigritania, either from the inhabitants, who are of a blacke colour, or from the river Niger, that 
<lb/>runneth thorow the countrey. It is bounded by Libya, South by the Æthiopick Ocean; West by 
<lb/>Guinee, and East by the Kingdome of Gago. And here we are to note, that according unto their 
<lb/>division, all Africa is included within the Mediterranean, Atlantick, and Æthiopick seas and the 
<lb/>river Nilus; whereof Ægypt and Abassia are accounted parts of it, which we not unworthily 
<lb/>therefore proper to belong to Africa. For the true Africa containes at this day Prester Johns 
<lb/>Empire, which by all late Writers is ascribed to Africa. Wherefore with Ptolomy indeed it ought to 
<lb/>be bound by the Mediterranean sea and Ocean seas, rather than by any river whatsoever; and 
<lb/>it hath the forme of a Peninsula, being joined toward Asia by an Isthmos of small neck-land, 
<lb/>which lies between the Mediterranean sea and the gulf of Arabia. The South part hereof was 
<lb/>unknowne to our ancestors, till the yeere 1497, whereas Vasco de Gama first doubling the Cape 
<lb/>of Bona Speranza, and passing about all Africa, came to Calecut in East India. This Southerne 
<lb/>part by the Persians and Arabians is called Zangibar.
<lb/>At the fore-sayd Cape of good hope the inhabitants are exceeding blacke; which we thought in 
<lb/>no wise to omit, because all men suppose the cause of blacknesse to be heat, and the 
<lb/>nearnesse of the Sunne; whereas the Sunne of it selfe forceth no more, than about the Streight 
<lb/>of Magellan (we measure the heat of the place, according to the position of the heavens and 
<lb/>distance from the Equinoctiall line) were now notwithstanding the people are reported to be 
<lb/>marvellous white. But if we will needs ascribe this blacknesse to the scorching of the Sun, let us 
<lb/>consider, that the same makes the Spaniards and Italians looke white; whereas they are equally 
<lb/>distant from the Equinoctiall with the inhabitants of the fore-sayd Cape; namely the one towards 
<lb/>the South, and the other towards the North. Prester Johns people are of a browne colour; in 
<lb/>Zanel and Mollala the inhabitants are cole blacke, yet all in one &amp; the same distance from the 
<lb/>equator, and under the very same parallell of the heavens. And on the contrary, why did 
<lb/>Herodotus and Pindarus describe such as inhabite the same climate with themselves, namely 
<lb/>Colches, to be a blacke people, and curled haired? Herodotus in his Thalia makes the Indians 
<lb/>blacke like the Æthiopians; which the experience of our times confirmeth. I know Herodotus will 
<lb/>have the cause hereof to be the seede of the parents, which he sayth is not whiter, than of other 
<lb/>people, but blacke. To whom Possidonius also subscribeth, and imputeth the matter of all this 
<lb/>blacknesse unto Canicular heate, against which opinion I have nothing to allege. Let the truth of 
<lb/>the matter rest upon the authors credit. But this as many men thinke more strange; that in all 
<lb/>America there were no black people found besides a few only in one place called by them 
<lb/>Quarequa. What then is the efficient cause of this colour? Is it the drinesse of the heavens, or of 
<lb/>the earth? is it perhaps some hidden propriety of the soile? Or a kind of fat licentious nature in 
<lb/>the nature of men? Or is it all these variances in one? But these things we leave to be 
<lb/>considered by them, who more curiously search into the secrets of nature.
<lb/>This portion of the world is called by the Greeks Libya, and by the Latines Africa, because it is 
<lb/>not moistened with extremity of cold: or (if we may credit some) of Afer one of the adventurers 
<lb/>posterity. Another derivation of the name you have (set downe by John Leo in the description of 
<lb/>his booke of the Description of Africa), who deriveth it from one blacke African, springing of the 
<lb/>stocke of Cham, who first inhabited that part of the Mediterranean sea, from Atlas, bounded by 
<lb/>the river Nilus, or rather as the best authors have taught us, the African soile called of the 
<lb/>Greekes Aphrice, Marce rubrum, and red sea. Herodotus reporteth, that Africa was first 
<lb/>unknowne till Cesars time, when it was found to be a third part of the inhabited world. Plinie the 
<lb/>like, and so doth Solinus. Caesar Scaliger gathereth of the word Africa, that it is a name of the 
<lb/>same import with aprica, that is, a sunne-shining place; for that this land lying open on every 
<lb/>side to the Sunnes visitation, seemed thereby to have beene named so little other than of 
<lb/>apricity. The principall regions of Africa have amongst themselves (as it were) a threefold 
<lb/>division: first, from Atlas in the West to the red sea and Arabia, whence it took the name of the 
<lb/>first inhabiters, or else from the colour of the people, for the most part blacke and duskie; the 
<lb/>second, to wit, the inner part of Africa, from Nilus to the Kingdome of Congo, is more temperate, 
<lb/>and not so much subject to the Sunnes heate; the third, which is next unto the South Pole, by 
<lb/>reason of the obliquity of the Zodiack, is more temperate than the former. The islands that 
<lb/>belong to Africa (some of which are expressed in the table) are Madagascar, the Canaries, the 
<lb/>Isles of Cape Verde, and St. Thomas situated under the equinoctiall, which aboundeth with 
<lb/>fruits.
<lb/>Among the ancient Writers none have particularly described this region. But concerning the 
<lb/>same saith Isidore in his Etymologies; Hanno his navigation about Africa, in diversities; and 
<lb/>Iambulus his voyages, in Diodorus Siculus; and likewise Herodotus his Melpomene. 
<lb/>Bartholomeus de Glanvilla in his Image of the World reporteth the like. Of late Writers reade 
<lb/>also the Commentaries of Vasco de Gama, Franciscus Alvares, who travelled Æthiopia. But of 
<lb/>all others John Leo hath most exactly described it; as also Andrew Thevet, and Francis Alvarez, 
<lb/>both travellers of Africa. Concerning the river Nilus, the greatest in all the world, you have the 
<lb/>letters of John Ramusio and Jerome Fracastorius. Of Africa itself, as by me read at large in the 
<lb/>second volume of Mr. Richard Hakluyts English Voyages.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f024"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.25
</ab>

<pb facs="#f025"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--I, Grace Avery, worked on seq, 26 of this text.--></personalstmt> 
<lb/>  That all this [Hemisphere] or halfe-rundle (which is called [America]), and in regard of the large extension, 
<lb/>The New world thould lie concealed from our ancestors, till the yeere of Christ 1492, at what time 
<lb/>[Christopher Columbus] a Genoway first discovered the fame; is a matter surpassing the measure of human 
<lb/>admitation. For considering both the diligence of ancient Geographers in describing the World, and 
<lb/>the commodious opportunitie of most large Empires for the searching out of new [Regions], the also the insatiable auarice of mankinde, leauing nothing vnattempted for the attaining of Golde and Siluer, 
<lb/>where with these [Countries] incredibly abound; I have often wondered, how it could so long have beene 
<lb/>hidden from our World. Some that which suppose that this [Continent] was described by Platovn-
<lb/>der the name of Atlas : my selfe also am of opinion, that Plutarch speaking of the face in the bodie of
<lb/>The Moone, makes mention there of vnder the name of a [Maine continent.] Some thinke that Seneca tauitht with a Poeticall furie,
<lb/>prefaged the discouerie hereof in these Propheticall verses in the very end of the 2.Act.of Medea:
<lb/><p rend="left">
<lb/>—venient annis
<lb/>Secularseris, quibus Oceanus
<lb/>Vincularerum laxet &amp; ingens
<lb/>Pateat tellus, Typhisgnouos
<lb/>Detegat Orbes,
<lb/>Nec Sit terris ultima Thyle.</p>
<lb/><p rend="middle">
<lb/>In English Thus:</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">
<lb/>Long hence those yeeres will come,
<lb/>When th'Ocean shall dissolue
<lb/>Natures saft bonds and barres.
<lb/>Then shall huge lands appear,
<lb/>Typlhis shall then detect
<lb/>New worlds; not Thyle then
<lb/>Shall bound the paths of men.</p>
<lb/>Like to those Sihyllin verses, which (as [Iacobus Nauarchus] writeth) were found at the foot of the promontorie of the Moone
<lb/>(commonly called Rochan de Sinna) vpon the Ocean sea-shore, ingrauen vpon a source-square pillar, in the time of [Don Emmanuel]
<lb/>King of Portugall, to this or the like purpose:
<lb/><p rend="left">
<lb/>Volunetur Faxaliteris &amp; oridinere rectis,
<lb/>Cùmvideas Occidens Orientus Opes.
<lb/>Ganges, Indues, Tagus, erit mirabile vifu,
<lb/>Merces commutabitfuas vterquefibi.</p>
<lb/><p rend="middle">
<lb/>In English Thus:</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">
<lb/>The stone with my stick letters, row'ld shall bee,
<lb/>When West the treasures of the East shall see.
<lb/>The Portugals and Indians (a thing admir'd)
<lb/>Shall truck their wares, on either part desir'd.</p>
<lb/>Howbeit, that these verses are not ancient, but grauen in our times; nor part of Sibylles Prophesies, but {counterfeit}; I was {ad-
<lb/>uettifed} (being in hand with the second edition of this my Theatrum) from Rome, by Cesar Orlando a Ciuilian, in his letters, out of 
<lb/>some printed works of {Gasper Vareriui}, in which since that my felf haue read fame. And afterward I found it confirmed by 
<lb/>Amil Resend in his antiques of Portugale: namely, that in the time of Don Emmanuel King of Portugale, one Hermes Caiado of 
<lb/>The same country, caused them to be ingrauen and buried in the earth: and when he supposed that the marble began to corrupt 
<lb/>with the moisture of the ground; pretending some cause of recreation, he inuites his friends to a countrey-house, neere vnto 
<lb/>which this fained Prophefie lay hid. Wherefore benign all set at meat, in comes his Bailiffe with newes, that his Labourers had by 
<lb/>Chance digged up a stone engrauen with letters. They all immediately runne forth, they reade it, they admire it, they highly esteeme 
<lb/>it, and are ready to adore it &amp;c. See how apt Caiado was to delude his friends. [Marina Siculus] in his Chronicle of [Spaine] writes, 
<lb/>that there was found in Gold-mines an ancient piece of coine with Augustus Cesars image vpon it, and for the more confirmation 
<lb/>of the matter, that it was fent by [Archbishop of Consance to the Pope]. But I am of opinion, that it was there lost by the same fa- 
<lb/>milie which first found it. Iosephus Acosta in his booke De Natura noui orbis indeuours by many reasons to proue, that this part of
<lb/>America was originally inhabited by certaine [Indians], forced thither by tempestuous weather ouer the South fea which now 
<lb/>they call Mare del Zur. But to me it seemes more probable, out of the historie of the two Zeni gentlemen of [Venice] (which I haue
<lb/>put downe before the Table of the South sea, and before that [Scandia]) that this New world many ages past was entered vpon by
<lb/>some islanders of [Europe], as namely of [Groenland], [Island], and [Frisland]; being much neerer thereunto than the Indians, nor disioy-
<lb/>ned thence (as appears out of the Map) by an Ocean so huge, and to the Indians so vnnauiagble. Also, what else may we conie-
<lb/>eture to be signified by this word Norumbega (the name of a [North region of America]) but that from [Norway], signifying a North 
<lb/>land, some [Colonie] in times past hath hither beene transplanted? But why in mine opinion the maine Ocean was neuer failed by 
<lb/>ancient Nauigatours, I have declared in my Thesaurus Geographieus, speaking of Ophir. 
<lb/>	All this part of the [World], (except the North treat thereof, whole Coasts are not yet discovered) hath in these last times beene 
<lb/>failed round about. From North to South it stretcheth in forme of two Peninfulae or Demi-ifles, which are feuered by a very nar- 
<lb/>row isthmos or neck-land. The Northernmost of the two conteineth New Spaine, the prouince of Mexico, the countrey of Florida and New-found-land. But the Southermost (which the Spaniards call Terra firma) contains Peru and Brasil. A description of all 
<lb/>which regions the studious in Geography may reade in Leuinus Apolonius, in the Decads of Peter Martyr, and in Maximilianus Transiluanus, white writ all in Latine. Also to this purpose you haue many things worthy the obseruatioin the Iessutes Epistles,
<lb/>and in Maffeius his story of the Indies. Postellus also promiseth Discourses of West-Indie-matters : and so doth Fredericus Furius 
<lb/>Cariolanus. 
<lb/>These that follow haue purposely written of [America], but all in their mother-languages, and for the most part in Spanish; but 
<lb/>the better halfe of them are translated into Italian:
<lb/><p rend="left">
<lb/>[Pedro Cieca De Leon.]
<lb/>[Gonsalvo Fernando De Oviedo.]
<lb/>[Fernando Cortez.]
<lb/>[Peter Alvarado.]
<lb/>[Diego Godoya.]
<lb/>[Alvarez Nvnnez.]
<lb/>[Nvnnez De Gusman.]
<lb/>[Francis Vlloa.]
<lb/>[Francis Vasquez De Coronado.]
<lb/>[Antonie Mendoca.]</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">
<lb/>[Frier Marco De Nizza.]
<lb/>[Fernando Alarchon.]
<lb/>[Francis Xeres.]
<lb/>[Iohn Verarzano.]
<lb/>[Americo Vespvtio.]
<lb/>[Francis Lopez De Gomara.]
<lb/>[Ierome Benzo], in Italian.
<lb/>[Iaques Carthier], and
<lb/>[Andrew Thevet], wrote in French.
<lb/>[Iohn Standen], in Dutch.</p>
<lb/>Diuerse of which Authors, and many that haue written since, are translated into English in the third volume of M. Hak’uyts
<lb/> English Voyages.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f026"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--I, Grace Avery, worked on seq, 27 of this text.--></personalstmt> 
<lb/>AMERICAE SIVE
<lb/>NOVI ORBIS, NO-
<lb/>VA DESCRIPTIO.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f027"/>
<ab>
<lb/>This sea albeit vnknowen, yet was it not vnnamed by ancient writers: for Plinie calles it Eoum,
<lb/> and Orosius Orientale, that is, The 
<lb/>East sea. Ptolomey falsly termes it Sinvm Magnvm, A great bay; whereas he should haue nam’d it Mare Mag-
<lb/>nvm, A great sea. For of all the seas in the world it is the greatest and the widest. In Paulus Venetus it is described vnder
<lb/>the name of Mare Cin, (that is, as I interpret it) of Nubiense Arabs, Bahci Itzni vel alkini, Mare Sinarum, (The sea of China)
<lb/>and in Haithon Armenus (whom elsewhere we more truly call Antonie Curctino) by the name of Mare Cathay. Well therefore
<lb/>might it be named by the ancient and middle-age writers; but neuer was it fully knowen and discouered, till Fernando Magel-
<lb/>lan a Portugall sailed thereupon. Seene it was indeed, and as it were saluted in the yeere 1513, by Vasco Nunnez, from the 
<lb/>coast of Peru. But Magellan in the yeere of our saluation 1520. hauing passed the streight by him found, and called after his
<lb/>owne name (which it hitherto retaineth, for euery common Mariner calles it The Streight of Magellan) with an heroick and
<lb/>Herculean courage entred this sea, which vncertaine it is, whether any hippe before his had euer stemmed. For meditating a 
<lb/>voyage to the isles of the Moloccos, whereunto the Portugals vsually sailed from West to East; and intending to make either
<lb/>a shorter cut from East to West, he came at length vnto them by this sea: in one of which isles called Machan, he was slaine in a skirmish. The course of his
<lb/>voyage was this: Departing from Sivvil with fiue ships, whereof one being his owne, was called by a name of good presage Victoria, he came to the fortunate
<lb/>or Canary-isles; then to the Gorgones or Hesperides, now termed The isles of Cape verde; and thence to the Streight abouenamed: which when he had found
<lb/>and past thorow, he enters into this sea; where with a fresh and prosperous gale hauing sailed vpon the maine 40. dayes together, and beholding nothing but
<lb/>sea on all sides, and till the sea; when he had crosfed the South tropick he descried two small barren and vnhabited isles: where notwithstanding, because they 
<lb/>found good fishing, they staied two dayes &amp; then departed, calling them the Vnfortunate isles. Now, they are knowen by the name of Tiburones, and the isles
<lb/>of S. Peter. Then he proceeds on his nauigation, &amp; in the space of 3. moneths and 20. dayes, hauing failed ouer this vast Ocean 2400. leagues, he attained at
<lb/>length to the Aequinocitall, and thence to the desired Moluccons. And because (as we haue said) he had for the most part a prosperous &amp; non tempestuous wind, 
<lb/>he named this Pacisicum or The peaceable sea, now called by the common Mariner, The South sea, or Mar del Sur. Those that haue written of the New
<lb/>world, say, that this sea about thole vnfortunate isles, is most exceeding deepe, and that neere vnto the coast of Peru it yeeldeth pearles, and that there are in it 
<lb/>7449. isles, so that some in our times not vnfitly haue called the Western part thereof Archipelago or A sea thick set with isles: seeing this, like the Aegean sea
<lb/>(which is planted all ouer with the Cyclades, the Sporades, and many other islands, and is called in the Italian tongue Archipelago) is also with isles most nota
<lb/>-bly replenished. In the bottome of this sea Francus Ulloa and Antonie Pigafetta do report, that there growes a weed of 14. or 15. fathoms high within the water;
<lb/>and that it riseth out of the water to the height of some 4. or 5. fathom: so that sometimes you shall seeme not to saile thorow a sea, but rather thorow a greene
<lb/>medow. The place of Aristotle in his booke De Admirandis &amp;c. doth not much disagree from this; where he writes of the Phoenicians which inhabited Gady-
<lb/>ra, that when they had failed a while without the pillars of Hercules, they arriued at certaine regions abounding with weeds and slime, which were ouerflow-
<lb/>ed with the tides of the sea. The very same affirmeth Iornandes in the beginning of his Getish history; where he writes, that none could saile thorow the O-
<lb/>cean, being impassable in regard of weeds or turfs, and for that cause vnknowen. Yea Plinie and Amianus also of Megasthenes haue left recorded, that all the
<lb/>East Ocean growes full of woods. And that there a tree called Porus should beare Okes laden with mast, Polybius reporteth in Athenæus. Also, that the Bay-tree 
<lb/>growes in the Red sea, the same authour affirmes vpon the credit of Pythagoras. Hereunto you may adde that of Theophrastus in his 4. booke of the history of
<lb/>Plants, cap. 7.8.9. and the testimony of Aelianus, lib. 12. de Animal. cap. 3. and Strabo, lib. 1.6. and Plinie, lib. 2. cap. 102. lib. 6. cap. 22. and lib. 13. cap. 25. and Plu-
<lb/>tarch in his naturall questions concerning the face in the orbe of the Moone. All these are in some sort confirmbed by PLatoes fables or histories in his timeus
<lb/>concerning the Ile Atlantis; whose sea he affirmes to be vnnauegable by reason of the slime or oazenes remaining of the same Iles inundation. But concerning
<lb/> the ship called La Victoria learne thus much: it is not sayd amisse: Bare names of times things named do resemble: Manifest it is by this ship, which vnder this
<lb/> happy name, the first voyage that euer she made, was the only ship that caried away the victory of sailing quite ouer the maine Ocean, for so many ages before. 
<lb/>For departing from Spaine, by the Streight of Magellan, to the Moluccos, thence hauing doubled the Cape of Buona Esperança, and returned, whence she first
<lb/> put forth, she was the first of all ships and images, that euer circumpassed the whole earth. The same ship made out of Spaine a second voyage as farre as S.
<lb/> Domingo and home againe. There also she made a third voyage; but in her returne she was quite lost; neither was it euer knowen what became of her. Anti-
<lb/>quity would haue thought she had beene taken vp into the skies, and placed among the Constellations, like another Argo. Nor had this propheticall verfe
<lb/> of the peerelesse Poet beene vnfitly alleaged in her commendation. Then comes another Tiphy, another gold fleeced Argo. Let Plinie now cease to maruell,
<lb/> that out of a small hempe-seed should grow that, which was of force to carry vp and downe the globe of [this] earth. We in our age haue seene with the very
<lb/>same thing this world of ours, much greater than his, nauigated round about. Ours, I say; which that you may more perfectly vnderstand, do but compare
<lb/>the first Table of our Theatre with the first of our Parergon or By-worke, and you shall see the difference.
<lb/>And here, I suppose, I shall not bestow my labour altogether in vaine, by adding certaine particulars not commonly knowen, concerning the first discouery
<lb/> hereof. Which by all our late Writers is now vnworthily ascribed to Christopher Columbus. For in the yere 1492. he was the first man that laid it open, &amp; made
<lb/> it knowen, and communicated the vse and benefit thereof to the Christian world. Howbeit I finde, that the North part of America (which hitherto neeret vnto
<lb/> Europe, and to some of our European isles: namely, Groenland, Island, and Frisland; and is called Estotiland) was long since discouered by certaine Frislandish 
<lb/>fishers, driuen by tempest vpon that coast: and afterward about the yeere 1390, that it was reufited anew by Antonio Zeno, a gentleman of Venice: and that by 
<lb/> authority of Zichmi, then King of the said isle of Frisland, a Prince in those times very valiant, and ouer all that sea, for his warres and victories most re-
<lb/>nowned. Concerning this his expedition there are extant in Italian certaine Collections or briefe extracts drawen by Francis Marcolinus out of the letters of 
<lb/>Nicolaus and Antonio Zeno gentlemen of Venice, who liued in the selfe parts. Out of which Collections I added this that followes touching the description of this region. Estotiland (he saith) abounds with all things necessary for mankind. In the midst thereof stands an exceeding high mountaine, from whence issue foure
<lb/> riuers that water the whole country. The inhabitants are witty, and most expert in all kind of handicrafts. A language and letters they haue peculiar to them-
<lb/>selues. Howbeit in this Kings Library there are certaine Latine bookes, not vnderstood by them, which might perhaps before that time be there left by 
<lb/>some of their European neighbors that had traffique with them. They haue all kinds of metall, but specially gold, wherewith they mightily abound. They
<lb/> exercise trade of merchandize with the people of Groenland; from whence they fetch hides, pitch, &amp; brimstone. The inhabitants say, that towards the South
<lb/> there are countries rich of gold, and replenished with inhabitants. There are also many &amp; great woods; out of which they haue matter for the building of their 
<lb/>ships and cities; whereof and of fortresses there are great numbers. Of the loadstones vse in nauigation they are vtterly ignorant. They also make mention of 
<lb/>Drogeo, a region toward the South, inhabited by Canibals, and such as are delighted to eat mans flesh; for want whereof, they liue with fishing, which they very
<lb/> vse much vse. Beyond this there are large countries and another New world; but the inhabitants are barbarous, and go naked: howbeit against the cold of Win-
<lb/>ter they arme themselues with beasts skins. These haue no vse of metall; they liue by hunting. For weapons they vse long and sharp-pointed staues and
<lb/>bowes. They make warres one vpon another. Gouernours they haue, and lawes whereto they yeeld obedience. Southward of this place they liue in a more 
<lb/>temperate climate, hauing cities and idol-temples, wherein they sacrifice liuing men, whose flesh they afterward deuoure. These haue the vse of gold and siluer. 
<lb/>Thus much concerning this tract of land, out of the foresaid collection or extracts; this also is worthy the obseruation, that euen then our Europe-
<lb/>an pilots by meanes of that olde lande sailed those seas. For I am of opinion, that there is not to be found in any history a more ancient testimony touching the 
<lb/>foresayd vse of this stone. And these things I was the willinger to adioyne to this Table, because I see none of them that haue written the histories of the 
<lb/>world so much as once mention this matter.
<lb/>But concerning the loadftone or fea-compaffe you are to vnderftand,that the firft inuentour therof was Iobn Goia a citizen of Melfi, whom Alexander Sardns
<lb/>in hos booke De innentoribusrerun calleth Flanins Campanns. For fo write the Italians, and fo much is confirmed by Antonie Panormitanns in this one verfe of
<lb/>his : Firft Melfi Sailors tangbt ,the loadftone bow to vfe, and that in the yere of our Sauior 1300. This Melfi called Amalpbis in Lstine, is a towne fituate vpon the
<lb/>tea-fhore of Lucania. Goropius afcribes the finding out Danes or Dutchmen ; being perfuaded hereunto , because the names of the 3 2. 
<lb/>winds written vpon the compafle, are by all Pilots and Mariners, be they French, Spaniards,or of what nation foeuer, exprefled in the Dutch tongue : which
<lb/>I confelIe to ve true, if you except the Italians only : fo was the fpeake of thefe winds in their owne mother-language.Howeit feeing all our na-
<lb/>uigatours of Europe, be they Spaniards,French,English,or Dutch,do exprefle them in our language, I am verily of opinion, that as it was firft found and vfed
<lb/>by the Amalfitans ot Italians efpecially within their owne Mediterranfea : fo was was the knowledge therof from them derive vnto our Netherlanders,and inoft
<lb/>ot all to thofe of Brrges ; whofe city at that time (before all traff que was reduccd to Aniwerpe) was a famous mart-towne, and frequented by Italians,efpcci-
<lb/>ally pf Venice ,as the foeaid Zeni report : and according to the teltimony of Peter Quirini, Cbriftopher Fioronari, and Nicolas Micbele, who in this our Ocean
<lb/>fuffered that horrible shipwracke which we reade of in the Italian volumes : witnefle alfo Lewis Cadimofta, who in his Epiftles written about the yeere 1454,
<lb/>a Fien;es this city of Brnges to be a Mart inferior to none elfe in the North parts of the world. Wherefore, that the citizens of Brnges rescind that vf, of
<lb/>the fea-compaffe from the Italians, and out Italian tranflared the names of the winds into their owne language, and that from them the other nations be-
<lb/>fore mentioned borrowed thi-knowledge, I fee not well, how it may be denied. Ofthe nature and admirable virtue of the loadftone you may reade many
<lb/>notable things in Linius Sanasus his defcription of Africa, printed in Italiam at Venice. 
<lb/>	Theifles ot Salomon, which in this table you fee defcribed about Nona Gninea, were not long finance difcoucered by Oliner Mendenio, after be had conducted
<lb/>his fleet out of the part of Lima in Pern,&amp; had failed ouer this hugeOcean : as I find recorded in Lofepbus Acofla his i .book &amp;17 .chapter De natura no::iorbus.
<lb/>
<lb/>Tartarx Li 	     
 <lb/>Mites.

<lb/>In China regione, Iapania alijsque 		
<lb/>infulis vicinis, mefbis Chrif= 			
<lb/>tianorum : quorum indies novvs co=                
<lb/>lonie ducuntur, patribus Societatis 	 
<lb/>Ielu fidis operaeijs. 	
<lb/>
<lb/>M A R I S  P A C I F I C I
<lb/>( quod vulgò Mar del Zur
<lb/>cum regionibus circuniacentibus insufisque in eodem
<lb/>paSsim Sparsis, noviSsima description . 
<lb/>			
<lb/>					
<lb/>Aegyra bęc
<lb/>forte anti
<lb/>quorum
<lb/>
<lb/>		
<lb/>M A R I S  A T L A N T I C
<lb/>S I V E   M A R  D E L  N I R T  P A R S
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>Prima ego velivolid ambivi cursibus Orbem, 				   
<lb/>Magellane nove te duce ducts freto.				          
<lb/>Ambivi, meritoq vocor VICTORIA: sunt mî 				
<lb/>Vela, ala; precium, gloria ; pugna, mare . 
<lb/>
<lb/>A M E R I C A E
<lb/>M E R I D I O N A
<lb/>L I O R  P A R S . 
<lb/>
<lb/>Nova Guinea, quibufdam 
<lb/>Terra de Piccinacoli . 
<lb/>
<lb/>GENIO ET INGENIO NO 
<lb/>BILI DN, NICOLAO ROCCOXIO, 
<lb/>PATRICIO ANTVERPIENSI, 
<lb/>EIVSIDEMQVE VRBIS SENATORI, 
<lb/>Abrafiamus Ortefnis 	Regia Mcs geograofus 
<lb/>Lub merito 			dedicabat .
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>Cum privifegijs Imp. B Reg. Maies tatum , 
<lb/>Nee non Canceffaria Brabantia, ad decnnium .
</ab>

<pb facs="#f028"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.29
</ab>

<pb facs="#f029"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.30
</ab>

<pb facs="#f030"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.31
</ab>

<pb facs="#f031"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.32
</ab>

<pb facs="#f032"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.33
</ab>

<pb facs="#f033"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.34
</ab>

<pb facs="#f034"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.35
</ab>

<pb facs="#f035"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.36
</ab>

<pb facs="#f036"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.37
</ab>

<pb facs="#f037"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.38
</ab>

<pb facs="#f038"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.39
</ab>

<pb facs="#f039"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.40
</ab>

<pb facs="#f040"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.41
</ab>

<pb facs="#f041"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.42
</ab>

<pb facs="#f042"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.43
</ab>

<pb facs="#f043"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.44
</ab>

<pb facs="#f044"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.45
</ab>

<pb facs="#f045"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.46
</ab>

<pb facs="#f046"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.47
</ab>

<pb facs="#f047"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.48
</ab>

<pb facs="#f048"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.49
</ab>

<pb facs="#f049"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--Translation for Seq.50
</ab>

  </div></body>
      </text>