<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f016"/>
<ab>
<lb/>A DESCRIPTION OF THE WHOLE WORLD.
<lb/>
<lb/>THIS Map next ensuing containeth and representeth the portraiture of the whole earth,
<lb/>and of the maine Ocean that enuirons &amp; compasseth the same: all which earthly Globe
<lb/>the Ancients (who were not as then acquainted with the New world, not long since de-
<lb/>scried) diuided into three parts; namely, Africa, Europe, and Asia. But since that discouery
<lb/>of America, the learned of our age haue made that a fourth part, and the huge Continent
<lb/>vnder the South pole, a fifth, Gerardus Mercator the Prince of modern Geographers in his
<lb/>neuer-sufficiently-commended vniuersall Table or Map of the whole world, diuides this
<lb/>Circumference of the earth into three Continents: the first he calles that, which the Anci-
<lb/>ents diuided into three parts, and from whence the holy Writ beares record, that mankind had their first origi-
<lb/>nall, &amp; first was seated: the second, is that which at this present is named America or the VVest Indies: for the third,
<lb/>he appoints the South maine, which some call Magellanica, as yet on very few coasts thorowly discouered. That
<lb/>this orbe or masse of the earthly Globe contains in circuit, where it is largest, 5400 German or 21600 Italian
<lb/>miles, antiquity hath taught, &amp; late Writers haue subscribed to their opinion. And these so manifold portions of earth
<lb/>(sayth Plinie in the 11. booke of his Naturall historie) yea rather, as some haue termed them, the pricke or center of the world
<lb/>(for so small is the earth in comparison of the whole frame of the world) this is the matter, this is the seat of our glorie. Here we enioy
<lb/>honours, here we exercise authoritie, here we hunt after riches, here men turmoile and tire themselues, here we moue and maintaine ciuill
<lb/>dissensions, and by mutuall slaughter make more roome vpon the earth. And to let passe the publike tumults of the world, this in which
<lb/>we force the borderers to giue place and remoue farther off, and where we incroch by stelth vpon our neighbors lands: as he that extends
<lb/>his lands &amp; lordships farthest, and cannot abide that any should seat themselues too neere his nose, How great, or rather how small a por-
<lb/>tion of earth doth he enioy? Or when he hath glutted his auarice to the full, How little shall his dead carcase possesse? Thus far Plinie.
<lb/>
<lb/>The situation of this earth and sea, the disposition of the seuerall regions, with their inlets and gulfs, the maners and inclinations of the people, and other memorable and note-worthy matters are described by men of ancienter times, such as follow:
<lb/>
<lb/>Column 1 verso/left
<lb/>PTOLEMEY ALEXANDRIA.
<lb/>CAIVS PLINIVS 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 books of his Natural history.
<lb/>ARISTOTELES DE MVNDO written and dedicated to Ale-
<lb/>	xander the Great.
<lb/>STRABO in 17. books.
<lb/>SOLINVS POLYHISTOUNCLEAR.
<lb/>POMPONIVS MELA.
<lb/>DIONYSIVS APHER and his Expositor.
<lb/>EVSTATHIVS.
<lb/>APVLEIVS in his booke of the World.
<lb/>DIODORVS SICVLVS in his fiue former books.
<lb/>MARTIANVS CAPELLA.
<lb/>PAVLVS OROSIVS in the beginning of his History.
<lb/>AETHICVS and another of that name surnamed SOPHISTA, not
<lb/>	yet printed.
<lb/>IVLIVS the Oratour called by Cassiodore, PRIMVS.
<lb/>BEROSVS described the antiquitie of the World.
<lb/>ANTONIVS AVGVSTVS (if the title be true) set downe the
<lb/>	Iournals of the Romane empire.
<lb/>SEXTVS AVIENVS, the sea coasts.
<lb/>STEPHANVS, the cities.
<lb/>VIKIVS SEQVESTER, in an Alphabeticall order, the Riuers,
<lb/>	Fountaines, Lakes, Woods, Hilles, and Nations thereof.
<lb/>
<lb/>By new Writers, as
<lb/>
<lb/>RAPHAEL VOLATERANVS.
<lb/>ABILFEDEA ISHMAEL, in the Arabian tongue.
<lb/>IOANNES HONTERVS; and HIERONYMVS OLIVERIVS UNCLEAR:
<lb/>	both in verse.
<lb/>BARTHOLIMVS in the eighth booke of Austria.
<lb/>SEBASTIAN MVNSTER, that learned Diuine, diligent Histori-
<lb/>	an, painfull Hebrician and Linguist, well studied in all maner
<lb/>	of learning, and vnto whom the learned Student is so much
<lb/>	beholding.
<lb/>ANTONIVS the Archbishop of Florence, in his Historie, in the
<lb/>	third chapter of the first Title.
<lb/>DOMINICVS NIGER.
<lb/>IOHN AVENTINE in his second booke of his Annals.
<lb/>IOHN CAMERS in his Commentaries vpon Solinus.
<lb/>GEORGE RYTHAIMER.
<lb/>IOACHIM VADIAN.
<lb/>PETRVS IOANNES OLIVARIVS vpon Mela.
<lb/>LAVRENTIVS CORVINVS NOVOF.
<lb/>ANTONIVS VERONENSIS.
<lb/>
<lb/>Column 2 r.
<lb/>
<lb/>GVALTERVS LVDOVICVS, in his Mirrour of Looking-glasse
<lb/>	of the World.
<lb/>S. ISIDORE of SIVILL in Spaine.
<lb/>MICHAEL of VILLANOVA, in his Commentary vpon Ptolemey.
<lb/>ZACHARIAS LILIVS VICENT.
<lb/>HIERONYMVS GIRAVA in the Spanish tongue.
<lb/>ALEXANDER CITOLINVS, in his Typocosmia or Patern of the
<lb/>	World written in the Italian tongue.
<lb/>VINCENTIVS BELVACENSIS in the Mirrour of Histories the
<lb/>	second booke
<lb/>GVILIELMVS POSTELLVS Barentonius.
<lb/>Sr. IOHN MANDEVILL and his companion of his trauels.
<lb/>ODERICVS of FRIVLY.
<lb/>MICHAEL NEANDER of Soraw.
<lb/>GAVDENTIVS MERVLA in his 5. booke of memorable things.
<lb/>FRANCISCVS MONACHI, in his Epistle to the Archbishop of
<lb/>	Panormus.
<lb/>ANDREAS THEVETVS, FRANCISVS BELLEFORESTIVS,
<lb/>	and PETRVS HEYNSIVS, in French: but this latter also in
<lb/>	Dutch rythmes of verse.
<lb/>LAVRENTIVS ANANIENSIS, in the Italian tongue.
<lb/>ANTONIVS PINETVS, in French: and he hath withal set
<lb/>	forth many Tables and Mappes (as the title sheweth) of Coun-
<lb/>	tries, Cities and Townes, aswell of Europe, as of Afrike, Asia
<lb/>    and America.
<lb/>IVLIVS BALLINVS, hath put forth the Plots and drafts of the
<lb/>    most famous Cities of the whole world, with a briefe historical
<lb/>	discourse, written in the Tuscane tongue. The same is done by
<lb/>GEORGIVS BRVNO, in Latine, but much more beautifully and
<lb/>	curiously.
<lb/>BENEDICTVS BORDONIVS, hath described all the Ilands of
<lb/>	the World. So also hath
<lb/>THOMAS PORCACCIVS: both in the Italian tongue.
<lb/>WOLFGANGVS LASIVS, and
<lb/>IOANNES GOROPIVS BECANVS, the originall and shifting
<lb/>	of the nations of the same.
<lb/>PETRVS APPIANVS, and
<lb/>BARTHOLOMAEVS AMANTIVS, haue gathered the ancient In-
<lb/>	scriptions: and so hath
<lb/>MARTINVS SMETIVS, but with greater diligence and care than
<lb/>	ordinary.
<lb/>IOANNES BOHEMVS, and ALEXANDER SARDVS haue writ-
<lb/>	ten of the maners, rites and customes of all nations and people
<lb/>	of it. The same hath
<lb/>FRANCISCVS BFLLEFORESTIVS done in the French tongue.
</ab>

</div></body></text>