<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f025"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--I, Grace Avery, worked on seq, 26 of this text.--></personalstmt> 
<lb/>  That all this [Hemisphere] or halfe-rundle (which is called [America]), and in regard of the large extension, 
<lb/>The New world thould lie concealed from our ancestors, till the yeere of Christ 1492, at what time 
<lb/>[Christopher Columbus] a Genoway first discovered the fame; is a matter surpassing the measure of human 
<lb/>admitation. For considering both the diligence of ancient Geographers in describing the World, and 
<lb/>the commodious opportunitie of most large Empires for the searching out of new [Regions], the also the insatiable auarice of mankinde, leauing nothing vnattempted for the attaining of Golde and Siluer, 
<lb/>where with these [Countries] incredibly abound; I have often wondered, how it could so long have beene 
<lb/>hidden from our World. Some that which suppose that this [Continent] was described by Platovn-
<lb/>der the name of Atlas : my selfe also am of opinion, that Plutarch speaking of the face in the bodie of
<lb/>The Moone, makes mention there of vnder the name of a [Maine continent.] Some thinke that Seneca tauitht with a Poeticall furie,
<lb/>prefaged the discouerie hereof in these Propheticall verses in the very end of the 2.Act.of Medea:
<lb/><p rend="left">
<lb/>—venient annis
<lb/>Secularseris, quibus Oceanus
<lb/>Vincularerum laxet &amp; ingens
<lb/>Pateat tellus, Typhisgnouos
<lb/>Detegat Orbes,
<lb/>Nec Sit terris ultima Thyle.</p>
<lb/><p rend="middle">
<lb/>In English Thus:</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">
<lb/>Long hence those yeeres will come,
<lb/>When th'Ocean shall dissolue
<lb/>Natures saft bonds and barres.
<lb/>Then shall huge lands appear,
<lb/>Typlhis shall then detect
<lb/>New worlds; not Thyle then
<lb/>Shall bound the paths of men.</p>
<lb/>Like to those Sihyllin verses, which (as [Iacobus Nauarchus] writeth) were found at the foot of the promontorie of the Moone
<lb/>(commonly called Rochan de Sinna) vpon the Ocean sea-shore, ingrauen vpon a source-square pillar, in the time of [Don Emmanuel]
<lb/>King of Portugall, to this or the like purpose:
<lb/><p rend="left">
<lb/>Volunetur Faxaliteris &amp; oridinere rectis,
<lb/>Cùmvideas Occidens Orientus Opes.
<lb/>Ganges, Indues, Tagus, erit mirabile vifu,
<lb/>Merces commutabitfuas vterquefibi.</p>
<lb/><p rend="middle">
<lb/>In English Thus:</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">
<lb/>The stone with my stick letters, row'ld shall bee,
<lb/>When West the treasures of the East shall see.
<lb/>The Portugals and Indians (a thing admir'd)
<lb/>Shall truck their wares, on either part desir'd.</p>
<lb/>Howbeit, that these verses are not ancient, but grauen in our times; nor part of Sibylles Prophesies, but {counterfeit}; I was {ad-
<lb/>uettifed} (being in hand with the second edition of this my Theatrum) from Rome, by Cesar Orlando a Ciuilian, in his letters, out of 
<lb/>some printed works of {Gasper Vareriui}, in which since that my felf haue read fame. And afterward I found it confirmed by 
<lb/>Amil Resend in his antiques of Portugale: namely, that in the time of Don Emmanuel King of Portugale, one Hermes Caiado of 
<lb/>The same country, caused them to be ingrauen and buried in the earth: and when he supposed that the marble began to corrupt 
<lb/>with the moisture of the ground; pretending some cause of recreation, he inuites his friends to a countrey-house, neere vnto 
<lb/>which this fained Prophefie lay hid. Wherefore benign all set at meat, in comes his Bailiffe with newes, that his Labourers had by 
<lb/>Chance digged up a stone engrauen with letters. They all immediately runne forth, they reade it, they admire it, they highly esteeme 
<lb/>it, and are ready to adore it &amp;c. See how apt Caiado was to delude his friends. [Marina Siculus] in his Chronicle of [Spaine] writes, 
<lb/>that there was found in Gold-mines an ancient piece of coine with Augustus Cesars image vpon it, and for the more confirmation 
<lb/>of the matter, that it was fent by [Archbishop of Consance to the Pope]. But I am of opinion, that it was there lost by the same fa- 
<lb/>milie which first found it. Iosephus Acosta in his booke De Natura noui orbis indeuours by many reasons to proue, that this part of
<lb/>America was originally inhabited by certaine [Indians], forced thither by tempestuous weather ouer the South fea which now 
<lb/>they call Mare del Zur. But to me it seemes more probable, out of the historie of the two Zeni gentlemen of [Venice] (which I haue
<lb/>put downe before the Table of the South sea, and before that [Scandia]) that this New world many ages past was entered vpon by
<lb/>some islanders of [Europe], as namely of [Groenland], [Island], and [Frisland]; being much neerer thereunto than the Indians, nor disioy-
<lb/>ned thence (as appears out of the Map) by an Ocean so huge, and to the Indians so vnnauiagble. Also, what else may we conie-
<lb/>eture to be signified by this word Norumbega (the name of a [North region of America]) but that from [Norway], signifying a North 
<lb/>land, some [Colonie] in times past hath hither beene transplanted? But why in mine opinion the maine Ocean was neuer failed by 
<lb/>ancient Nauigatours, I have declared in my Thesaurus Geographieus, speaking of Ophir. 
<lb/>	All this part of the [World], (except the North treat thereof, whole Coasts are not yet discovered) hath in these last times beene 
<lb/>failed round about. From North to South it stretcheth in forme of two Peninfulae or Demi-ifles, which are feuered by a very nar- 
<lb/>row isthmos or neck-land. The Northernmost of the two conteineth New Spaine, the prouince of Mexico, the countrey of Florida and New-found-land. But the Southermost (which the Spaniards call Terra firma) contains Peru and Brasil. A description of all 
<lb/>which regions the studious in Geography may reade in Leuinus Apolonius, in the Decads of Peter Martyr, and in Maximilianus Transiluanus, white writ all in Latine. Also to this purpose you haue many things worthy the obseruatioin the Iessutes Epistles,
<lb/>and in Maffeius his story of the Indies. Postellus also promiseth Discourses of West-Indie-matters : and so doth Fredericus Furius 
<lb/>Cariolanus. 
<lb/>These that follow haue purposely written of [America], but all in their mother-languages, and for the most part in Spanish; but 
<lb/>the better halfe of them are translated into Italian:
<lb/><p rend="left">
<lb/>[Pedro Cieca De Leon.]
<lb/>[Gonsalvo Fernando De Oviedo.]
<lb/>[Fernando Cortez.]
<lb/>[Peter Alvarado.]
<lb/>[Diego Godoya.]
<lb/>[Alvarez Nvnnez.]
<lb/>[Nvnnez De Gusman.]
<lb/>[Francis Vlloa.]
<lb/>[Francis Vasquez De Coronado.]
<lb/>[Antonie Mendoca.]</p>
<lb/><p rend="right">
<lb/>[Frier Marco De Nizza.]
<lb/>[Fernando Alarchon.]
<lb/>[Francis Xeres.]
<lb/>[Iohn Verarzano.]
<lb/>[Americo Vespvtio.]
<lb/>[Francis Lopez De Gomara.]
<lb/>[Ierome Benzo], in Italian.
<lb/>[Iaques Carthier], and
<lb/>[Andrew Thevet], wrote in French.
<lb/>[Iohn Standen], in Dutch.</p>
<lb/>Diuerse of which Authors, and many that haue written since, are translated into English in the third volume of M. Hak’uyts
<lb/> English Voyages.
</ab>

</div></body></text>