<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f029"/>
<respStmt> <!--I, Alex Wheeler, transcribed and encoded seq. 30 of this text--> </respStmt>
<ab>
<figure rend="middle-top"><fw type="pageNum" place="top">7</fw></figure>
<lb/><figure rend="middle-top"><figDesc><head>NEVV SPAINE</head></figDesc></figure>
<lb/>This Prouince was about the yeere <date when="1518">1518</date> forcibly subdued to the
<lb/>Spanish gouernment, vnder the command and conduct of <persName ref="#corlez">Fer-
<lb/>nando Corlez</persName>: who with the great slaughter of his owne people,
<lb/>but farre greater of the inhabitants fighting for their liberty, con-
<lb/>quered the fame. It is a region rich of siluer and golde: for it
<lb/>hath very many riuers yeelding sands or graines of perfect gold.
<lb/>Vpon the coast of this countrey are many commodious fishings for pearle. Salt
<lb/>lakes here are diuers, the water whereof through the heat of the Sunne is conuer-
<lb/>ted into excellent salt. Here is great abundance of <hi rend="fiftula">Cassia fiftula</hi>, and a kind of fruit in
<lb/>the Mexican language called <hi rend="italic">Cacao</hi>, somewhat resembling an Almond: which is
<lb/>with them very highly esteemed; for hereof they make a kinde of drinke, to their
<lb/>owne taste most delicate. The seas and riuers belonging to this countrey abound
<lb/>mightily with fish. Their riuers also breed Crocodiles, whose flesh is food to the
<lb/>inhabitants. In these places this creature is for the most part aboue twenty foot
<lb/>long. It is a countrey very mountainous and beset here and there with most lofty
<lb/>and cragged rocks. So great is the diuersity of languages in these regions, that one
<lb/>cannot vnderstand another without an Interpreter. The principall Colonies to
<lb/>be seene in this Table, which in <placeName ref="#spaine">New Spaine</placeName> haue been planted by the Spaniards, 
<lb/>are first <placeName ref="#compostella">Compostella</placeName>, the feat of a bishop, and one of the Kings counsels. <placeName ref="#colima">Colima</placeName>, 
<lb/>by another name called the city of the Purification. <placeName ref="#guadalajara">Guadalajara</placeName>, a towne most fa-
<lb/>mous, and head of the Kingdome of <placeName ref="#gallicia">New Gallicia</placeName>. <placeName ref="#mecboacan">Mecboacan</placeName>, a Bishops sea also.
<lb/><placeName ref="#sacatula">Sacatula</placeName>, the city of the Angels, a mother-towne and a Bishoprick. <placeName ref="#mexico">Mexico</placeName>, a Kingly
<lb/>city, or rather Queene of all the cities in the New world; situate vpon the banke
<lb/>of a lake, or rather of a fenne: yea the very ground-plot of this city is so fenny, that
<lb/>you cannot come thither, nor depart thence but ouer bridges and cawseys. The 
<lb/>lake adioyning is falt, being six leagues long and fiue broad. Fishes it hath none,
<lb/>but very small ones; which more aptly may be called wormes than fishes: of
<lb/>whose putrefaction, which is there caused by the heat of the Summer, the aire is some-
<lb/>times so infected, that it is most vnholesome dwelling there: yet is it as much fre-
<lb/>quented with inhabitants and merchants, as any mart-towne in <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>. It is a large 
<lb/>city, for in compasse it containeth about three leagues. The other lake adioining 
<lb/>to this, is fresh water, and very plentifull of fish; wherein also stand many townes.
<lb/>There are likewise a great number vpon the banks of either lake. In this city (as
<lb/><persName ref="#giraua">Ierome Giraua</persName> reporteth) there was by <persName ref="#paul">Pope Paul</persName> the third established the feat of 
<lb/>an Archbishop, in the yeere <date when="1547">1547</date>. 
<lb/>This citie was taken by the Spaniards 140 yeeres after the first foundation
<lb/>thereof; <persName ref="#montezuma">Montezuma</persName> at the same time being King, the ninth in number. A won-
<lb/>der, how in so few yeeres it should grow to such largenesse and magnificence.
<lb/>The nature, situation, and customes of this citie and of the territory adiacent, who
<lb/>desires more perfectly to know, may reade the relations of <persName ref="#corlez">Fernando Corlez</persName>. Ex-
<lb/>tant they are in the volume intituled <hi rend="italic">Nouus Orbis</hi>; and in the volume of Nauiga-
<lb/>tions printed at <placeName ref="#venice">Venice</placeName> in Italian: but especially <persName ref="#Gonsaluo">John Gonsaluo </persName>, who in his little
<lb/>booke of <placeName ref="#china">China</placeName> hath a most large description of this region. You haue also many
<lb/>notable discourses hereof in the third Volume of <persName ref="#Hakluyts">M. Hakluyts  </persName> English voyages. 
</ab>

</div></body></text>