<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FirstPass"><body><div><pb facs="#f029"/>
<ab>
<lb/>Sacatula, the city of Angels, a mother-towne and a Bishoprick. Mexico, aKingly
<lb/>city, or rather Queene of all the cities in the New World; situate vpon the banke
<lb/>of a lake, or rather of a fenne: yea the very ground-plot of this city is so fenny,that
<lb/>you cannot come thither, nor depart thence but ouer bridges and cawfeys. The
<lb/>lake adioyning is salt, being fix leagues long and fiue broad. Fishes it hath none,
<lb/>but very small ones; which more aptly may be called worms than fishes: of
<lb/>whole putrefaction, which is there caused by the heat of Summer, the aire is some-
t<lb/>imes so infected, that it is most vnholesome dwelling there: yet it is as much fre-
<lb/>quented with inhabitants and merchants, as any mart-towne in Europe. It is a large
<lb/>city; for in compasse it containeth about three leagues. The other lake adioining
<lb/>to this, is fresh water, and very plentifull of fish; wherein also stand many townes.
<lb/>There are likewise a great number vpon the banks of either lake. In this city (as
J<lb/>erome Girana reporteth) there was by Pope Paul the third established the seat of
<lb/>an Arch bishop, in the yeere 1547.
<lb/>	This citie was taken by the Spaniards 140 yeeres after the first foundation thereof; Montezuma at the same time being King, the ninth in number. A won-
<lb/>der, how in so few yeeres it should grow to such largenesse and magnificence.
<lb/>The nature, situation, and customes of this citie and of the territory adiacent, who desires more perfectly to know, may reade the relations of Fernando Cortez. Ex-
<lb/>tant they are in the volume intituled Nouus orbis; and in the volume of Nauiga-
t<lb/>ions printed at Venice in Italian: but especially John Gonfaluo, who in this little
<lb/>booke of China hath a most large description of this region. You haue also many
<lb/>notable discourses hereof in the third Volume of M. Hakluyts English voyages.
</ab>

</div></body></text>