<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FirstPass"><body><div><pb facs="#f011"/>
<ab>
<lb/>my purpose was to represent unto thy view whatsoeuer heretofore thou had'st, or now hast, in any Geographical or Choro-
<lb/>graphical Chartes here and there lately or long since set out that euer csame to my hands, or were possibly to bee gotten for
<lb/>loue or money. Of all country's whose descriptions are set out in out in Geographicall Tables, we have selected one (for of some
<lb/>there are diuers) which in our indgement seemed to bee the best and most exact: Which, notwithstanding that it were, by
<lb/>the first draught of the Authour somewhat large and broad, we haue brought into that small forme, as might agree with this
<lb/>our worke, and that the whole Mappe might be contein'd in one leafe: or, which sometime thou shalt obserue we haue done,
<lb/>as thou may'st see, that in one leafe many might bee contein'd and expressed: yet so as nothing, no neuer so small a thing, is
<lb/>either omitted or altered that was to bee found in the greater: except it be this, which oftentimes thou shalt finde, that the
<lb/>names of places and other things, which in the first Copies could hardly be read,in these our Mappes we haue so expressed, that
<lb/>they may perfectly be read of any man. And sometime, where occasion did serue,or need require,and the place would permit,
<lb/>unto the modern and usuall names of certaine places, wee haue added the ancient names mentioned by old writers, but now
<lb/>uulgary unknowne. Which, as we doubt not, we haue done with the good leaue and liking of the Authours themselues:
<lb/>so I hope it will be a thing very well pleasing to all such as are readers and students of old Histories and Antiquities. In those
<lb/>Mappes, which haue their Authours names written upon them, we haue, as I laid, altered nothing at all, excepting two or
<lb/>three of the Marine tracts of the Low-countreys, which the see hath changed since the time that their descriptions
<lb/>were first set foorth: As for examples sake,in Flaunders,ouer against Zeland,not farre from the towne Wateruliet, where
<lb/>by the goodnesse and great benefit of Almighty God, long after that the description of this Countrey was first set out , 
<lb/>the Maine-land was much enlarged and had gotten an advantage of the Sea: wee there haue altered the forme of that Mappe,
<lb/>according as the place is found to be at this day. The description of which plot ground we obteined of Master Marke Lau-
<lb/>rine,the Lord and owner, thereof, a braue gentleman, greatlt renowmedboth for the noble stocke from whence hee is descen-
<lb/>ded, as also for his wisdome and great experience. Eut in other Mappes, which had no name of the Authour subscribed
<lb/>unto them,we were somewhat more bold : for in these, in some places, at our discretion, where we thought good,wee haue al-
<lb/>tered some-things, some-things we haue put out, and otherwhere, if it seemed to be necessary,we haue put in. Of some Coun-
<lb/>treys also,that we might,as much as in us did lye,make up our iust number and fill up our ranke, be haue made some Mappes
<lb/>of our owne, that there might as few Mappes be wanting, as possibly might be. In the abridgement and bringing of those
<lb/>Mappes,which had as i said the names of the Authours added unto them,into a letter frome, we haue used that faithfulnesse
<lb/>and diligence, that we hope to deserue thankes not onely of the Reader, but also euen of the Authours themselues, or at least
<lb/>we haue dealt so in them , that no man need be asham'd of these of ours whatsoeuer they be; yea he may aswell acknowledge
<lb/>and take this little one of ours,for his owne , as that first set out by himselfe. For wee have endeuoured to the
<lb/>uttermost of our power in this our worke, if it were possible, to deserue thankes of the Authours, if not, uet by no meanes to
<lb/>displease them: Not to follow or imitate that bad custome of some men in these our dayes, who, that they mat seeme to the
<lb/>world to set fouurth some new thing, does nothing els but alter the workes and labours of other men, and ostentimes, out of those
<lb/>which are good, to select that which is not good, and to sell it commonly for the best: Sometimes by adding something at their
<lb/>pleasure, and in some places againe taking out and detracting something, and witball either by concealing the right Authors
<lb/>names, or setting to their owne, or seyning a name of some one or other, they thinke to please the vulgar sort with nouelties,
<lb/>that that their worke may sell the better; and they may rake money together they care not how: For we were not mooued to
<lb/>undertake this labour by any couetous desire of getting much by it, but even of a willing and forward minde that wee had to
<lb/>helpe and further those that had a love and affection to these studies, not any whit respecting the gayning of any vaine glory
<lb/>and commendation by other mens labours. For what need we to make new Mappes, when as the old Mappes of other men,
<lb/>now extant, would serue our turne? Some there are peraduenture, which will looke to finde in this our Theater more de-
<lb/>scriptions of particular Countreys, for every man naturally, for the love that he beareth to his native soil, would, I doubt
<lb/>not, with that it were here seuerally described amongst the rest but let them know, that those which are here missing, are
<lb/>not left out and omitted, either by our negligence, or for that we were lothe to be at that cost and charges: but because that ei-
<lb/>ther we never saw any such, or at leastwayes for that there never came any such to our hands. If there be any man, which
<lb/>either hath any such, or knoweth where there may be had, him we would earnestly entreate, that be would be the meanes to
<lb/>helpe us unto them, assuredly promising him, that we will, at our owne coft and charges, not without great thankes to him,
<lb/>and a most honourable mention of his name, cause them to be cut and imprinted apart and by themselves, that hereafter they
<lb/>may be inserted into this our Booke, either in their owne place, elsewhere, as any man shall like best.
<lb/>	
<lb/>Of the Order also by us here obserued in the place of these our Mappes, I thinke it not amisse, gentle Reader, to speake a
<lb/>word or two, and to acquaint thee with our purpose: that if peraduenture there be any man, which doeth thinke, that
<lb/>can be looked for at our hands. First of all, we present unto thy view an Vniuersall Mappe of the whole world: Then,
<lb/>the foure quarters of principall parts of the same; to wit, Europe, Asia, Africa, and America: in this following dame Na-
<lb/>ture, in which alwayes before the parts can be, the whole, whereof they be the parts, must of necesitie first be. Next after
<lb/>these we have put the seuerall and particular Countreys of these parts, beginning at the West part of the world, in this fol-
<lb/>lowing Ptolemey the Prince of Geographers, and almost all others that have written of this argument: And so the Pro-
<lb/>vinces and particular countreys of America do first put foorth and shew themselves: next to these do follow the Brittifh
<lb/>Iles, after them Spaine, and then France. From hence we passe to Germany: whole Countreys being after our maner dili-
<lb/>gently surueyed, from Heluetia or Switzerland we passed over the Mountaines into Italy, whiches the next countrey unto
<lb/>it Eastward, purposing also to view all the Provinces thereof seuerally. From thence we croped the Sea Sayl’d into
<lb/>Greece. Whereupon going into Slauonia, we surueyed all the Countreys seuerally which do vulgarly speake the Slaunian
<lb/>tongue,
</ab>

</div></body></text>