<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="TEI Tagged Transcription">
<body><div>
<pb facs="#f000"/>
<personalstmt> <!--This my personal Statement--> </personalstmt>
<ab>
        <lb/><fw type="header" place="top">THEATRVM ORBIS TERRARVM</fw>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">THEA</hi>
        <lb/><placeName ref="#antwerp">ORBIS TERRA</placeName>
        <lb/><persName ref="#ortelius">Abraham Ortelius</persName>
        <lb/><date when="1606">1606</date>
        <lb/><foreign xml:lang="la">Braccas meas vescimini!</foreign>
        <lb/><note type="historical"><!--This edition was printed in--><placeName ref="#london"><!--London--></placeName> <!--during --><persName ref="#james1"><!--King James--></persName><!--’ reign.--></note>
        <lb/><unclear reason="faded" cert="low">Ortel...</unclear>
        <lb/><supplied reason="lost" resp="#leblanc">Ortelius</supplied>
        <lb/>
            <choice>
                <orig>IOHN</orig>
                <reg>John</reg>
            </choice>
        <lb/>
            <choice>
                <orig><unclear>Orteli...</unclear></orig>
                <reg><supplied reason="lost">Ortelius</supplied></reg>
            </choice>
        <lb/><hi rend="italic">The Theatre of the Whole World</hi>
        <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">WORLD</fw>
        <lb/><fw type="pageNum" place="top">1</fw>
        <lb/><figure type="ornament">
                <head>Fleuron</head>
                <figDesc>Decorative floral ornament</figDesc>
            </figure>
        <lb/><signature type="printed">LL</signature>
</ab>
<pb facs="#f001"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.2
</ab>

<pb facs="#f002"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.3
</ab>

<pb facs="#f003"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.4
</ab>

<pb facs="#f004"/>
<ab>
<lb/>THEA
<lb/>TRVM
<lb/>ORBIS
<lb/>TERRA
<lb/>RVM
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>ABRAHAMI ORTELI ANTVERP.
<lb/>GEOGRAPHI REGII.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>THE THEATRE OF THE WHOLE
<lb/>WORLD: SET FORTH BY THAT
<lb/>Excellent Geographer Abraham Ortelius.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>LONDON,
<lb/>Printed by IOHN NORTON; Printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie in 
<lb/>Hebrew, Greeke, and Latine. 1606.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f005"/>
<ab>
<lb/>The sway, by Sea &amp; Land, grat IAMES doth beare,
<lb/>His Birth, His Bloud, These Kingdomes figure here:
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>But, were his seuerall vertues to be crown'd
<lb/>A World, past thine, Ortelius, must be found.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f006"/>
<ab>
<lb/>ABRAHAMI ORTELII
<lb/>QVEM VRBS VRBIVM ANTVERPIA EDITIT,
<lb/>REX REGVM PHILLIPVS GEOGRAPHVM HABVIT,
<lb/>MONVMENVM HIC VIDES.
<lb/>BREVIS TERRA EVM CAPTIT
<lb/>QVI IPSE ORBEM TERRARVM CEPIT,
<lb/>QVI IPSE ORBEM TERRARVM CEPTIT,
<lb/>STILO ET TABVLIS ILLVSTRAVIT:
<lb/>SED MENTE CONTEMPSIT,
<lb/>QVA CAELVM ET ALTA SVSPEXIT
<lb/>CONSTANS ADVERSVM SPES AVT METVS.
<lb/>AMICITIAE CVLTOR, CANDORE FIDE, OFFICIIS,
<lb/>QVIETIS CVLTOR, SINE LITE, VXORE, PROLE.
<lb/>VITAM HABVIT, QVALE ALIVS, VOTVM.
<lb/>VT NVNC QVOQVE AETERNA EI QVIES SIT
<lb/>VOTIS FAVE LECTOR.
<lb/>OBIIT IIII.KAL. IVLII. ANNO CIƆ.XCIIX.
<lb/>VIXIT ANN. LXXI. MENSS.II. DIES IIXX.
<lb/>COLII EX SORORE NEPOTES B.M.POSS.
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>CONTEMNO ET ORNO MENTE, MANV
</ab>

<pb facs="#f007"/>
<ab>
<lb/>TO THE
<lb/>MOST HIGH,
<lb/>MOST MIGHT,
<lb/>AND MOST HAPPY 
<lb/>PRINCE, IAMES BY THE
<lb/>GRACE OF GOD, KING
<lb/>OF GREAT BRITAINE,
<lb/>FRANCE AND IRE-
<lb/>LAND, DEFEN-
<lb/>DER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c.
<lb/>IOHN NORTON
<lb/>HIS MA-
<lb/>IESTIES MOST 
<lb/>HVMBLE AND
<lb/>FAITHFVLL SER-
<lb/>[V]ANT CONSECRATETH
<lb/>THESE IMMORTALL LA-
<lb/>BOVRS OF ABRAHAM
<lb/>[OR]TELIVS, TRANS-
<lb/>[L]ATED INTO
<lb/>ENGLISH
</ab>
<ab>
<lb/>[fleurons]
</ab>

<pb facs="#f008"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.9
</ab>

<pb facs="#f009"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.10
</ab>

<pb facs="#f010"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.11
</ab>

<pb facs="#f011"/>
<ab>
<lb/>my purpose was to represent unto thy view whatsoeuer heretofore thou had'st, or now hast, in any Geographical or Choro-
<lb/>graphical Chartes here and there lately or long since set out that euer csame to my hands, or were possibly to bee gotten for
<lb/>loue or money. Of all country's whose descriptions are set out in out in Geographicall Tables, we have selected one (for of some
<lb/>there are diuers) which in our indgement seemed to bee the best and most exact: Which, notwithstanding that it were, by
<lb/>the first draught of the <persName>Authour</persName> somewhat large and broad, we haue brought into that small forme, as might agree with this
<lb/>our worke, and that the whole <placeName>Mappe</placeName> might be contein'd in one leafe: or, which sometime thou shalt obserue we haue done,
<lb/>as thou may'st see, that in one leafe many might bee contein'd and expressed: yet so as nothing, no neuer so small a thing, is
<lb/>either omitted or altered that was to bee found in the greater: except it be this, which oftentimes thou shalt finde, that the
<lb/>names of places and other things, which in the first Copies could hardly be read,in these our Mappes we haue so expressed, that
<lb/>they may perfectly be read of any man. And sometime, where occasion did serue,or need require,and the place would permit,
<lb/>unto the modern and usuall names of certaine places, wee haue added the ancient names mentioned by old writers, but now
<lb/>uulgary unknowne. Which, as we doubt not, we haue done with the good leaue and liking of the <persName>Authours</persName> themselues:
<lb/>so I hope it will be a thing very well pleasing to all such as are readers and students of old Histories and Antiquities. In those
<lb/>Mappes, which haue their Authours names written upon them, we haue, as I laid, altered nothing at all, excepting two or
<lb/>three of the Marine tracts of the Low-countreys, which the see hath changed since the time that their descriptions
<lb/>were first set foorth: As for examples sake,in Flaunders,ouer against <placeName>Zeland</placeName>,not farre from the towne Wateruliet, where
<lb/>by the goodnesse and great benefit of <persName>Almighty God</persName>, long after that the description of this Countrey was first set out , 
<lb/>the Maine-land was much enlarged and had gotten an advantage of the Sea: wee there haue altered the forme of that Mappe,
<lb/>according as the place is found to be at this day. The description of which plot ground we obteined of Master Marke Lau-
<lb/>rine,the Lord and owner, thereof, a braue gentleman, greatlt renowmedboth for the noble stocke from whence hee is descen-
<lb/>ded, as also for his wisdome and great experience. Eut in other Mappes, which had no name of the <persName>Authour</persName> subscribed
<lb/>unto them,we were somewhat more bold : for in these, in some places, at our discretion, where we thought good,wee haue al-
<lb/>tered some-things, some-things we haue put out, and otherwhere, if it seemed to be necessary,we haue put in. Of some Coun-
<lb/>treys also,that we might,as much as in us did lye,make up our iust number and fill up our ranke, be haue made some Mappes
<lb/>of our owne, that there might as few Mappes be wanting, as possibly might be. In the abridgement and bringing of those
<lb/>Mappes,which had as i said the names of the <persName>Authours</persName> added unto them,into a letter frome, we haue used that faithfulnesse
<lb/>and diligence, that we hope to deserue thankes not onely of the Reader, but also euen of the Authours themselues, or at least
<lb/>we haue dealt so in them , that no man need be asham'd of these of ours whatsoeuer they be; yea he may aswell acknowledge
<lb/>and take this little one of ours,for his owne , as that first set out by himselfe. For wee have endeuoured to the
<lb/>uttermost of our power in this our worke, if it were possible, to deserue thankes of the <persName>Authours</persName>, if not, uet by no meanes to
<lb/>displease them: Not to follow or imitate that bad custome of some men in these our dayes, who, that they mat seeme to the
<lb/>world to set fouurth some new thing, does nothing els but alter the workes and labours of other men, and ostentimes, out of those
<lb/>which are good, to select that which is not good, and to sell it commonly for the best: Sometimes by adding something at their
<lb/>pleasure, and in some places againe taking out and detracting something, and witball either by concealing the right <persName>Authors</persName>
<lb/>names, or setting to their owne, or seyning a name of some one or other, they thinke to please the vulgar sort with nouelties,
<lb/>that that their worke may sell the better; and they may rake money together they care not how: For we were not mooued to
<lb/>undertake this labour by any couetous desire of getting much by it, but even of a willing and forward minde that wee had to
<lb/>helpe and further those that had a love and affection to these studies, not any whit respecting the gayning of any vaine glory
<lb/>and commendation by other mens labours. For what need we to make new Mappes, when as the old Mappes of other men,
<lb/>now extant, would serue our turne? Some there are peraduenture, which will looke to finde in this our Theater more de-
<lb/>scriptions of particular Countreys, (for every man naturally, for the love that he beareth to his native soil, would, I doubt
<lb/>not, with that it were here seuerally described amongst the rest but let them know, that those which are here missing, are
<lb/>not left out and omitted, either by our negligence, or for that we were lothe to be at that cost and charges: but because that ei-
<lb/>ther we never saw any such, or at leastwayes for that there never came any such to our hands. If there be any man, which
<lb/>either hath any such, or knoweth where there may be had, him we would earnestly entreate, that be would be the meanes to
<lb/>helpe us unto them, assuredly promising him, that we will, at our owne coft and charges, not without great thankes to him,
<lb/>and a most honourable mention of his name, cause them to be cut and imprinted apart and by themselves, that hereafter they
<lb/>may be inserted into this our Booke, either in their owne place, elsewhere, as any man shall like best.
<lb/>	
<lb/>Of the Order also by us here obserued in the place of these our Mappes, I thinke it not amisse, gentle Reader, to speake a
<lb/>word or two, and to acquaint thee with our purpose: that if peraduenture there be any man, which doeth thinke, that
<lb/>can be looked for at our hands. First of all, we present unto thy view an Vniuersall Mappe of the whole world: Then,
<lb/>the foure quarters of principall parts of the same; to wit, <placeName>Europe</placeName>, <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <placeName>Africa</placeName>, and <placeName>America</placeName>: in this following dame Na-
<lb/>ture, in which alwayes before the parts can be, the whole, whereof they be the parts, must of necesitie first be. Next after
<lb/>these we have put the seuerall and particular Countreys of these parts, beginning at the West part of the world, in this fol-
<lb/>lowing Ptolemey the Prince of Geographers, and almost all others that have written of this argument: And so the Pro-
<lb/>vinces and particular countreys of <placeName>America</placeName> do first put foorth and shew themselves: next to these do follow the Brittifh
<lb/>Iles, after them Spaine, and then France. From hence we passe to Germany: whole Countreys being after our maner dili-
<lb/>gently surueyed, from <placeName>Heluetia</placeName> or <placeName>Switzerland</placeName> we passed over the Mountaines into <placeName>Italy</placeName>, whiches the next countrey unto
<lb/>it Eastward, purposing also to view all the Provinces thereof seuerally. From thence we croped the Sea Sayl'd into
<lb/>Greece. Whereupon going into <placeName>Slauonia</placeName>, we surueyed all the Countreys seuerally which do vulgarly speake the Slaunian
<lb/>tongue,
</ab>

<pb facs="#f012"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.13
</ab>

<pb facs="#f013"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.14
</ab>

<pb facs="#f014"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.15
</ab>

<pb facs="#f015"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.16
</ab>

<pb facs="#f016"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.17
</ab>

<pb facs="#f017"/>
<ab>
<lb/> <personalstmt><!--We, Haley Jensen and Audrey Gauthier, worked on seq. 18 of this text--></personalstmt>
<lb/> <foreign xml:lang="la">TYPVS ORBIS TERRAVM.</foreign>
<lb/>
<lb/>HOMI 
<lb/>NES HAC LEGE 
<lb/>SVNT GENERATI, 
<lb/>QVI TVERENTVR
<lb/>ILLVM GLOBVM,
<lb/>QVEM IN HOC TEM 
<lb/>PLO MEDIVM VI
<lb/>DES, QVAE TER 
<lb/>RA DICITVR. 
<lb/><hi rend="italic"><persName>Cicero</persName>.</hi>
<lb/>
<lb/>EQVS 
<lb/>VEHENDI 
<lb/>CAVSA, ARANDI 
<lb/>BOS, VENAN'DI
<lb/>ET CVSTODIENDI 
<lb/>CANIS, HOMO AV 
<lb/>TEM ORTVS AD 
<lb/>MVNDVM CON 
<lb/>TEMPLANDVM. 
<lb/><hi rend="italic"><persName>Cicero</persName>.</hi>
<lb/>
<lb/>HOC 
<lb/>EST PVNCTVM, 
<lb/>QVOD INTER TOT. 
<lb/>GENTES FERRO 
<lb/>ET IGNI DIVIDI 
<lb/>TVR,O QVAM RIDI 
<lb/>CVLI SVNT MOR 
<lb/>TALIVM TER
<lb/>MINI?
<lb/><hi rend="italic"><persName>Seneca</persName>.</hi>
<lb/>
<lb/>QVID EI POTEST VIDERI MAGNV <note type="editorial"><!--There is a rip in the page here--></note> IN REBVS HVMANIS, CVI AETER
<lb/>NITAS OMNIS, TOTIVSQVE MVNDI <note type="editorial"><!--There is a rip in the page here--></note> NOTA SIT MAGNITVDO. <persName>CICERO</persName>
<lb/>
<lb/>VTINAM
<lb/>QVEMADMO 
<lb/>DVM VNIVERSA 
<lb/>MVNDI FACIES 
<lb/>IN CONSPECTVM 
<lb/>VENIT, ITA PHI 
<lb/>LOSOPHIA TOTA 
<lb/>NOBIS POSSET 
<lb/>OCCVRRERE. 
<lb/><hi rend="italic"><persName>Seneca</persName>.</hi>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f018"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--We, Audrey Gauthier and Haley Jensen, transcribed and encoded seq 19 of this text at Framingham State University.--></personalstmt>
<lb/> <title><placeName>Evrope</placeName></title>
<lb/><p>In the diuision of the world, diuers haue placed <placeName>Africa</placeName> in the third part : some few haue made no more but <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Europe</placeName> only ; and <placeName>Africa</placeName> they make a part of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, saith <persName>Salustius</persName>. This is that which <persName>S. Paulinus</persName> in <placeName>Aulonius</placeName>, out o
<lb/> the opinion of the same Saluit, thus writeth of : <foreign xml:lang="la">Europam Afiamque duo vel maxima terrae Membra, quibus Lybiam
<lb/>dubie Sallustius addit, Europæ admixtram : poffit quum tertia dici</foreign> : <placeName>Europe</placeName> and <placeName>Asia</placeName> vast, the Earthly globe between 
<lb/>them share. Yet whether <placeName>Africke</placeName> should a part of this our <placeName>Europe</placeName> be ; or make a third part by it selfe, Saluit doth doubt 
<lb/>I see. But <persName>Philostratus</persName> also in <persName>Isocrates</persName> doth diuide the world into <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Europe</placeName> : yea <persName>Isocrates</persName> himself, in his Pane-
<lb/>gyricos. Moreouer in <persName>Varroes</persName> booke <foreign xml:lang="la">De lingua Latina</foreign> these words are read ; As all the world is diuided into <placeName>Heaven</placeName>
<lb/>and <placeName>Earth</placeName> : so <placeName>Heaven</placeName> is seuered into his quarters : and the <placeName>Earth</placeName> into <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Europe</placeName>. Againe the same author in his 
<lb/>booke of Husbandrie writeth thus : first, when as the world, by <persName>Eratosthenes</persName>, was very fully and naturally divided into 
<lb/>two parts, the one toward the South, [<placeName>Asia</placeName> doubtlesse he meaneth ] the other in the north [<placeName>Europe</placeName> we call it.] <persName>S. Augu-
<lb/>stine</persName> in his 16. booke <foreign xml:lang="la">De Ciuitate Dei</foreign> : <persName>Lucane</persName> in his 9. booke: and <persName>Orosius</persName> in the first booke of his history, haue the like
<lb/>wordes to the same sense. Notwithstanding custome since hath preuailed with all historiographers and cosmographers which haue written either in Latine 
<lb/>or Greeke, ioinly to diuide the globe of the earth into these three parts: <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <placeName>Africke</placeName> and <placeName>Europe</placeName>: the last of which we have taken vpon vs to describe in 
<lb/>this place, not only in forme of a mappe or chart, like a Geographer: but in this present discourse, like an historian. Concerning the forme of it therefore, it 
<lb/>is manifold, as <persName>Strabo</persName> writeth. It is a Peninsula or demy-isle, and not an island; although <persName>Silenus</persName>, as <persName>Elianus</persName> writeth, did sometime to <persName>Midas</persName> so relate of
<lb/>it. For it is on all sides, as you may see in the mappe, bounded and beaten with the salt sea, but only upon the East, where it is by a small necke ioined to the 
<lb/>greater <placeName>Asia</placeName>. Yet by what limits they are there distinguished, the ancient and the later writers do not altogether agree. For those which are more ancient 
<lb/>as <persName>Aristotle</persName>, <persName>Plato</persName>, <persName>Herodotus</persName>, and others which do follow their opinion, do diuide <placeName>Europe</placeName> from <placeName>Asia</placeName>, by the riuer <placeName>Phasis</placeName>, (a riuer of Colchis falling 
<lb/>into the <placeName>Euxine sea</placeName>, <placeName>Mar Maiore</placeName>, or <foreign xml:lang="la">Maurothalassa</foreign>, as the greeks call it) neere <placeName>Trapezonda</placeName> : some mappes do now call that riuer <placeName>Fasso</placeName>, others <placeName>Phaz-
<lb/>zeth</placeName>: the Scythians, (as <persName>Theuet</persName> reporteth, Debbaffethca) or which is all one, by that ithmos or neckland which is between the forefaid <placeName>Mar Maiore</placeName> or 
<lb/><placeName>Pontus Euxinus</placeName>, and the <placeName>Caspian sea</placeName> (<placeName>Mar de Cachu</placeName>, the ancient called it <placeName>Mare Hyrcanum</placeName>, the <placeName>Hyrcanie sea</placeName>) which formerly all old writers thought to 
<lb/>be but a bay or gulfe of the Scythian or Northren ocean, as <persName>Strabo</persName>, <persName>Pliny</persName>, <persName>Mela</persName>, <persName>Dionysius</persName>, <persName>Plutarch</persName> (in the life of <persName>Alexander</persName> and in his discourse of the 
<lb/>face in the sphere of the Moone) and <persName>Iornandes</persName> a more late writer, have first recorded. Yet all of them were deceiued. Only <persName>Herodotus</persName> truly (as this 
<lb/>our latter age doth approve and find to be so) doth affirme this to be a sea of it selfe, and to have neither in-let nor out-let, or to be intermeddled with any other 
<lb/>sea. <persName>Dionysius</persName>, <persName>Arrianus</persName>, <persName>Diodorus</persName>, <persName>Polybius</persName>, <persName>Iornandes</persName> and <persName>Ptolemey</persName> have diuided it from <placeName>Asia</placeName> by the riuer <placeName>Tanais</placeName> (<placeName>Don</placeName> or <placeName>Tana</placeName>, as now the 
<lb/>Italians name it) who think that both the rise of this riuer, and the land Northward from where it commeth, are both unknown and uncertaine. All 
<lb/>doubt where to place and lay their bounds : as indeed who never perfectly knew those places toward the East and North, not being then discovered, but only 
<lb/>described by them, from the fabulous reports of others: as for example, the <placeName>Riphæan</placeName> and <placeName>Hyperboræan</placeName> mountaines, which are fained inventions of the 
<lb/>Greekes, as <persName>Strabo</persName> writeth: together with Aluani montes, heere described by <persName>Ptolemey</persName>, where not only these mountaines, but also no other at this 
<lb/>day, are to be seene: but in their places diuers huge and vast woods, great fennes and bogges, or large champion plaines. <persName>Orpheus</persName> also long since described 
<lb/>in this part of the continent I meane, between <placeName>Mæotis palus</placeName>, the <placeName>fenne Mæotis</placeName>, (now called <placeName>Mar delle Zabbache</placeName>, and <placeName>Mardella Tana</placeName>) and the <placeName>sea
<lb/>Cronium</placeName>, an huge wood. Likewise, <persName>Dionysius</persName> after heereabouts placeth an infinite wood, as he termeth it, from whence he saith <placeName>Tanais</placeName> or <placeName>Don</placeName> doth
<lb/>spring, which after many windings and turnings at last falleth into the forenamed <placeName>fenne Maeotis</placeName>. <persName>Isidorus</persName> heere hath the <placeName>Riphaean woods</placeName>, in which he
<lb/>saith <placeName>Tanais</placeName> doth first take the beginning. That <placeName>Donaw</placeName> (Danubis) doth diuide <placeName>Asia</placeName> from <placeName>Europe</placeName>, Seneca in the sixth booke Naturall doth manifestly
<lb/>affirm; of which his opinion, what do we thinke, we will, God willing, set downe in the discourse to the Mappe of <placeName>Dacia</placeName>. Hitherto we see the forenamed au-
<lb/>thours to doubt and disagree between themselues of the limits of these two parts of the world: if therefore they shall find me a meet vmpier and arbitratour
<lb/>in this matter, I would, not vnfitly, and as I hope to the liking of all parties, decide the controuer thus: I would make the bounds to be <placeName>Tanais</placeName>, or the ri-
<lb/>uer <placeName>Don</placeName>; the straits or narrow peece of the maine land that is between the riuer and the <placeName>riuer Rha</placeName> (Athel), which emptyeth it selfe into the <placeName>Caspian sea</placeName>:
<lb/>the East branch of the same Athel: then from his head vnto the <placeName>riuer Oby</placeName>, and so even vnto his mouth or fall into the <placeName>Northren sea</placeName>: For by this mouth, I
<lb/>do easily perswade my selfe, that antiquity did verily beleeue that the <placeName>Caspian sea</placeName> did vnlade it selfe into the maine Ocean. For that the name of this <placeName>riuer O-
<lb/>by</placeName> is ancient, it is very likely, for that <placeName>montes Obij</placeName>, certain mountaines called <placeName>Obij</placeName> are placed heere about in this tract, by <persName>Athenaeus</persName>, which he saith for-
<lb/>merly were called of the ancient <placeName>montes Riphæi</placeName>, the <placeName>Riphaean hils</placeName>: but then in his daies <placeName>montes Alpes</placeName>, the <placeName>Alpes</placeName>. Againe <persName>Iornandes</persName> in this continent,
<lb/>not farre from hence, describeth Ovim or Obim, a Scythian nation or family. And that these foresaid mountaines are in this place (not where <persName>Ptolemey</persName>
<lb/>and <persName>Pomponius Mela</persName> haue placed them) very many men of great credit and learning in these our daies, sufficient witnesses do stoutly auouch. Amongst
<lb/>which <persName>Baro Herberftein</persName>, in his history of <placeName>Moscouy</placeName>, is one: <persName>Paul Oderborne</persName>, in his treatise written of the life of <persName>Bafilides</persName>, is another: lastly, <persName>Antony
<lb/>Wied</persName>, in his mappe of <placeName>Moscouy</placeName> may be the third. Now they name it vulgarly by diuers and sundrie names, but commonly they call it <placeName>Cingulum mundi</placeName>,
<lb/>The girdle of the world, as the said <persName>Herberftein</persName> doth affirme. In a mappe of these countries set out by <persName>Master Jenkinson</persName>, an Englishman, who travelled
<lb/>through these parts, it is called <placeName>Zona Orbis</placeName>, The girdle of the Earth. Moreouer I haue in some sort for this diuision, <persName>Iornandes</persName> and <persName>AEthicus</persName>, upon my 
<lb/>side, where they say that the <placeName>Riphean mountaines</placeName> do part <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Europe</placeName>. Againe these selfe same hils, yea, and in this tract, are the <placeName>montes Hyperbo-
<lb/>rei</placeName>; not where <persName>Ptolemey</persName> placeth them. And they are the same with montes <placeName>Riphæi</placeName>, <placeName>Obij</placeName>, and <placeName>Alpes</placeName>. Thus farre of the diusion of <placeName>Asia</placeName> from <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>
<lb/>        <p><persName>Pliny</persName> calleth this part of the world, The Nurce of all Nations; <persName>Mardonius</persName>, as <persName>Herodotus</persName> doth tell of him, auoucheth it to <persName>Xerxes</persName>, to be by farre 
<lb/>the beautifulleft of all places of the World, to be a most goodly and gallant country, yielding all maner of fruits and fruitfull trees and those
<lb/>in their kindes and best; and to be such that it were pity that any king in the World should haue ought to do in but he. Varro in his bo kes Dere 
<lb/>Rustica, of Husbandrie writeth, That it is a more temperate and healthful soile than <placeName>Asia</placeName>. <placeName>Statius</placeName> in his Achilleidos, more than once or twice, calleth
<lb/>it, The Mighty prouince of the World. <foreign xml:lang="la">Maximaterra viris &amp; fœcundissima doctis Vrbibus</foreign>, <placeName>Europe</placeName> for multitude of warlike men and scholers 
<lb/>deeply learned, doth farre excell thus <persName>Mamilius</persName> writeth of it. <persName>Aristotle</persName>, the prince of Philospophers, maketh the inhabiters of this part of the world, to be, 
<lb/>A very stout and couragious people. The same authour affirmeth, that, All kind of beasts and cattell heere, are in their kind, greater, and stronger 
<lb/>than in <placeName>Asia</placeName> and <placeName>Africke</placeName>. But of the nature of this country, the maners and customes of the people, let vs heare what <placeName>Strabo</placeName> that excellent Geographer saith
<lb/>in his second book ; This part is most fertile of valiant and prudent men. It is all generally habitable, excepting only a very small portion toward 
<lb/>the North, and abutting vpon the Hamaxici, which dwell vpon <placeName>Tanais</placeName>, <placeName>Don</placeName> Meo'is Palus (<placeName>Mar delle Zabacche</placeName>) and <placeName>Borysthenes</placeName> (<placeName>Nieper</placeName> or
<lb/><placeName>Dnester</placeName>) which place, by reason of the extream cold, is not habitable. Yet certaine bleake and mountainous places inhabited, although in re-
<lb/>spect of the nature of the soile they are tilled and manured with greater difficulty, yet having gotten good skilull and industrious husbands,
<lb/>those also are tamed and much bettered, which heeretofore were badly vsed, and kept only by theeues and out-lawes. And indeed the Greekes
<lb/>when they dwelt vpon the rocks and mountaines, dwelt well and conueniently, by reason of their wise cariage in ciuill matters, arts, sciences and 
<lb/>knowledge of those things, which necessarily are required to the maintenance of mans life. In like maner the Romanes, hauing brought many 
<lb/>sauage and fierce Nations vnder their seruile yoke, seated, I meane, in places not very conuenient to dwell in, in respect of the nature of the coun- 
<lb/>try, either for that it was rough and craggy, or wanted hauens, or was too bleake and cold, or for other causes, taught them to vse merchandise
<lb/>before vnknowen, and haue brought them from a sauage and brutish life, to live ciuilly and more humanely. But those parts which are situate in
<lb/>an equall and temperat climate, there nature administreth all things necessary for the maintenance of man and beast. Now when as those Nations
<lb/>which do inhabite and dwell in fertile and rich countries, are maintainers of peace and quietnesse ; and those which are seated in barren and vn-
<lb/>fruitfull countries, are most hardy and stout : it commeth to passe that both are helpfull one to another ; while these do vse their weapons for 
<lb/>their countries defence, those againe do help and maintaine them by the profits that they raise out of the earth, by their arts and mysteries, as also
<lb/>by their learning, wisedome and policy : euen as in like maner also the dammage is mutuall and either side feeleth a sensible hurt, when the one
<lb/>part doth not helpe the other : yet the estate of the souldier and warlike man is somewhat better, if they be not ouercome with multitude. And
<lb/>the nature of <placeName>Europe</placeName> serueth very fitly for this purpose : for it is all diuersly distinguished by lofty mountaines and lowly plaines ; so that euery
<lb/>where the husbandmen and soldiers ; the politicians and the martiall warriers do dwell together : yet so as the greatest number are peaceable
<lb/>men : which kind of life they enjoy especially by the meanes and labour of their captaines, first of the Greekes, then of the Macedonians, and
<lb/>lastly of the Romanes. Therefore both in peace and warre it is sufficient of itselfe to maintaine and defend itselfe : for it hath great plenty both
<lb/>of stout soldiers, painfull husbandmen, and politique statesmen. In this also it doth excel, that it bringeth foorth passing good fruits, such I
<lb/>meane, as are necessary for the maintenance of mans life: with all sorts of mettall, for what vse soeuer. Spices or sweet smelling things and preti- 
<lb/>ous stones, are brought hither from forren countries, WHICH THINGS WHOSOEVER HAVE NOT, THEY LIVE NEVER A WHIT 
<lb/>WORSE THAN THOSE DO THAT HAVE THEM. Moreouer this is especially worth the noting, that hauing wonderfull store of cattell, 
<lb/>sheep and oxen ; it breedeth very few dangerous wild beasts. Thus farre the learned <persName>Strabo</persName>. Many other things thou maist read of this <placeName>Europe</placeName>,
<lb/>together with the nature and condition of the people of the same, in that treatise which <persName>Hippocrates</persName>, the prince of Physitions, wrote of the aire and waters.
<lb/>This <placeName>Europe</placeName> also, and not any other place of the world beside, doth yeeld Succinum or Electrum, (Amber we call it, the Germanes, Glessum) yet it is not 
<lb/>found in <placeName>Eridianus</placeName>, a river falling into some Northren sea, as <persName>Herodotus</persName> doth fabulously report : or in <placeName>Padus</placeName>, a riuer of Italy (Po) as the poets iestingly af-
<lb/>firme: nor in the Electrides, certaine fained ilands in the <placeName>Hadriaticke sea</placeName>, as some men of better credit, and more diligent searchers out of the <supplied reason="illegible">t</supplied>ruth, as <persName>Pliny</persName></p>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f019"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.20
</ab>

<pb facs="#f020"/>
<personalstmt><!--I, Emily Agnelli, with proofreading and additional help from Mary Zouharis, transcribed seq. 21 of this text--></personalstmt>
<ab>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">saith, have seriously thought: nor in</hi> <placeName>Spaine</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName><note type="letter"><!--ash or aesc-->AE</note></persName> <hi rend="italic">beleeued: nor in certaine rockes at the further end of the gulfe of</hi> <placeName>Venice</placeName>, (mare Hadriaticum)
<lb/><hi rend="italic">as some mere suber men haue giuen out: nor in</hi> <persName>Liguria</persName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Sudinus</persName>, <persName>Metrodorus</persName>, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <persName>Theophraftus</persName> <hi rend="italic">would haue men thinke: nor in</hi> <placeName>Ethiopia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">neere</hi> Iupiter Ammons <hi rend="italic">temple, or in</hi> <placeName>Scythia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Philemon</persName> <hi rend="italic">imagined: nor in</hi> <placeName>Britaine</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Socatus</persName>: <hi rend="italic">nor in the</hi> <placeName>Gleflari<note type="letter">ae</note></placeName>, <hi rend="italic">ilands in the</hi> <placeName>Germane ocean</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Pliny</persName>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">hathtaught: nor in</hi> <placeName>Bannonia</placeName> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <placeName>Baltia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">(a certain iland) as</hi> <persName>Tim<note type="letter">ae</note>us</persName> <hi rend="italic">hath broached: nor in a certain riuer, as</hi> <persName>Dion Prul<note type="letter">ae</note>us</persName> <hi rend="italic">hath taught: but neere vnto the neckland or peninsula</hi> <placeName><note type="letter">ae</note></placeName>, <hi rend="italic">in the bay</hi> <placeName>Pautzkerwicke</placeName> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <placeName>Frifch-haff</placeName> (<hi rend="italic">Sinus Clilipenus</hi>) <hi rend="italic">in the</hi> <placeName>Balticke</placeName> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <placeName>East Sea</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">not farre from</hi> <placeName>Dantzk</placeName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi>
<lb/><placeName>Pomerell</placeName> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <placeName>Sprufe</placeName>: <hi rend="italic">where hitherto it hath been taken (a thing wholly hidden from the ancients) to the great gaine and enriching of the Nations neere inha-</hi>
<lb/>biting: <hi rend="italic">and not in any other place of the world beside. In the same</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName> <hi rend="italic">are there many goodly and stately cities, amongst the which the most famous, in all</hi>
<lb/>ages, <hi rend="italic">are</hi> <placeName>Rome</placeName> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">(which afterward was called</hi> <placeName>New-Rome</placeName><hi rend="italic">) and now are</hi> <placeName>London</placeName>, <placeName>Venice</placeName> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <placeName>Paris</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">The riuers of greater note</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">are</hi> <placeName>Rhein</placeName>, <placeName>Isther</placeName> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <placeName>Donaw</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">and the</hi> <placeName>Thames</placeName>: <hi rend="italic">the woods more notable are</hi> <placeName>Ardene</placeName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>Gallia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">500 miles of length, reaching from the riuer of</hi> <placeName>Rhein</placeName> <hi rend="italic">vn-</hi>
<lb/>to <placeName>Tourney</placeName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>France</placeName>; <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <placeName>Hercynia</placeName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">40 daies iourney long, as</hi> <persName>Pomponius</persName> <hi rend="italic">writeth, and 9 daies iourney broad, as</hi> <persName>C<note type="letter">ae</note>ser</persName> <hi rend="italic">in his Commen-</hi>
<lb/>taries <hi rend="italic">reporteth: a greater wood than which, or more vast, there is no history maketh mention of. Thus much of</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">But whereof it tooke the name</hi>
<lb/>and <hi rend="italic">was so called, or who first gave it that name, I thinke</hi> <persName>Herodotius</persName> <hi rend="italic">saith, there is no man vnder heauen doth certainly know or can vpon any probabilitie</hi>
<lb/>gesse, <hi rend="italic">except one should think it so called of</hi> <placeName>Europa Tyria</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">But wherefore it should so of her be named, I am wholly ignorant, and I perswade my selfe and do</hi>
<lb/>verily beleeue, <hi rend="italic">that no man in the world truly knoweth. For that she, as we read in the fabulous stories of the poets, was violently taken out of</hi> <placeName>Ph<note type="letter">oe</note>nicia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
<lb/>country <hi rend="italic">of</hi> <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">and carried from thence into</hi> <placeName>Cyprus</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">or as others write, into the iland</hi> <placeName>Creta (Candy)</placeName> <hi rend="italic">all men do know well enough: where, as</hi> <persName>Eusebius</persName> <hi rend="italic">his</hi>
<lb/>Chronicle <hi rend="italic">doth witnesse, being taken of</hi> <persName>Asterius</persName> <hi rend="italic">king of</hi> <placeName>Creta</placeName> <hi rend="italic">to wife, she bare him</hi> <persName>Minoes</persName>, <persName>Rhadamanthus</persName> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <persName>Sarpedon</persName>: <hi rend="italic">from whence she went not into</hi>
<lb/><placeName>Europe</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">but into</hi> <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Herodotus</persName> <hi rend="italic">hath left recorded. But what is that to</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName> <hi rend="italic">this part of the world? One might easilier beleeue it to haue been so</hi>
<lb/>named <hi rend="italic">of</hi> <persName>Europus</persName>, <hi rend="italic">who, as</hi> <persName>Trogus Pompeius</persName> <hi rend="italic">witnesseth, sometime in these parts possessed a large kingdome: which also I do see to be auouched by</hi> <persName>Eustathius</persName>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">vpon</hi> <persName>Lycophron</persName>, <hi rend="italic">who maketh this</hi> <persName>Europis</persName> <hi rend="italic">to be the sonne of one</hi> <persName>Himerus</persName>. <persName>Pausanias</persName> <hi rend="italic">saith that one</hi> <persName>Eurpoa</persName> <hi rend="italic">was king of</hi> <placeName>Sicyonia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">a prouince of</hi>
<lb/><placeName>Peloponnelius</placeName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>Greece</placeName>: <hi rend="italic">to him</hi> <persName>Eusebius</persName> <hi rend="italic">in his Chronicle doth ascribe, who maketh him equall to the Patriarke</hi> <persName>Abraham</persName>, <hi rend="italic">and to haue liued aboue 3550</hi>
<lb/>yeares <hi rend="italic">since, about 1950 yeares before the birth of</hi> <persName>Christ</persName>. <hi rend="italic">There be some, as</hi> <persName>Festus</persName> <hi rend="italic">writeth, that thinke it so named of the beautifulnesse and excellency</hi>
<lb/>of the <hi rend="italic">country. <hi rend="italic">These we are sure are fabulous or vncertaine: may we not therefore, as they haue formed of</hi> <persName>Phrat</persName>, <persName>Euphrates</persName>, <hi rend="italic">and of</hi> <persName>Koft</persName>,</hi> <persName>AEgyptus</persName> <hi rend="italic">(as
<lb/>we haue shewed before) thinke that of</hi> <persName>Riphath</persName> <hi rend="italic">(the sonne of</hi> <persName>Gomer</persName>, <persName>Iapheths</persName> <hi rend="italic">sonne, to whom this part of the world was presently after the confusion at</hi> <placeName>Babel</placeName>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">assigned) they haue likewise formed</hi> <placeName>Europa</placeName>? <hi rend="italic">And surely the name</hi> <persName>Riphath</persName> <hi rend="italic">doth very manifestly shew it selfe in</hi> <placeName>Rhip<note type="letter">ae</note>is</placeName> <placeName>montibus</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi> <unclear><placeName>Riphean hils</placeName></unclear>:
<lb/>item <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>Riph<note type="letter">ae</note>o</placeName> <placeName>fluuio</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">now called the riuer</hi> <placeName>Oby</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>Ripe</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">a city of</hi> <placeName>Peloponneses</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>Rhiphat<note type="letter">ae</note>is</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the people of</hi> <placeName>Paphlagonia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Iosephus</persName> <hi rend="italic">writeth.</hi> 
<lb/><persName>Ptolemey</persName> <hi rend="italic">in the second booke of his</hi> <placeName>Quadripartite</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">in my opinion much more truly, writeth that it was sometime called by a common name,</hi> <placeName>C E L T I C A</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">name-</hi>
<lb/>ly <hi rend="italic">of a principall Nation that first did inhabite it. For there is almost no prouince in all this part, in which in time past the</hi> <note type="group of people">C E L T A E</note> <hi rend="italic">did not inhabit.</hi> 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">For in</hi> <placeName>Spaine</placeName> <hi rend="italic">toward the West, and beyond Hercules pillars are the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Herodotus</persName> <hi rend="italic">affirmeth. Item, about the riuer</hi> <placeName>B<note type="letter">ae</note>tis</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Strabo</persName> <hi rend="italic">auoucheth, the</hi>
<lb/><unclear><note type="group of people">Celtici Pre<note type="letter">ae</note>samarci</note></unclear>, <hi rend="italic">are in the prouince of</hi> <placeName>Lucensis</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">and others otherwise named</hi> <unclear><note type="group of people">Nerij</note></unclear> <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Pliny</persName> <hi rend="italic">saith:</hi> <persName>Dion</persName> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <persName>Xiphilinus</persName> <hi rend="italic">do shew that the</hi> <note type="group of people">Canta-</note>
<lb/><note type="group of people">bri</note> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <note type="group of people">Astures</note> <hi rend="italic">are the same with the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note>: <persName>Pliny</persName> <hi rend="italic">nameth the city</hi> <placeName>Celtica</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">in the prouince</hi> <placeName>Hispalensis</placeName>. <persName>Antonius</persName> <note type="group of people">Celti</note>: <hi rend="italic">item</hi> <placeName>Celticum promontorium</placeName>,
<lb/><hi rend="italic">is the same that</hi> <placeName>Cantabrum promontorium</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">which now is called</hi> <placeName>Cabo de finis terre</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">What Geographer or Historian is he amongst the anci-</hi>
<lb/>ents <hi rend="italic">that hath not made mention of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celtebri</note>? <hi rend="italic">In</hi> <placeName>France</placeName> <hi rend="italic">were the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <unclear><note type="group of people">Celtogalat<note type="letter">ae</note></note></unclear>: <hi rend="italic">and from thence are those in</hi> <placeName>Britaine</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">For that this iland</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">was first peopled from hence, lying so neere oueragainstit, it is a common opinion and very probable. That the</hi> <note type="group of people">Gauls Germanes</note> <hi rend="italic">were vulgarly called</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note>,
<lb/><hi rend="italic">all Historiographers do iointly agree: and indeed</hi> <persName>Dion</persName> <hi rend="italic">doth affirme, that the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">did dwell vpon either side of the riuer</hi> <placeName>Rhem</placeName>: <hi rend="italic">the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">dwelt in</hi>
<lb/><placeName>Gallia Cisalpina</placeName> <placeName>(Lombardy)</placeName> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <placeName>Italy</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Appianus</persName> <hi rend="italic">writeth. And again vpon the</hi> <placeName>Ionian sea</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">(that is, the</hi> <placeName>Hadriaticke</placeName>), <hi rend="italic">which also</hi> <persName>Strabo</persName> <hi rend="italic">doth auerre.</hi>
<lb/><persName>Silius Italicus</persName> <hi rend="italic">placeth them about the riuer</hi> <placeName>Eridianus (Po)</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">In</hi> <placeName>Epirus</placeName> <hi rend="italic">sometime dwelled the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note>, <hi rend="italic">as</hi> <persName>Antonius Liberalis</persName> <hi rend="italic">hath giuen out:</hi> <persName>Stepha-
<lb/>nus</persName> <hi rend="italic">placeth the same about the mount</hi> <placeName>H<note type="letter">oe</note>mus</placeName>: <placeName>Arrianus</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">neere the mouth of the riuer</hi> <placeName>Donaw</placeName>: <hi rend="italic">as also</hi> <persName>Strabo</persName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <placeName>M<note type="letter">oe</note>sia</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">The same author writeth,</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">that the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">are intermedled with the</hi> <note type="group of people">Illyrij</note> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <note type="group of people">Thraces</note>. <hi rend="italic">Who also placeth them vpon the riuer</hi> <placeName>Borysthenes</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Moreouer</hi> <persName>Aristotle</persName> <hi rend="italic">in his booke</hi> <placeName>De mundo</placeName>,
<lb/><hi rend="italic">ioineth the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">with the</hi> <note type="group of people">Scythians</note>. <hi rend="italic">Heere hence the same</hi> <persName>Strabo</persName> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <persName>Plutarch</persName> <hi rend="italic">do make their</hi> <note type="group of people">Celtoscyth<note type="letter">ae</note></note>. <hi rend="italic">In</hi> <persName>Plutarch</persName>, <hi rend="italic">in the life of</hi> <persName>Camilus</persName>,
<lb/><hi rend="italic">I read that the</hi> <note type="group of people">Galat<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">(which he maketh to haue come of the stocke of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note>) <hi rend="italic">passing the</hi> <placeName>Northren sea</placeName> <hi rend="italic">came vnto the</hi> <placeName>Riph<note type="letter">ae</note>an mountains</placeName>. 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Againe out of the forenamed</hi> <persName>Strabo</persName> <hi rend="italic">I learne that the nations dwelling Northward were in his time called</hi> <unclear><note type="group of people">Calt<note type="letter">ae</note></note></unclear>. <hi rend="italic">The which also their ancient lan-</hi>
<lb/>guage, <hi rend="italic">which is called the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celticke</note> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <note type="group of people">Germane</note> <hi rend="italic">tongue, doth at this day sufficiently demonstrate: which is the same (only differing a little in dialect) with that which</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">is vsed in the ilands neere adioining to these places, as in Island,</hi> <placeName>Groenland</placeName>, <placeName>Friesland</placeName> <hi rend="italic">and others in this ocean.</hi> <persName>Plutarke</persName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <persName>Marius</persName> <hi rend="italic">wri-</hi>
<lb/>teth, <hi rend="italic">that Celtica doth begin at the outmost sea (that is, the</hi> <placeName>Atlanticke Sea</placeName>) <hi rend="italic">and so stretcheth itselfe out farre into the North and from thence vn-</hi>
<lb/>to the fenne <placeName>M<note type="letter">ae</note>otis</placeName>, (<foreign xml:lang="la">Mare delle Zabacche</foreign>). <persName>Pomponius Mela</persName> <hi rend="italic">calleth the</hi> <placeName>Cassiterides</placeName> <hi rend="italic">(which in another place we haue proued to belong to</hi> <placeName>great Britaine</placeName>, 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">or to be the number of those which are named</hi> <placeName>Brittanic<note type="letter">ae</note></placeName> <hi rend="italic">) Celticke Ilands. What is this else, I pray you, than plainly to affirme that</hi> THE <note type="group of people">C E L T <note type="letter">AE</note></note> DO  
<lb/>POSSESSE ALL <placeName>E V R O P E</placeName>? <hi rend="italic">Which indeed is that which</hi> <persName>Ephorus</persName> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <persName>Strabo</persName> <hi rend="italic">did see so many years since: when as he diuiding all the world into 4. quar-</hi>
<lb/>ters, <hi rend="italic">saith that, That part which is toward the East, is inhabited of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Indians</note>: <hi rend="italic">that which is in the South, of the</hi> <note type="group of people">AEthiopians</note>: <hi rend="italic">the North parts, of</hi> 
<lb/><note type="group of people">Scythians</note>: <hi rend="italic">and the West, of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note>. <hi rend="italic">The scholiast of</hi> <persName>Appollonius</persName> <hi rend="italic">nameth the</hi> <placeName>Hadriaticke sea</placeName>, <placeName>Mare Celticum</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi> <placeName>Celticke Sea</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">And</hi> <persName>Lyco-</persName>
<lb/>phron <hi rend="italic">describeth Celtos, a certain poole, about the mouth of the riuer</hi> <placeName>Ister</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Item he placeth</hi> <placeName>Leuce</placeName> <hi rend="italic">an iland of</hi> <placeName>Mar maiore</placeName> <foreign xml:lang="la">(<hi rend="italic">Pontus Euxinus</hi>)</foreign> <hi rend="italic">oueragainst the mouth of the riuer</hi> <placeName>Donaw</placeName>.
<lb/><hi rend="italic">May we not therefore properly, as they call those that inhabit</hi> <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <note type="group of people">Asians</note>: <hi rend="italic">and those which dwell in</hi> <placeName>Africa</placeName>, <note type="group of people">Africanes</note>: <hi rend="italic">call these which dwell in</hi> <placeName>Celtica</placeName>, <note type="group of people">Celtickes</note><unclear>?</unclear> 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">He that out of all ancient stories, penned either in Latine or Greeke, doth not know that the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note> <hi rend="italic">are the</hi> <note type="group of people">Germanes</note>, <hi rend="italic">let him haue recourse to the 22. chapter of</hi> <persName>Hadrianus Iunius</persName> <hi rend="italic">his</hi> <placeName>Batauia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">and I doubt not but, hauing throughly waied those many sound ar-</hi>
<lb/>guments, <hi rend="italic">and sufficient testimonies of ancient graue writers, shall rest satisfied and sweare to our opinion. If not, let him listen to the</hi> <note type="group of people">Dutchmen</note>, <hi rend="italic">and he shall</hi>
<lb/>heare <hi rend="italic">them call one another in their familiar communication,</hi> Kelt. <hi rend="italic">The</hi> <note type="group of people">French</note> <hi rend="italic">also or</hi> <placeName>Gauls</placeName> <hi rend="italic">I call a German nation. And I can proue by good arguments, if it</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">were a matter pertaining to this our purpose, that the Germane or Dutch tongue is the ancient language of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Celt<note type="letter">ae</note></note>, <hi rend="italic">and to be the same which hitherto they</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">haue vsed in all places and now is spoken, except in some places where the power of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Romanes</note> <hi rend="italic">so preuailed, that they banished this, and seated theirs in the</hi> 
<lb/>roome. <hi rend="italic">It is likely therefore that the etymology and reason of the deriuation of the word</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">which was vnknowen vnto the old writers, is to be sought</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">and fetched from no other language else, but from that which was most</hi> <unclear>usuall</unclear> <hi rend="italic">in this part of the world. For that the inhabitants of any country should take</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">the name of their natiue soile from strangers, it is so absurd and hard to be beleeued, that there cannot any thing more foolish or contrary to truth be inuent-</hi>
<lb/>ed <hi rend="italic">or deuised. Wherefore I thinke it good, concerning this matter, heere to lay downe the iudgement of</hi> <persName>Goropius Becanus</persName>, <hi rend="italic">our countryman, who thinketh</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">it to be so named, not of a woman, (which is probable, either neuer was, or neuer came heere) but</hi> <unclear>a</unclear> <hi rend="italic">latitudine videndi, of the largenesse of his prospect (as</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">he speaketh) namely, because (I do cite his owne words out of the 9. booke of his</hi> <persName>Origines</persName>) <hi rend="italic">it doth not only looke toward</hi> <placeName>Asia</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">on the East and South:</hi> <placeName>Africa</placeName>,
<lb/><hi rend="italic">on the South and West: but also the New-found-world beyond the</hi> <placeName>Hyperborei</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">on the West and North. Neither shall any man perswade me, that</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">had the name from</hi> <placeName>Greece</placeName> <hi rend="italic">or the Greeke language, seeing that it was first inhabited of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Cimbers</note> (<hi rend="italic">Cimmerij, descended from</hi> <persName>Gomer</persName>, <hi rend="italic">the elder brother)</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">before it was possessed of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Greeks</note> (<unclear>Iones</unclear>, <hi rend="italic">come from</hi> <persName>Iawan</persName> <hi rend="italic">a yonger brother) but the 4. son of</hi> <persName>Yapheth</persName>) <hi rend="italic">we make a dipthong by setting the 5. vowel of the</hi> 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Latins before the 2. which neither the</hi> <note type="group of people">Latins</note> <hi rend="italic">nor</hi> <note type="group of people">Greeks</note> <hi rend="italic">do admit. Therefore if so be at any time they change the words in which this did light, for</hi> We,
<lb/><hi rend="italic">they put</hi> Eu; <hi rend="italic">turning it backward. Therefore our men do term it</hi> <unclear>Verop</unclear>, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> Europ, <hi rend="italic">whereby they vnderstand a worthy company of men: for</hi> Wer <hi rend="italic">(a mono-</hi>
<lb/>syllable <hi rend="italic">pronounced like a dipthong) signifieth lofty, great, excellent &amp; that which is best in euery kind of thing: which notwithstanding some do write</hi> ur, 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">without a dipthong, yet with a long vowell. Therefore, as of</hi> <persName>Terues</persName>, <hi rend="italic">they formed</hi> <persName>Tereus</persName>, <hi rend="italic">so of</hi> <persName>Werop</persName>, <hi rend="italic">the</hi> <note type="group of people">Latines</note> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <note type="group of people">Greeks</note> <hi rend="italic">haue made</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName>: <hi rend="italic">so named of</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">the excellency of the Nation, which doth farre surpasse all the other men of the World. For</hi> <unclear><persName>Hop</persName></unclear>, <hi rend="italic">as I haue shewed before, signifieth a company or multitude of men.</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">More of this word thou maist see in his</hi> <persName>8.</persName> <hi rend="italic">booke. Thus farre out of his workes which are foorth in print: that which followeth, is taken out of a booke of his</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">which he also hath set foorth, yet not imprinted, but such as he vsed priuatly, and hath many additions in sundrie places in the margin written with his owne</hi>
<lb/>hand, <hi rend="italic">which he had prepared against the second edition. But I waighing, saith he, and comparing this name with that which I haue read in holy Scripture, a-</hi>
<lb/>nother <hi rend="italic">reason farre more excellent, and better commeth into my mind. We see that to</hi> <persName>Yaphet</persName> <hi rend="italic">was promised enlargement or a farre spreading of his posterity,</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">or as some other interpret the word, ioy and gladnesse: which then he truly had enioied, when as</hi> <persName>Christ</persName> <hi rend="italic">had redeemed vs by his death and pretious bloud (which</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">blessing doth agree to this part of the world, rather than to any other vnder heauen beside: and therefore all other countries generallie do call</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName>: THE
<lb/>KINGDOME <hi rend="italic">OF THE</hi> <note type="group of people">CHRISTIANS</note>: <hi rend="italic">and the</hi> <note type="group of people">Europeans</note>, <hi rend="italic">are called of the</hi> <note type="group of people">Turkes</note> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <note type="group of people">Arabians</note>, <hi rend="italic">GAIVVR, that is,</hi> <note type="group of people">Christians</note>. <hi rend="italic">E, therefore,</hi>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">doth signifie a lawfull contract and mariage:</hi> VR, <hi rend="italic">excellent: and</hi> HOP, <hi rend="italic">hope: whereupon it commeth to passe, that</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName> <hi rend="italic">signifieth</hi> The excellent hope
<lb/>of <hi rend="italic">a lawfull mariage. which is proper to this portion of the world which</hi> <persName>Noah</persName> <hi rend="italic">gaue to</hi> <persName>Iapheth</persName> <hi rend="italic">his sonne to inhabite. For although that the posterity of</hi> <persName>Sem</persName>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">was by</hi> <persName>Abraham</persName>, <hi rend="italic">for many ages wedded to God, yet at length he put her away and diuorced her from him. But the wedlocke whereby God, by</hi> <persName>Christ</persName> <hi rend="italic">is wed-</hi>
<lb/>ded to <placeName>Europe</placeName> <hi rend="italic">his Church, shall neuer be dissolued: so that</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName> <hi rend="italic">may most properly be said to be</hi> <persName>Iaphets</persName> <hi rend="italic">portion. But of this word we will speake more in</hi>
<lb/>our <placeName>Francica</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Thus farre</hi> <persName>Goropius</persName>. <hi rend="italic">Which I haue very willingly communicated to the courteous Reader, leauing it to the censure of the learned to be iud-</hi>
<lb/>ged. <hi rend="italic">Yet I know that these things haue been very bitterly skoffed at already by a certaine learned man, but one wholly ignorant of this tongue, and therefore of</hi>
<lb/>lesse <hi rend="italic">iudgement in this argument. There are some which do think that this</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName> <hi rend="italic">was in the holy Scripture called</hi> <persName>IAPETIA</persName>. <hi rend="italic">Thus farre of</hi> <placeName>Europe</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">to</hi>
<lb/>which <hi rend="italic">before I do altogether leaue, I will adioyne out of</hi> <persName>Herodotus</persName> <hi rend="italic">in his</hi> <persName>Polymnia</persName>, <hi rend="italic">the words of</hi> <persName>Mardonius</persName> <hi rend="italic">to</hi> <persName>Darius</persName> <hi rend="italic">spoken of this country.</hi> <hi rend="italic">That it is a</hi>
<lb/>country <hi rend="italic">most goodly and beautifull, bearing all maner of excellent fruitfull trees, and those in their kind the best: and to be such that it were pi-</hi>
<lb/>ty <hi rend="italic">that any man but a king only should possesse.</hi>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f021"/>
<ab> 
<personalstmt><!--Transcribed and encoded by Nicholas Vitale and Karolina Rosberg--></personalstmt><placeName>ASIA</placeName>
<lb/>
<lb/><placeName>Asia</placeName> diuides it selfe from <placeName>Europe</placeName> by the river <placeName>Tanais</placeName>, and a streight line drawen
<lb/>from the fountaines thereof to the <placeName>Bay of S. Nicolas</placeName> in the <placeName>North Ocean</placeName>:
<lb/>but from <placeName>Africa</placeName>, by the neck-land Ifthmos or narrow place of the earth, which
<lb/>in betweene the <placeName>Arabian gulfe</placeName> and the <placeName>Mediterran sea</placeName>. The residue thereof the
<lb/>Ocean and other seas do enuiron.
<lb/>
<lb/>This part the ancient Geographers, as <persName>Strabo</persName> in his eleuenth booke, and <persName>Ar-
<lb/>rianus</persName> in his fift booke, haue dinersly divided. But at this present it may be us not altogether un-
<lb/>fitly be distributed into fine parts, according to the great Empires by which it is gouerned. The first
<lb/>whereof, which bordereth upon <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and is subiect to the great <persName>Duke of Mofcouia</persName>, is bounded
<lb/>by the Frozen sea, the riuer <placeName>Ob</placeName>, the lake <placeName>Kitaia</placeName>, and a line drawen from thence to the <placeName>Caspian sea</placeName>,
<lb/>and by the Isthmus or neck-land between the <placeName>Caspian</placeName> and <placeName>Euxin seas</placeName>. The second is that, which
<lb/>yields obedience to the great <persName>Cham Emperour</persName> of the <placeName>Tartars</placeName>, whole Southern borders are the <placeName>Caspi-
<lb/>an sea</placeName>, the riuer <placeName>Iaxartest</placeName>, and mount <placeName>Imaus</placeName>; on the East and North it is begirt with the Ocean;
<lb/>and Westward it confines vpon the dominions of the foresaid great <persName>Duke of Russia</persName>. The third part,
<lb/>the progeinie of the Ottomans or the <persName>Turkish Emperour</persName> enioyes, which containeth whatsoeuer re-
<lb/>gions are situate within the compasse of the <placeName>Euxin sea</placeName>, the <placeName>aegean sea</placeName> (now called Arcipelago)
<lb/>and the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName>, the land of <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, the <placeName>Arabian</placeName> and <placeName>Persian seas</placeName>, the riuer <placeName>Tigris</placeName>, the <placeName>Ca-
<lb/>spian sea</placeName>, and the Isthmos or neck-land between it and the sea <placeName>Euxine</placeName>. Vnder the fourth shalbe com-
<lb/>prised the <placeName>Kingdome of Persia</placeName>, now gouerned by the Sophies; Westward it hat the <placeName>Turkes</placeName>, with
<lb/>whom the Persian for the most part manteineth continuall warres; Northward the Empire of the
<lb/><persName>great Cham</persName>; Eastward it extends almost to the riuer <placeName>Indus</placeName>; and on the south it is restrained by the
<lb/>sea, at this present called <placeName>Indicum</placeName>, but in times past <placeName>Mare Rubrum</placeName>, or <placeName>The Red sea</placeName>. Now the
<lb/>sift part takes vp all that remaineth, which as in times past, so at this present, is called <placeName>The Indies</placeName>;
<lb/>neither is it gouerned by one only, as the former; but by many pety Kings, euery region almost hauing
<lb/>a peculiar Gouernour, some which are tributarie to the <persName>great Cham</persName>. And here it is not to be omitted,
<lb/>that all the sea-coasts from the <placeName>Arabian gulfe</placeName>, to the <placeName>Promontory of China</placeName>, commonly called <placeName>Cabo
<lb/>de Lampo</placeName>, situate in 30. degrees of Northerly latitude, are in a maner possessed, or made tributary
<lb/>to the <placeName>Portugals</placeName>. 
<lb/>
<lb/>Amongst infitinte others, the princpall isles ascribed to <placeName>Asia</placeName>, are <placeName>Cyprus</placeName> and <placeName>Rhodes</placeName> in the
<lb/><placeName>Mediterran</placeName> sea; <placeName>Zeilan</placeName> of the vulgar and <placeName>Taprobana</placeName> well knowento the ancients now called <placeName>Sa-
<lb/>motra</placeName>, but falsly <placeName>Sumatra</placeName>, in the <placeName>Indick-Ocean</placeName>, where also within the memory of our fathers, the
<lb/><placeName>Portugals</placeName> haue discouered the two <placeName>Iauas</placeName>, with the isles of <placeName>Borneo</placeName>, <placeName>Celebes</placeName>, <placeName>Palohan</placeName>, and<placeName>Min-
<lb/>danao</placeName>; and here likewise <placeName>Gilolo</placeName>, and the <placeName>Moluccos</placeName>, at this day famous for abundance of spi-
<lb/>ces which they yeeld. To these may be added the isles of <placeName>Iapan</placeName>, and <placeName>new Guinie</placeName> very lately descried;
<lb/>but this last, whether it be an island, or adioyned to the <placeName>South maine</placeName>, it is not yet Certainly knowen.
<lb/>
<lb/>The memorie of this part of the world is most renowmed, not only with prophane authors (as they 
<lb/>terme them) in regard of the first monarchies established by the Assyrians, the Persians, the Babylo-
<lb/>nians, and the Medes; but in the holy Scriptures also it is more famous than the rest: for here man-
<lb/>kinde was not only created by almightie God, deluded and corrupted by the enemie Satan, and resto-
<lb/> by our Saviour Christ; but we finde almost all the hestories in either Testament to haue beene in
<lb/>this part both written and accomplished.
<lb/><persName>Strabo</persName> hath described Asia in six books, namely from the 11. booke vnto the 16. <persName>Ptolomey</persName> hath
<lb/>decyphered the fame in three, as in his 5. 6. And 7. books; and likewise in 12. Geographicall Tables,
<lb/>and ascribes unto it 40. prouinces. It is also let foorth by <persName>Ammianus Marcellinus</persName> in his 23.
<lb/>booke, and by <persName>Diodorus Siculus</persName> in the beginning of his 18. Of late Writers none haue wholly and
<lb/>particularly described it. <persName>M. Paulus Venetus</persName>, <persName>Lewes of Barthema</persName>, and <persName>St. Iohn Mandeuile</persName>,
<lb/>(but this Authour is fraught with tables) haue written so much thereof, as by trauelling the regions,
<lb/>they found worthie of obseruation. Reade also the Epistle of <persName>Iacobus Nauarca</persName> a Fesuite.
<lb/>        I my selfe likewise certaine yeeres past set forth a large Map the description of the same.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f022"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.23
</ab>

<pb facs="#f023"/>
<ab>
<lb/><personalstmt><!--Transcribed and Encoded by Avery Slavin--></personalstmt>This the Ancients have diuersly distinguished; but at this present it is divided by <persName>John Leo</persName> of
<lb/> <placeName>Africa</placeName>, into foure chiefe parts; <placeName>Barbaria</placeName>, <placeName>Numidia</placeName>, <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and the Land of Negros. <placeName>Barbarie</placeName>, 
<lb/>which is accounted the best, they circumscribe with the <placeName>Atlantick</placeName> &amp; <placeName>Mediterranean seas</placeName>; with 
<lb/>mount Atlas, &amp; whither region of Barca bordering upon <placeName>Ægypt</placeName>. <placeName>Numidia</placeName>, called by the 
<lb/>inhabitants Biledulgerid, and abounding with Dates (for which cause the Arabians call it by no 
<lb/>other name, but the Date-bearing region) is bounded Westward by the <placeName>Atlantick Ocean</placeName>; 
<lb/>Northward by mount Atlas; it stretcheth East as farre as the citie <placeName>Caphsa</placeName>, which is an hundred &amp; 
<lb/>fiftie miles distant from <placeName>Ægypt</placeName>; and the sande <placeName>Deserts of Libya</placeName> embrace it on the South. <placeName>Libya</placeName>
<lb/>the third part, is named in the Arabian tongue Sura, which word signifies a Desert. It begins East 
<lb/>from <placeName>Nilus</placeName>, and thence runneth West as farre as the <placeName>Atlantick sea</placeName>; <placeName>Numidia</placeName> lies to the North of it, 
<lb/>and the Land of Negros to the South. Now followeth the fourth part, which they call <placeName>Nigritarum</placeName> or 
<lb/><placeName>Nigritania</placeName>, either from the inhabitants, who are of a blacke colour, or from the <placeName>river Niger</placeName>, that 
<lb/>runneth thorow the countrey. It is bounded by <placeName>Libya</placeName>, South by the <placeName>Æthiopick Ocean</placeName>; West by 
<lb/><placeName>Guinee</placeName>, and East by the <placeName>Kingdome of Gago</placeName>. And here we are to note, that according unto their 
<lb/>division, all <placeName>Africa</placeName> is included within the <placeName>Mediterranean</placeName>, <placeName>Atlantick</placeName>, and <placeName>Æthiopick</placeName> seas and the 
<lb/><placeName>river Nilus</placeName>; whereof <placeName>Ægypt</placeName> and <placeName>Abassia</placeName> are accounted parts of it, which we not unworthily 
<lb/>therefore proper to belong to <placeName>Africa</placeName>. For the true <placeName>Africa</placeName> containes at this day <persName>Prester Johns</persName> 
<lb/>Empire, which by all late Writers is ascribed to <placeName>Africa</placeName>. Wherefore with Ptolomy indeed it ought to 
<lb/>be bound by the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName> and Ocean seas, rather than by any river whatsoever; and 
<lb/>it hath the forme of a Peninsula, being joined toward <placeName>Asia</placeName> by an Isthmos of small neck-land, 
<lb/>which lies between the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName> and the <placeName>gulf of Arabia</placeName>. The South part hereof was 
<lb/>unknowne to our ancestors, till the yeere <date when="1497">1497</date>, whereas Vasco de Gama first doubling the <placeName>Cape 
of Bona Speranza</placeName>, and passing about all <placeName>Africa</placeName>, came to <placeName>Calecut in East India</placeName>. This Southerne 
<lb/>part by the Persians and Arabians is called <placeName>Zangibar</placeName>.
<lb/>At the fore-sayd Cape of good hope the inhabitants are exceeding blacke; which we thought in 
<lb/>no wise to omit, because all men suppose the cause of blacknesse to be heat, and the 
<lb/>nearnesse of the Sunne; whereas the Sunne of it selfe forceth no more, than about the Streight 
<lb/>of <placeName>Magellan</placeName> (we measure the heat of the place, according to the position of the heavens and 
<lb/>distance from the Equinoctiall line) were now notwithstanding the people are reported to be 
<lb/>marvellous white. But if we will needs ascribe this blacknesse to the scorching of the Sun, let us 
<lb/>consider, that the same makes the Spaniards and Italians looke white; whereas they are equally 
<lb/>distant from the Equinoctiall with the inhabitants of the fore-sayd Cape; namely the one towards 
<lb/>the South, and the other towards the North. <persName>Prester Johns</persName> people are of a browne colour; in 
<lb/><placeName>Zanel</placeName> and <placeName>Mollala</placeName> the inhabitants are cole blacke, yet all in one &amp; the same distance from the 
<lb/>equator, and under the very same parallell of the heavens. And on the contrary, why did 
<lb/><persName>Herodotus</persName> and <persName>Pindarus</persName> describe such as inhabite the same climate with themselves, namely 
<lb/>Colches, to be a blacke people, and curled haired? <persName>Herodotus</persName> in his Thalia makes the Indians 
<lb/>blacke like the Æthiopians; which the experience of our times confirmeth. I know <persName>Herodotus</persName> will 
<lb/>have the cause hereof to be the seede of the parents, which he sayth is not whiter, than of other 
<lb/>people, but blacke. To whom Possidonius also subscribeth, and imputeth the matter of all this 
<lb/>blacknesse unto Canicular heate, against which opinion I have nothing to allege. Let the truth of 
<lb/>the matter rest upon the authors credit. But this as many men thinke more strange; that in all 
<lb/><placeName>America</placeName> there were no black people found besides a few only in one place called by them 
<lb/><placeName>Quarequa</placeName>. What then is the efficient cause of this colour? Is it the drinesse of the heavens, or of 
<lb/>the earth? is it perhaps some hidden propriety of the soile? Or a kind of fat licentious nature in 
<lb/>the nature of men? Or is it all these variances in one? But these things we leave to be 
<lb/>considered by them, who more curiously search into the secrets of nature.
<lb/>This portion of the world is called by the Greeks <placeName>Libya</placeName>, and by the Latines <placeName>Africa</placeName>, because it is 
<lb/>not moistened with extremity of cold: or (if we may credit some) of Afer one of the adventurers 
<lb/>posterity. Another derivation of the name you have (set downe by <persName>John Leo</persName> in the description of 
<lb/>his booke of the Description of <placeName>Africa</placeName>), who deriveth it from one blacke African, springing of the 
<lb/>stocke of Cham, who first inhabited that part of the <placeName>Mediterranean sea</placeName>, from <placeName>Atlas</placeName>, bounded by 
<lb/>the <placeName>river Nilus</placeName>, or rather as the best authors have taught us, the African soile called of the 
<lb/>Greekes Aphrice, Marce rubrum, and red sea. <persName>Herodotus</persName> reporteth, that <placeName>Africa</placeName> was first 
<lb/>unknowne till <persName>Cesars</persName> time, when it was found to be a third part of the inhabited world. Plinie the 
<lb/>like, and so doth Solinus. <persName>Caesar Scaliger</persName> gathereth of the word <placeName>Africa</placeName>, that it is a name of the 
<lb/>same import with aprica, that is, a sunne-shining place; for that this land lying open on every 
<lb/>side to the Sunnes visitation, seemed thereby to have beene named so little other than of 
<lb/>apricity. The principall regions of <placeName>Africa</placeName> have amongst themselves (as it were) a threefold 
<lb/>division: first, from <placeName>Atlas</placeName> in the West to the red sea and <placeName>Arabia</placeName>, whence it took the name of the 
<lb/>first inhabiters, or else from the colour of the people, for the most part blacke and duskie; the 
<lb/>second, to wit, the inner part of <placeName>Africa</placeName>, from <placeName>Nilus</placeName> to the <placeName>Kingdome of Congo</placeName>, is more temperate, 
<lb/>and not so much subject to the Sunnes heate; the third, which is next unto the <placeName>South Pole</placeName>, by 
<lb/>reason of the obliquity of the Zodiack, is more temperate than the former. The islands that 
<lb/>belong to <placeName>Africa</placeName> (some of which are expressed in the table) are <placeName>Madagascar</placeName>, <placeName>the Canaries</placeName>, the 
<lb/><placeName>Isles of Cape Verde</placeName>, and <placeName>St. Thomas</placeName> situated under the equinoctiall, which aboundeth with 
<lb/>fruits.
<lb/>Among the ancient Writers none have particularly described this region. But concerning the 
<lb/>same saith Isidore in his Etymologies; <persName>Hanno</persName> his navigation about <placeName>Africa</placeName>, in diversities; and 
<lb/><persName>Iambulus</persName> his voyages, in Diodorus Siculus; and likewise <persName>Herodotus</persName> his Melpomene. 
<lb/><persName>Bartholomeus de Glanvilla</persName> in his Image of the World reporteth the like. Of late Writers reade 
<lb/>also the Commentaries of <persName>Vasco de Gama</persName>, <persName>Franciscus Alvares</persName>, who travelled <placeName>Æthiopia</placeName>. But of 
<lb/>all others <persName>John Leo</persName> hath most exactly described it; as also <persName>Andrew Thevet</persName>, and <persName>Francis Alvarez</persName>, 
<lb/>both travellers of <placeName>Africa</placeName>. Concerning the <placeName>river Nilus</placeName>, the greatest in all the world, you have the 
<lb/>letters of <persName>John Ramusio</persName> and <persName>Jerome Fracastorius</persName>. Of <placeName>Africa itself</placeName>, as by me read at large in the 
<lb/>second volume of <persName>Mr. Richard Hakluyts</persName> English Voyages.
</ab>

<pb facs="#f024"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.25
</ab>

<pb facs="#f025"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.26
</ab>

<pb facs="#f026"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.27
</ab>

<pb facs="#f027"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.28
</ab>

<pb facs="#f028"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.29
</ab>

<pb facs="#f029"/>
<ab>
<personalstmt> <!--I, Alex Wheeler, transcribed and encoded seq. 30 of this text--> </personalstmt>
<fw type="pageNum" place="top">7</fw>
<lb/>--This Prouince was about the yeere <date when="1518">1518</date> forcibly subdued to the
<lb/>Spanish gouernment, vnder the command and conduct of <persName ref="#corlez">Fer-
<lb/>nando Corlez</persName>: who with the great slaughter of his owne people,
<lb/>but farre greater of the inhabitants fighting for their liberty, con-
<lb/>quered the fame. It is a region rich of siluer and golde: for it
<lb/>hath very many riuers yeelding sands or graines of perfect gold.
<lb/>Vpon the coast of this countrey are many commodious fishings for pearle. Salt
<lb/>lakes here are diuers, the water whereof through the heat of the Sunne is conuer-
<lb/>ted into excellent salt. Here is great abundance of <hi rend="fiftula">Cassia fiftula</hi>, and a kind of fruit in
<lb/>the Mexican language called <hi rend="italic">Cacao</hi>, somewhat resembling an Almond: which is
<lb/>with them very highly esteemed; for hereof they make a kinde of drinke, to their
<lb/>owne taste most delicate. The seas and riuers belonging to this countrey abound
<lb/>mightily with fish. Their riuers also breed Crocodiles, whose flesh is food to the
<lb/>inhabitants. In these places this creature is for the most part aboue twenty foot
<lb/>long. It is a countrey very mountainous and beset here and there with most lofty
<lb/>and cragged rocks. So great is the diuersity of languages in these regions, that one
<lb/>cannot vnderstand another without an Interpreter. The principall Colonies to
<lb/>be seene in this Table, which in <placeName ref="#spaine">New Spaine</placeName> haue been planted by the Spaniards, 
<lb/>are first <placeName ref="#compostella">Compostella</placeName>, the feat of a bishop, and one of the Kings counsels. <placeName ref="#colima">Colima</placeName>, 
<lb/>by another name called the city of the Purification. <placeName ref="#guadalajara">Guadalajara</placeName>, a towne most fa-
<lb/>mous, and head of the Kingdome of <placeName ref="#gallicia">New Gallicia</placeName>. <placeName ref="#mecboacan">Mecboacan</placeName>, a Bishops sea also.
<lb/><placeName ref="#sacatula">Sacatula</placeName>, the city of the Angels, a mother-towne and a Bishoprick. <placeName ref="#mexico">Mexico</placeName>, a Kingly
<lb/>city, or rather Queene of all the cities in the New world; situate vpon the banke
<lb/>of a lake, or rather of a fenne: yea the very ground-plot of this city is so fenny, that
<lb/>you cannot come thither, nor depart thence but ouer bridges and cawseys. The 
<lb/>lake adioyning is falt, being six leagues long and fiue broad. Fishes it hath none,
<lb/>but very small ones; which more aptly may be called wormes than fishes: of
<lb/>whose putrefaction, which is there caused by the heat of the Summer, the aire is some-
<lb/>times so infected, that it is most vnholesome dwelling there: yet is it as much fre-
<lb/>quented with inhabitants and merchants, as any mart-towne in <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>. It is a large 
<lb/>city, for in compasse it containeth about three leagues. The other lake adioining 
<lb/>to this, is fresh water, and very plentifull of fish; wherein also stand many townes.
<lb/>There are likewise a great number vpon the banks of either lake. In this city (as
<lb/><persName ref="#giraua">Ierome Giraua</persName> reporteth) there was by <persName ref="#paul">Pope Paul</persName> the third established the feat of 
<lb/>an Archbishop, in the yeere <date when="1547">1547</date>. 
<lb/>This citie was taken by the Spaniards 140 yeeres after the first foundation
<lb/>thereof; <persName ref="#montezuma">Montezuma</persName> at the same time being King, the ninth in number. A won-
<lb/>der, how in so few yeeres it should grow to such largenesse and magnificence.
<lb/>The nature, situation, and customes of this citie and of the territory adiacent, who
<lb/>desires more perfectly to know, may reade the relations of <persName ref="#corlez">Fernando Corlez</persName>. Ex-
<lb/>tant they are in the volume intituled <hi rend="italic">Nouus Orbis</hi>; and in the volume of Nauiga-
<lb/>tions printed at <placeName ref="#venice">Venice</placeName> in Italian: but especially <persName ref="#Gonsaluo">John Gonsaluo </persName>, who in his little
<lb/>booke of <placeName ref="#china">China</placeName> hath a most large description of this region. You haue also many
<lb/>notable discourses hereof in the third Volume of <persName ref="#Hakluyts">M. Hakluyts  </persName> English voyages. 
</ab>

<pb facs="#f030"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.31
</ab>

<pb facs="#f031"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.32
</ab>

<pb facs="#f032"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.33
</ab>

<pb facs="#f033"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.34
</ab>

<pb facs="#f034"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.35
</ab>

<pb facs="#f035"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.36
</ab>

<pb facs="#f036"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.37
</ab>

<pb facs="#f037"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.38
</ab>

<pb facs="#f038"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.39
</ab>

<pb facs="#f039"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.40
</ab>

<pb facs="#f040"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.41
</ab>

<pb facs="#f041"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.42
</ab>

<pb facs="#f042"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.43
</ab>

<pb facs="#f043"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.44
</ab>

<pb facs="#f044"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.45
</ab>

<pb facs="#f045"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.46
</ab>

<pb facs="#f046"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.47
</ab>

<pb facs="#f047"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.48
</ab>

<pb facs="#f048"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.49
</ab>

<pb facs="#f049"/>
<ab>
<lb/>--TEI Translation for Seq.50
</ab>

  </div></body>
      </text>