<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="TEI Tagged Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f010"/>
<ab>
<personalstmt> <!--I, Iz Shields, worked on sequence 11, facsimile 10, of this text.--> </personalstmt>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top"><persName ref="#ortelius">Abraham Orte-</persName></fw>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top"><persName ref="#ortelius">lius</persName> Citizen of <placeName ref="#antwerp">Ant-</placeName></fw>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top"><placeName ref="#antwerp">-werpe</placeName>,and Georgrapher to Philip the</fw>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top">second, King of<placeName ref="#spaine"> Spaine</placeName>, to the cour-</fw>
<lb/><fw type="header" place="top">teous Reader.</fw>
<lb/>
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Seeing, that as I thinke, there is no man, gentle Reader, but knoweth what, 
<lb/>and how great profit the knowledge of Histories doth bring to those which are serious students
<lb/>therein; I doe verily believe and perswade my selfe, that there is almost no man, be it that he
<lb/>have made neuer so little an entrance into the same, and touched them neuer so lightly, that is
<lb/>ignorant how necessary, for the understanding of them aright, the knowledge of </hi>[Geogra-
<lb/>phy]<hi rend="italic"> is, which, in that respect therefore is of some, and not without just cause called The eye 
<lb/>of history. For thou shalt meet with many things in the readings of Histories, (I will not say,
<lb/>almost all) which, except thou have the knowledge of the countreys and places mentioned in
<lb/>them, cannot onely not bee well conceived and understood, but also ost-times they are cleane
<lb/>mistaken and otherwise understood then they ought to bee: which thing commeth to pass in many discourses: but especially
<lb/>in the expeditions and voyages of great Kings, Captaines and Emperours: in the divers and sundry shirftings of Nations
<lb/>from one place to another: and in the traveils and peregrinations of famous men, made into sundry countreys. But seeing
<lb/>that this is a matter which even experience it selfe doeth teach us to be true, there is no reason why I should stand up
<lb/>on the proofe of the same. This so necessary knowledge of </hi>[Geography]<hi rend="italic">, as many worthy and learned men have testified,
<lb/>may very easily be learn'd out of </hi>[Geographical charts]<hi rend="italic"> or Mappes. And when we have acquainted our selves somewhat
<lb/>with the use of these </hi>[Tables]<hi rend="italic"> or Mappes, or have attained thereby to some reasonable knowledge of </hi>[Geography]<hi rend="italic">
<lb/>we shall read, these </hi>[charts]<hi rend="italic"> being placed, as it were certaine glasses before our eye, will the longer be kept in memory, and
<lb/>make the deeper impression in us: by which means it commeth to pass, that now we do seeme to perceive some fruit of that
<lb/>which we have read. I omit here, that the reading of </hi>[Histories]<hi rend="italic"> does both seem to be much more pleasant, and in deed so
<lb/>it is, when the Mappe being layed before our eyes, we may behold things done, or places where they were done, as if they were
<lb/>at this time present and in doing. For how much we are holpen, when as in the Holy Scripture, we read of the journey of the
<lb/> <note type="historical"><!--members of the anchient Hebrew nation.-->Israelites</note>, which they made from </hi><placename ref="#egypt">[Egypt]</placename><hi rend="italic">, through the Red sea, and that same huge Wildernesse, into the land of promise,
<lb/>when as looking upon the Mappe of </hi><placename ref="#palestina">[Palestina]</placename><hi rend="italic">, we doe almost aswell see it as if we were there, I think any student in Divini-
<lb/>tie, or that History hath st made trial. Which things being so, how much those which are students and lovers of </hi>[Histories]<hi rend="italic">
<lb/>are cornbred, hindred and stayd, yea, &amp; many times, even while they are in their race and continued course, drawne backe, it is
<lb/>an easie matter to conceive, when either the description of all countreys cannot be gotten, or if they may be gotten, they are dea-
<lb/>rer then that every mans money will reach and attaine unto especially those that are but poore, or none of the wealthiest.
<lb/>For there are many that are much delighted with </hi>[Geography]<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>[Chorography]<hi rend="italic">, and especially with Mappes or Tables con-
<lb/>tayning the plots and descriptions of Countreys, such as there are many now adayes extant and every where to be sold: Be
<lb/>because that either they have not that, that should buy them; or if they have so much as they are worth, yet they will not lay it
<lb/>out, they neglect them, neither do they any way satisfie themselves. Others there are who when they have that which will buy
<lb/>them, would very willingly lay out the money, were it not that by reason of the narrownesse of the rooms and places, broad
<lb/>and large Mappes cannot be opened or spread, that every thing in them may easily and well be seene and discern'd. For, that
<lb/>I may speake that which is the trueth, those great and large </hi>[Geographical]<hi rend="italic"> Maps or Charts, which are folded or rowl'd up,
<lb/>are not so commodious; not when any thing is peraduenture read in them, so easie to be look'd upon. And be that will in or-
<lb/>der hang them all along upon a wall, had need have not only a very large &amp; wide house, but even a Princess gallery or spacious
<lb/>Theatre. This I having of unmade trial of, I began to bethinke my selfe, what means might be found to redresse these discom-
<lb/>modities, which I have spoken of, and either to make them somewhat lesse, or, if possibly might bee, to take them all cleane
<lb/>away. And at length me thought it might be done by that means which we have obscured and set downe in this our booke, to
<lb/>which I earnestly with that every student would afford a place in his Library, amongst the rest of his books.
<lb/>	But that thou mayest the better understand, what it is that we have done in this our Theater, and what it is that thou
<lb/>must expect and looke for in the same; I thinke it not amisse in few words briefly here to declare unto the. First
<lb/>												     		my</hi>
</ab>

</div></body></text>