<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="TEI Tagged Transcription"><body><div><pb facs="#f012"/>
<ab>
<personalstmt><!--Transcribed and encoded Seq. 13/f012 - Valerie Hernandez FSU 28'--></personalstmt>
<lb/> tongue, ( to wit, <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>, <placeName ref="#transsyluania">Transsyluania</placeName>,<placeName ref="#polonia"> Polonia</placeName>, <placeName ref="#scandia">Scandia</placeName>, and <placeName ref="#rusia">Rusia</placeName>.) Thus hausing finished <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>, we come vn-
<lb/>to the <placeName ref="#isthmus">Isthmus</placeName> or <placeName ref="#straight-land">Straight-land</placeName>, which is betweene the head of the <placeName ref="#river-tanais">River Tanais</placeName> and the <placeName ref="#north-sea">North sea</placeName>, which is in deed the
<lb/>bound of <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName> and <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName> : from it we step into <placeName ref="#asia">Asia</placeName>. Which, after we have a while beheld, we left, and so passed into <placeName ref="#africa">Afri-
<lb/>ca</placeName>, by the <placeName ref="#streights">Streights</placeName>, or narrow piece of the <placeName ref="#mainland">Mainland</placeName>, which runneth between the <placeName ref="#bay-of-arabia">Bay of Arabia</placeName>, and the <placeName ref="#gulfe-of-damiata">gulfe of Damiata</placeName>,
<lb/>(Sirbonus Lacus) made by the ouerflowing of the <placeName ref="#midland-sea">Midland-sea</placeName>. From thence passing through <placeName ref="#egypt">Egypt</placeName> and <placeName ref="#barbary">Barbary</placeName> wee
<lb/>came vnto the <placeName ref="#streights-of-gibraltar">Streights of Gibraltar</placeName>, which we crossed, and at the length came home againe to our owne natiue countrey from
<lb/>whence we first set foote; like vnto a trauailer or a Pilgrime, which hath viewed and trauailed through many and sundry
<lb/>seuerall Nations and Countreys, pasing out of one into another, orderly as they lay and we situate one by another, ouer-
<lb/>skipping none, at last returneth lasely and ioyfully from whence he first set foorth.
<lb/> Thus farre of the Mappes themselues: Now let vs speake a word or two of the backside of the same. Because we thought
<lb/>it would be a thing nothing pleasing to the Reader or Beholder, to see the backsides of the leaues altogether bare and empty;
<lb/>we determined there to make a certaine briefe and short declaration and Historical discourse of euery Mappe, in the same
<lb/>manner and order as we said we obserued in the Mappes themselues; omitting nor concealing any mans name, that we had oc-
<lb/>casion to vse. Moreouer to these also we have added a Table of the names of all the Authors, that euer wee knew or had;
<lb/>out of which, those that are so disposed, may fetch a more ample and larger <unclear reason="faded">[discowse]</unclear> and description of the seurall Countreys
<lb/>handled by them.  Wherefore the students of Geography shall haue here, in the Authours thus named in order, and in the 
<lb/>Catalogue of the Authours of the Geographicall Tables or Mappes, which we have set before this our worke, and lastly in 
<lb/>these Tables themselues, a certaine shoppe, as it were, furnished with all kinde of instruments necessarily required in such 
<lb/>like business : out of which, if peraduenture there may seeme any thing wanting, in his iudgement , either to be finishing of 
<lb/>any Booke of that argument, or more fuller descriptions of any Countreys whatsoeuer, very easily, or in deed without any la-
<lb/>bour at all be may see, from whence it may be and by be fetched.
<lb/>	These things they are which I thought good to admonish the Reader of. It remaineth now, that wee doe entreate every 
<lb/>man, to take this our labour and entertaine it, with no other minde then it was by vs both begunne and finished, at the length 
<lb/>set out and Imprinted. Farewell, and wish well to<persName ref="#francis-hogenberg">Francis Hogenberg</persName>, <persName ref="#ferdinand">Ferdinand</persName>, and <persName ref="#ambrofe-arfen">Ambrofe Arfen</persName>, by whose skil-
<lb/>full bands and extraordinary great paines and diligence almost all these Mappes were engrauen and cut.
<lb/>	From <placeName ref="#antwerp">Antwerp</placeName>, this present yeere <date when="1570">1570</date>.
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>			THE
</ab>

</div></body></text>